<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-22T13:53:05-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alexis’ Journal</title><subtitle>Unscripted speech, premeditated thought.</subtitle><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><entry><title type="html">sacred pain</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/21/poetry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sacred pain" /><published>2022-07-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/07/21/poetry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/21/poetry.html">&lt;p&gt;Your servility is necessary&lt;br /&gt;
So they tell me&lt;br /&gt;
There is no alternative&lt;br /&gt;
So they tell me&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A master for your home, a master outside your home&lt;br /&gt;
One for every place you live&lt;br /&gt;
We own the land under you and the sky above&lt;br /&gt;
One for every moment alive&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Possessed — “not me, but it in me” —&lt;br /&gt;
I see you walk around&lt;br /&gt;
Phantoms speak through you, friend&lt;br /&gt;
They weigh your eyes to the ground&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I want to ask you a question, but it comes out a scream&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Is this inescapable?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
        This invisible fist around our throats?&lt;br /&gt;
            Is another world really — unattainable?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I’m not an oracle&lt;br /&gt;
So don’t ask me to plan it all out&lt;br /&gt;
Conditions, not conclusions&lt;br /&gt;
But I have a magic hex for you, a wilderness-born shout&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Your face turns pale, I see it&lt;br /&gt;
A rain of ash; smoke in the sky; we’ll take them to account&lt;br /&gt;
It’s okay to be afraid, we all are&lt;br /&gt;
But is this pain any less fearful?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="anarchism" /><category term="poetry" /><summary type="html">Your servility is necessary So they tell me There is no alternative So they tell me A master for your home, a master outside your home One for every place you live We own the land under you and the sky above One for every moment alive Possessed — “not me, but it in me” — I see you walk around Phantoms speak through you, friend They weigh your eyes to the ground I want to ask you a question, but it comes out a scream     Is this inescapable?         This invisible fist around our throats?             Is another world really — unattainable? I’m not an oracle So don’t ask me to plan it all out Conditions, not conclusions But I have a magic hex for you, a wilderness-born shout Your face turns pale, I see it A rain of ash; smoke in the sky; we’ll take them to account It’s okay to be afraid, we all are But is this pain any less fearful?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Power and Hierarchy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/18/power-and-hierarchy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Power and Hierarchy" /><published>2022-07-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/07/18/power-and-hierarchy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/18/power-and-hierarchy.html">&lt;p&gt;Identifying inequalities of power, instances of domination which creates the space for hierarchies and other forms of authority and subordination, is one of the cornerstones anarchist political and social theory. In order to fight back against something, after all, you have to be able to identify it. I began this project from an unorthodox angle in my account of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/07/10/anarchic-encounter.html&quot;&gt;anarchic encounter&lt;/a&gt;, but I think a few words (at least) are necessary concerning the nature of hierarchies, authority, domination, subordination, and power-over; after all, these are the structural factors which either create the space for, or preclude, the anarchic encounter, and which my theory of justice-as-balance is linked to, as a sort of test for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I jump in, however, I need to set the table — elaborate on some core concepts of my social critique in general, and relate them to this project of understanding power and hierarchy specifically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like my conception of justice itself, my conception of hierarchy (and henceforth also authority and subordination, which should be read implicitly whenever I mention it from now on) is not one based on a set of rigid rules or relations which are prohibited in the case of hierarchy just as they are prescribed in the case of justice. Hierarchy wears as many faces as there are human faces, as many shapes as there are places and times in the world where people interact. It is one of the most versatile things in existence. It is a description of a social relationship, and human social relationships are infinitely, fractally complex, an interplay between the endless subtle variety and detail of objective states of the world, and the infinite nuance of subjectivity, perception, and language. In fact, the existence of hierarchy is ultimately a subjective phenomenon, created by the &lt;em&gt;feelings&lt;/em&gt; of those involved — their feelings of choice or lack of choice, which motivate their actions with respect to one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might sound unsettling, but it’s okay to leave wiggle room, exceptions, spaces for exploration and situational decisions and subjectivity, in things like this. Social science is broad, deep, and ever-shifting. I think Wittgenstein’s concept of &lt;a href=&quot;http://fs2.american.edu/dfagel/www/Class%20Readings/Wittgenstein/Philosophical%20Investigations%20\(1st%20100\).html#65&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;family resemblance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is something especially useful to invoke here — I can present a sort of general “example” of a lot of things that I consider instances of hierarchy by giving an abstract account, but specific instances are going to be related to this in different ways than each other or even only transitively related to the examples I give, related to each other and then some of their number related to the example. Indeed, there might even be tensions or contradictions between specific instances, even as they are related to each other or related to other common instances as well. Thus there is ultimately no essence to these things at all, no necessary and sufficient conditions that make something hierarchy or not-hierarchy, nor any “central example” that all other examples are directly related to even in diverse ways. Just the presence of a resemblance between one instance and another instance, in a criss-crossing quilt of such resemblances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any attempt to come up with a complete account of any ethical concept, such as justice, self-defense, hierarchy, or whatever else you please, is bound to fall afoul of exceptions, which one is either then forced to accept — making that account a sacred idea that you bow down to, over and above your own intuitions, feelings, and needs in the moment regarding specific matters — or which one is forced to accommodate by adding ever more epicycles to the theory until it is basically no guide at all (the way that guides is not the constant way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless I think it is worth taking a stab at it. Not as a complete description, but as a sort of &lt;em&gt;generalized example&lt;/em&gt; which can serve as something to build a proper form of family resemblance off of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coercion&quot;&gt;Coercion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s begin with a basic concept: &lt;strong&gt;coercion&lt;/strong&gt;. Someone is coerced into making a choice when their list of acceptable alternative choices is so restricted as to make that choice the only acceptable one, or at least one of very few acceptable alternatives, especially when these choices themselves are not something one would choice were their choices not as restricted (when the choice is not choiceworthy in itself and is even an unnecessarily poor means of achieving its end). In other words, one can say one’s choice to do something is less free the less freedom remains to you should you make each one of the alternative choices available to you, and still less free if the best choice you have leaves you little freedom as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an analogy, I am less free in my choice of direction if, proceeding down a tunnel, I come to a fork, where one path continues on (if perhaps narrower), while the other ventures on a little way and then ends in a dead end. Likewise, if, continuing down the narrower tunnel, as I proceed, I find that I have fewer new branches to go down than I did in the tunnels I left behind, I am, again, less free, because my freedom of movement is more restricted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might notice at this point that this account of coercion implies that &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathyreisenwitz.substack.com/p/consent-is-non-binary&quot;&gt;coercion is a spectrum&lt;/a&gt; — the list of acceptable choices can vary in length (or they can even have no physical choice at all in extreme cases), the relative acceptability of the choices can change in degree, and the choices that are available to you in the future after you make the choice currently at hand might change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, this account of coercion implies that whether coercion is present or not is up to the person who is &lt;em&gt;in the situation in question&lt;/em&gt; — it is at least partially subjective! After all, how much someone is coerced into a choice is dependent not on the objective existence of viable alternatives or the objective freedom that different choices would allow in the future, as if we were able to somehow have insight into those alternate universes; it is dependent on the &lt;em&gt;perceived&lt;/em&gt; choices, or lack thereof, and their &lt;em&gt;perceived&lt;/em&gt; quality! This intuitively makes sense: if someone holds a gun to my head and tells me to do something, I am coerced into doing it even if, unbeknownst to me, the gun isn’t loaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should also be noted that coercion can be achieved actively, by the person benefiting from the coerced choice, as in the case of making someone do something by putting a gun to their head, or &lt;em&gt;passively&lt;/em&gt;, by merely taking advantage of someone’s already dire circumstances, their lack of alternative options. In either case the result is the same, and in many such cases the surrounding conditions which enable such “passive” coercion are in fact artificial and constructed for the benefit of the person taking advantage, and as such the lines between these two are also often blurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that saying that coercion is subjective and exists on a spectrum is not to deny that coercion not used in self-defense can’t be distinctly pointed out, referred-to, and understood, or can’t be treated as undesirable. This fear that if something is complex, multifaceted, and has elements of subjectivity in it, it must be invalid and disappear under investigation is simply the ludicrous result of modernist bastardizations of scientism and positivism, the hundred-times picked over crumbs of our “Enlightenment inheritance.” We can still understand when something is clearly taking place from an external point of view by analyzing the factors at play, the structures, systems, and individuals which compose them; we can analyze the severity of what is taking place and decide for ourselves what is too severe; we can &lt;em&gt;ask&lt;/em&gt; the people involved and understand and learn from their perspectives. After all, one can turn to a friend and ask them what happened somewhere, and believe them, without a scientific investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a certain extent, in a technical sense, we all exercise “coercion,” because self-defense does exactly what I described above: it makes people that want to hurt us not do so by using violence or the threat of it. Likewise, we “force” people to deal with us fairly, instead of dominating us or being tyrannical over us, through the threat of using violence if they don’t. But this is merely the absolutism of the free absolute, the unique, which defends its own. It is in fact, in a sense, the precondition for the anarchic encounter at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crucial difference between these kinds of “egalitarian,” unobjectionable uses of “coercion” and coercion exercised in a way that leads to power over others, hierarchy, domination, etc. (which is typically what people are referring to when they call something coercion) is that in the second case, it’s aggressive interference — marching into someone’s life and telling them what to do and not to do when otherwise they would’ve had nothing to do with you, or taking control of the things they use to maintain their lives — while in the more common case it’s a reaction, it’s defensive — we are controlling their lives in a sense, but only to get them to stop dominating and controlling ours. I don’t want to become my landlord’s landlord, I just want to get him to stop being my landlord, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether someone is controlling others only to not themselves be controlled, or controlling others for the purpose merely of controlling them is a detailed, case by case thing, an area that I leave up to judgment, although I don’t think it’s very often a difficult thing to determine — just ask whose life is effected more by the use of coercion. If what you want to control effects my life more than yours, then you are trying to control me — if your life more than mine, you are more interested in controlling yourself. Thus for instance if someone is trying to outlaw public displays of affection on the part of queer people because they don’t want to see it, they are trying to control queer people, because that effects queer people’s lives far more than their own (not having to see something you can easily ignore, versus not being able to express affection toward a loved one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key here, ultimately, seems to be whether something is &lt;em&gt;invasive&lt;/em&gt; or not, just as Tucker says in his writings — but that itself seems to boil down to equality of a sort, so, the key to justice remains equality, as Proudhon thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;power-over-domination&quot;&gt;Power-Over (Domination)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next concept is &lt;strong&gt;power over&lt;/strong&gt;, or domination. Power-over is constituted in the ability to get an advantage over someone else — to get what &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; want out of some interaction or relationship with much less significant concern for the interests of the others involved. Power over someone or some situation lets you set the terms of a bargain unilaterally, or nearly so, to extract more out of the relationship than the other parties to a relationship get, makes one party more beholden to the interests of the other, and so on. Power-over is usually only possible when coercion is forcing people to interact with the person who wants it, so that they can’t simply reject a relation which is inequitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One example is, for instance, bosses who have to care very little about the happiness of the employees under them, can ignore employee input, etc, while the employees have to worry a lot about displeasing their boss all the time, because they might lose their job, which is a seriously bad option much of the time. Another example is the classic example of capitalist profit: since capitalists own the means of production and people need to eat, they have extremely unequal bargaining power and so can get much more out of the deal than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power-over is distinct from “mere” power because we &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; want, and possess, power to one degree or another. This is implicit in all of my previous discussion in this essay already — we all possess a will to power, and varying degrees of ability to project that power into our lives and the world around us. The more capacity we have to express our will to power, the more self-actualized we are capable of being, and so empowerment itself is neither good nor evil, and when considered in isolation can indeed be a great, beautiful thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power only becomes dangerous to anarchism, a servant of hierarchy, when there is an inequality of power between those who have competing interests in some affair. That is when power &lt;em&gt;over&lt;/em&gt; someone is possible: when you exercise your greater power to get what you want in a situation where someone else is effected by what you are doing and has interests contrary to yours, but can’t stand against you. Therefore, part of the project of anarchism is to empower everyone &lt;em&gt;equally&lt;/em&gt;, so that everyone has power, which means that no one has power &lt;em&gt;over&lt;/em&gt; anyone else. There are many ways of doing that — a cultural commitment to leveling mechanisms that ensure that leadership and authority are at most temporary tools, decentralization of systems and distribution of decision-making power, providing support and mutual aid for people to multiply their power, proper tools for self-defense and security, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is opposed to the statist solution to power-over, which is to equally disempower everyone, subjecting them all to the same laws, rules, and regulations, so that they are all equally powerless in the face of forces that decide from outside what conditions must be like — a self-defeating notion because it inherently requires an &lt;em&gt;even greater&lt;/em&gt; power-over, which then creates exactly the sort of domination and hierarchy, exactly the sort of power-over, that one sought to avoid in the first place. Thus we go from the occasional &lt;a href=&quot;https://thewhyaxis.substack.com/p/cops-still-take-more-stuff-from-people&quot;&gt;thief or burglar to asset forfeiture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again the key seems to be equality and balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hierarchy-and-authority&quot;&gt;Hierarchy and Authority&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, finally, we arrive at &lt;strong&gt;hierarchy&lt;/strong&gt;: hierarchy is the reification and perpetuation of power and coercion. Hierarchy, and its accompanying authority, takes relationships of power-over and legitimizes them, by constructing some sustaining myth about how they are inevitable, inescapable, good, or necessary. By this means, relations of power which are ultimately arbitrary, created by happenstance or particular contextual or environmental factors, are transformed into things that are preserved and actively perpetuated by both the people that benefit from them and those that are on the losing end of them. Thus we get the divine right of kings, social contract theory, natural law, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once legitimating myths concerning these relations of power are created, the processes of perpetuation and preservation of these power relations start to turn into patterns, and then these patterns themselves are reified into myths, traditions, norms, and, eventually, laws, further feeding the cycle. After that, the hierarchy is reified (thing-ified) and made into a solid, stable entity both conceptually and materially. The concept of the hierarchy is turned into something separate from the people and actions that actualize it into something with its own force, its own wants, needs, and obligations, while that concept is also given tangible reality which further perpetuates the myth of the concept’s independent reality. Thus hierarchies can be understood in terms of the relatively stable patterns of behavior that they engender, distorting the social fabric around themselves, and also the physical, material changes they make to our reality: government buildings, road blocks, fences, ghettos, police cars. All of these things reinforce the hierarchy, make it seem all the more just &lt;em&gt;part of reality itself&lt;/em&gt;, all the more inescapable and inevitable, in a feedback loop of self-creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, once a relationship of power has been turned into a hierarchy, legitimized, and reified into a set of institutions, where this vicious cycle of self-reinforcement can begin, problems of coordination and collective action become serious. If a system has overwhelming power behind it, so that no single individual could stand completely against it for long, it becomes necessary to coordinate action; the problem is, such action is lethal and also largely pointless on the part of each individual, so each individual needs to be able to guarantee that the others will join in, and this can be difficult because there is an incentive for each individual to defect to save their own hides or even make a deal with the powers-that-be. How to resist this problem and powerful hierarchies themselves is far outside my wheelhouse, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is by no means a complete account. Instead, it is a hasty sketch which grew out of a flash of inspiration while writing another essay. Nevertheless, I think it offers some useful conceptual tools in an accessible package and perhaps has some unique ideas about how to construct a framework through which to understand and critique power and hierarchy. That’s all I aim to do, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="ethics" /><category term="anarchism" /><summary type="html">Identifying inequalities of power, instances of domination which creates the space for hierarchies and other forms of authority and subordination, is one of the cornerstones anarchist political and social theory. In order to fight back against something, after all, you have to be able to identify it. I began this project from an unorthodox angle in my account of the anarchic encounter, but I think a few words (at least) are necessary concerning the nature of hierarchies, authority, domination, subordination, and power-over; after all, these are the structural factors which either create the space for, or preclude, the anarchic encounter, and which my theory of justice-as-balance is linked to, as a sort of test for.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Is A Woman?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/11/woman.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Is A Woman?" /><published>2022-07-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/07/11/woman</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/11/woman.html">&lt;p&gt;Since Matt Walsh’s transphobic ‘documentary’ &lt;em&gt;What Is A Woman?&lt;/em&gt; was released, I’ve been seeing a lot of people, even allies and members of the LGBT community, reiterating this question. What &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a woman? Just what does that &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt;? Well, I’ve got a simple, compact answer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;b style=&quot;font-size: 22px&quot;&gt;A woman is someone who identifies with womanhood.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t go beyond that for anyone in general conversation, certainly not with someone who asks that question as a challenge or in a “debate me bro” way, because actually elaborating on what you mean by that will take a lot of time and they’ll be likely to just dismiss you as dodging the question or being a post-modern neo-Marxist or whatever the fuck as soon as you start to take longer than a few seconds to answer. Because to them, everything has to have a simple, rigid answer, everything has to fit into neat little boxes and pre-defined roles. Subjects can’t be genuinely complex and sometimes fuzzy and subjective or relative for them, they start out with a presupposition that all that kind of stuff is “woke nonsense.” This is the deep-seated anti-intellectualism of the right that serves as a defense mechanism for having to change their minds. That’s why Matt Walsh’s documentary is so disingenuous to the core — he dismisses anything that sounds complicated or vague to him because ultimately it isn’t meant to be a measure of who can actually answer, or who’s right, it’s a measure of his own low comprehension abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, let’s dig into the meaning behind this a little deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different ways in which (or reasons why) one can identify with womanhood — even among cis women opinions vary, and in feminist philosophy it has been a hotly debated subject for at least a century, not to mention that the concept itself is socioculturally dependent, and is imbued with deep history — but that’s okay, the important thing is that people who identify as women will typically tell you if you ask (that’s why the simple way to answer is “whoever identifies as a woman”) and also use (some of) the culturally constructed ways that we have of ‘performing womanhood’ to broadcast their identity because, typically, it both expresses their inward identification with womanhood (and so makes them happy) and helps their identity be recognized by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A woman is not a woman by virtue of this outward performance any more than house with a different coat of paint is a different house, because this outward appearance can always be taken away by force or circumstance, or merely not be of interest to them, and exactly what looks “enough like a woman” or even “looks like a woman” in the first place is subjective and blurry, but it is one indicator of that inward identification with the female gender. So, it is this identification of one’s ideal self with womanhood that makes the difference to my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, to determine what constitutes “womanhood,” or to identify a woman, or even use the word “woman,” we don’t even need to come up with a list of necessary and sufficient conditions — an essence — that is common to all women! If you think about it, we don’t do that for most of the words we use: instead, we have examples of what to use the word on, drawn from our experience using language with other people, and we consider the word to apply to anything that bears a resemblance to those examples. In that fashion we are able to productively use the word and understand what it means in a broad, holistic sense, without ever needing to come up with a set of properties that everything the word applies to shares: each thing that the word applies to can be related to other things the word applies to in different ways, creating an overlapping, crisscrossing network of &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; relations between each example of the word, where some things are even only related to others through a chain of intermediary relations (like the transitive property in math).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The things a word applies to will all have a sort of “family resemblance”: like a family, there may not even be one thing that every member shares in common, but different things (hair, nose, face, eyes, gait, accent) are relatively alike between different members of the family, in different ways. Not only that, but the borders can be fuzzy, because how much something resembles another is up for debate sometimes — it’s more a relative question of whether something is more like an example of one word, or more like an example of another, because almost everything has a commonality with anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of that doesn’t matter, though, because exactitude isn’t actually a bar to being able to use a word in a language-game and have people understand what you mean. I can say “stand roughly there” or “give me a red square” and you can do as I ask without knowing where I want you to stand down to the inch or knowing exactly which wavelength of light I want the square to be reflecting. Wittgenstein talks about all of this in &lt;a href=&quot;http://fs2.american.edu/dfagel/www/Class%20Readings/Wittgenstein/Philosophical%20Investigations%20\(1st%20100\).html#65&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Philosophical Investigations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in great detail, presenting counter arguments to various objections you’re likely to hear, and I highly recommend reading it. It is dry, but clearly written and, to me, was engaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, when categorizing &lt;em&gt;humans&lt;/em&gt;, often times trying to essentialize us or taxonomize actually ends up doing violence to us far more than actually improving our understanding of ourselves and our (social) reality. After all, even in biology, taxonomy is a discipline with fluid categories, fuzzy definitions, many disputes and open questions, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/06/05/dont-fix-us.html&quot;&gt;numerous exceptions&lt;/a&gt;. That is all the more true with respect to humans, with the added difficulty that there are social realities we have to take into account, and also that we often take our constructed, limited, and non-objective categories as not only absolute, but also as having normative implications, implications which can seriously cause harm to those who aren’t captured accurately by those categorizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me what’s important about being a woman is the family resemblance between what women identify with, how we conceptualize our ideal selves in relation to others who also identify with womanhood, and how we want to be in the world, both personally and socially. This is what is typically termed one’s “gender identity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a natural question might be — aren’t we reinforcing gender roles by identifying womanhood with cultural constructs? Not at all. The difference between what I do and what your average bioessentialist or conservative traditionalist does is that I’m querying the internal sense of identity of the person in question — I’m asking them whether, to what degree, and in what ways they identify with womanhood, and letting their answer dictate what I believe about them. So a woman who dresses in a masculine way, has a career, has had a hysterectomy, and has no children or husband remains a woman for me because she wants to be a woman in one way or another, wants to exist and be acknowledged as one, whereas a particularly angry traditionalist might deny her her womanhood — or, conversely, a man with long hair who is stereotypically feminine remains a man so long as he wishes to remain one, unlike the schoolyard bully who might call a boy a girl for having long hair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise I do not take &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; conceptions of what it means to be a woman, or my ideas about it, as universal or normative: I do not tell a woman who doesn’t relate to womanhood like I do that they are wrong, or failing at womanhood. I do not say to a woman who lies farther along the family resemblance between women, or perhaps at the fuzzy border, that she should move ‘more toward being a woman,’ because she is equally a woman to me, because she still shares that resemblance and, through the transitive property, is related thus to all other women, and there &lt;em&gt;is no center, is no essence&lt;/em&gt; to womanhood for me! Crucially, you will find, that for everyone who truly is a member of their gender, if you deny them their gender they will protest, and if you ask them — and they have time to think about it and a space to answer without feeling judged — they will give you an answer about how they relate to their gender. And that is all that is necessary. For me, womanhood is about the feeling of kinship and identification with other women, the way I want my body to be and the way I want to be treated and exist and present myself in the social world. For my best friend, it’s about wanting her body to be as female as possible (this is why I call myself transgender and she prefers transsexual). But these are equally valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize — the point is not to abolish identities. Let people who enjoy their identities revel in them, be proud of them, love them, find common cause and community through them, connect to history and literature and poetry through them! The point is to abolish normativity — telling people what identity they should have, or how they have to fulfill that identity. Let each person find their own &lt;em&gt;dao&lt;/em&gt;. This doesn’t just go for womanhood and manhood, either. This framework also allows for the construction of new genders, by creating new sociocultural clusters of associations, roles, presentations, expressions, histories, and identifications with others, to name just a few dimensions along which gender can be understood, or the mixing of manhood and womanhood, or even the rejection of all gender entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I meant above about trying to force people into essentialized categories ultimately being something that does violence to at least a few of them, maybe all of them to a certain degree. When it comes to matters of social existence and identity, subjectivity and phenomenological experience, complexity and nuance, must be given their due — humans are complex creatures, after all, and I personally wouldn’t have it any other way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="transgender" /><category term="lgbt" /><summary type="html">Since Matt Walsh’s transphobic ‘documentary’ What Is A Woman? was released, I’ve been seeing a lot of people, even allies and members of the LGBT community, reiterating this question. What is a woman? Just what does that mean? Well, I’ve got a simple, compact answer:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Justice and the Anarchic Encounter: Synthesizing Neo-Proudhonian Social Science and Egoism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/10/anarchic-encounter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Justice and the Anarchic Encounter: Synthesizing Neo-Proudhonian Social Science and Egoism" /><published>2022-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/07/10/anarchic-encounter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/10/anarchic-encounter.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Another world is possible” every time equal uniques, free absolutes, meet on a terrain shaped by any number of histories but no structures of authority. — Shawn P. Wilbur, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libertarian-labyrinth.org/contrun/the-anatomy-of-the-encounter/&quot;&gt;“The Anatomy of the Encounter”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;authors-note&quot;&gt;Author’s Note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As has become somewhat of a theme, perhaps even a requirement, for this recent spate of better-quality postings beginning with “Vision of An Anarchist Society,” instead of sitting down to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Write About Something&lt;/code&gt; because I want to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Build A System&lt;/code&gt; and building a system &lt;em&gt;requires&lt;/em&gt; writing on certain subjects — instead of, in other words, treating my blog posts as chapters in a gigantic book that I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to write to “get it out of the way” — I’ve waited until I feel writing on this subject welling up inside me. Until writing on it feels natural, an act of outpouring, as if I was already going to write on this, whether I made the choice or not. I spent two days pondering what I should write about, feeling out all the different topics that have been occupying my mind in the past few months, turning them about in my hands and inspecting them carefully, like fruit, to see which was just ripe enough. I waited until this subject was on the &lt;em&gt;tip of my tongue&lt;/em&gt; to write about it. In other words, I followed &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/anna-ronan-anarchism-as-a-spiritual-practice&quot;&gt;wu wei&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I find myself back to staring into the depths of the subject of an anarchist conception of ‘justice’, embodied in a particular kind of relationship, for the first time in six months and three weeks. I’ve tried this project twice before: once, in the fury of inspiration and shocking, icy, firey &lt;em&gt;realization&lt;/em&gt;, which led me to produce “Two Principles,” a work so deeply flawed in so many ways, so full of both my old kinds of thinking &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; my new kinds, that I’m still slowly unpacking and developing everything that was good in it even now; then a second time, in a confused, contemplative, groping essay that represented me trying to really wrestle with and internalize what I’d realized through discussions with someone who was very influential to me at the time. This time, I hope to take the months of deep thinking and experience, and far-ranging reading, that I’ve been carrying out, and apply it to producing something clearer, cleaner, and more coherent than what I’ve written before on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the fundamental characteristic features of anarchism? I think that anarchism is fundamentally defined by a single thing — an opposition to subordination, domination, or hierarchies of power or authority — from which two other things flow naturally, and without which that ‘single thing’ would be incompletely expressed: an opposition to governmentalism (the principle which tries to govern people’s actions or lives) and by extension the state, and a positive love and hope for the possibilities that human beings can create when liberated from hierarchy and government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One crucial part of understanding anarchism, in my view, is understanding its projectual-relational dimension: understanding what relations, both singular and ongoing, between both individuals and collectivities, might look like when taking place in an essentially anarchic manner. This is something which lies at a nexus of sorts at the heart of egoist anarchism itself: an emergent anarchism that is not a prescription of certain social structures, but just what results, in all its plurality and multiplicity, from &lt;em&gt;conditions of anarchism&lt;/em&gt;. Although it won’t have much specific content — it is almost another non-concept like ‘the unique’ and ‘self-interest’ — this can give us some conception of what, although opposed to fixed ideas, we might still colloquially term ‘justice’ — of what we are fighthing &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purpose of pursuing such an understanding, I have found that using the lens of Neo-Proudhonian social science, which sees society as an eternal, ongoing process of balancing conflicting and interpenetrating forces, where the greatest liberty is found precisely at the moment where these contradictory forces are most balanced, to the egoist framework which already sees society as an eternal war between the will to power of each individual, has been extremely fruitful for me. The purpose of this essay is to share that odd synthesis, which I see every so often among other anarchists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make an important clarification, I am not interested in producing rules for the outcomes of justice, whether rules of thumb, or mathematical equations, or categorical imperatives, or tables of virtues and vices, or natural laws. I am interested, instead, in conditions, not conclusions — I am interested in understanding what sorts of arrangements might naturally flow from what is already quintessentially anarchist: the &lt;em&gt;anarchic encounter&lt;/em&gt;, a meeting of two or more equals — Unique ones who accept neither master nor higher power nor sacred idea — on a playing field shaped by all manner of history and circumstance, but no hierarchies, no governments, no authority, no state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is the embodiment of the anarchist commitment to eliminating &lt;em&gt;archos&lt;/em&gt;, the anarchic encounter represents everything we fight for in the social world, and, as such, it has a direct link to what sorts of arrangements we might find ‘just.’ With that in mind, it is useful to ask: what sorts of arrangements between individuals could (or might tend to) arise from actual conditions free from hierarchy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is with reasoning substantially similar to this that Proudhon dismisses the social contract theory of property: had conditions of equality and universal consent really obtained when such a contract was formed, the result, too, would have had to be equality:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But I wish that this consent, of which so much is made, had been given, either tacitly or formally. What would have been the result? Evidently, the surrenders would have been reciprocal; no right would have been abandoned without the receipt of an equivalent in exchange. We thus come back to equality again… so that, after having justified property by universal consent, that is, by equality, we are obliged to justify the inequality of conditions by property. Never shall we extricate ourselves from this dilemma. Indeed, if, in the terms of the social compact, property has equality for its condition, at the moment when equality ceases to exist, the compact is broken and all property becomes usurpation. We gain nothing, then, by this pretended consent of mankind. — Proudhon, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/economics/proudhon/property/ch03.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What Is Property?&lt;/em&gt; Chapter II.2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, it is important to remember that if we wish to have an accurate analysis of social justice, we should, unlike &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/rawls/&quot;&gt;Rawls&lt;/a&gt;, reject placing this hypothetical understanding of what free and equal people would do above the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; arrangements free people choose to make, or whether there are real relations of hierarchy and subordination warping the fabric of social reality in a given instance. To do otherwise would be just to reproduce yet another sacred idea. (Nor should we assume that society must be planned, and resources distributed, from the top down by a central committee of such psychologically impossible sock-puppets as those placed behind the veil of ignorance.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how I balance the possible tension between my egoism and a concept of justice. As an egoist I am more than free to have interests regarding things other than myself, and there is no fixed concept of self-interest that must motivate me, only an attentiveness to “the feelings and thoughts that are aroused in me by [things],” and it is true that I sincerely hate living in a society which upholds structures of power over me and those I care about, that stomps us beneath its boot — or does so to anyone, for that matter; I also know that my liberty will never be secure until the power of each is unlocked and the cathedrals of power-over-us are razed to the ground. Interests like these are all equal, whether they regard myself, those I care about, or other people whom I don’t know, as long as they remain &lt;em&gt;my own&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am not altruistic so long as the goal remains my own, and instead of stooping to being the blind means of its fulfillment, I always leave it open to question. My zeal doesn’t, therefore, have to be less than the most fanatical, but at the same time I remain frosty cold against it, unbelieving, and its most implacable enemy; I remain its judge, because I am its owner. — &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/max-stirner-the-unique-and-its-property&quot;&gt;Max Stirner, &lt;em&gt;The Unique and Its Property&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as part of my will to power, I seek to push forward anarchism, as the &lt;em&gt;sine qua non&lt;/em&gt; of the society I wish to live in, and, as part of that, I view justice-as-balance as a thing that is pleasing to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cascade2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Untitled, by Wang Wei&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-anarchic-encounter-and-justice-as-balance&quot;&gt;The Anarchic Encounter and Justice-As-Balance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To return to the subject of the anarchic encounter, now that I’ve outlined what exactly makes it so important, let me have Wilbur speak for me here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[bold is mine] On one level, then, under anarchism we simply see a particular sort of encounter acted out, over and over again: equal individuals meet, find the means to balance their individual interests, and from their association arises something else—a collective something with the potential to emerge as another individual, with interests of its own, which must then figure in &lt;strong&gt;the balancing of interests that is justice&lt;/strong&gt;… Any number of encounters may take place, involving any number of individuals, on any number of scales and creating any number of associations, but the basic elements remain the same. &lt;strong&gt;The social field of play remains level, the status of the individuals—whether self-conscious free absolutes or various sorts of collectivities—remains equal&lt;/strong&gt; before whatever norms and conventions we adopt, and &lt;strong&gt;those norms and conventions always remain subject to critique on the basis of their relationship to the most general, practical sort of equality and justice-balance.&lt;/strong&gt; — Shawn P. Wilbur, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libertarian-labyrinth.org/contrun/summary-notions/&quot;&gt;“Summary Notions”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand why justice-as-balance is so crucial and why, importantly, it is not so much a normative principle as an epiphenomena that results from the interaction of Uniques, let me quote from a different essay of Wilbur’s:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[bold mine] We begin with these free absolutes, these uniques. According to the first, Proudhonian designation, we are dealing with individuals, groups [in Proudhon’s social science, even individual persons are regarded as groups] organized according to an unfolding law of development, but with a consciousness of their nature and a capacity for self-reflection. &lt;strong&gt;They may, on the one hand, be inclined to absolutism, to taking their internal law for the law of the world, but they are also capable of recognizing another like themselves, and understanding that in a world of absolutes either some must be masters of others, or there must be balance&lt;/strong&gt;. With no criterion of certainty for their observations or judgments, beyond the apparently similarity—in this absolutist dimension—of these otherwise unique beings, &lt;strong&gt;with incommensurable experiences and unknowable essences, they find themselves with equality, Proudhon suggests, as the only basis on which to proceed from individual isolation to society&lt;/strong&gt;. — Shawn P. Wilbur, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libertarian-labyrinth.org/contrun/the-anatomy-of-the-encounter/&quot;&gt;“The Anatomy of the Encounter”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words: when someone who refuses to bow to anyone or any thing, not even an abstract idea of justice (perhaps derived from, e.g., natural law) is faced with another such 
indomitable will, they have one choice: to duke it out, face each other down, and see who will ultimately be the more powerful and who will be forced to submit to the other, or to compromise. And of course, any compromise between real equals is almost always going to be a 50-50 compromise — balance — in some crucial way, although perhaps not in the same way each time or in an obvious dimension. Thus justice-as-balance emerges as the &lt;em&gt;resultant indicator&lt;/em&gt; of conditions of anarchy, and gains its value not by being enforced from above, but by being the litmus test for that which we already value: a world where, in Novatore’s words, the rabble have ceased to be rabble, and sprung forth in all their flowering potentiality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that true justice, in the anarchist sense, is not the application of a rigid set of rules for how relations should be organized, but the resolution of conflicts in a way that treats everyone’s interests as equal, arrived at through direct reconciliation between the people in conflict by reasoning together, &lt;em&gt;whatever the outcome&lt;/em&gt;. And this is not an categorical imperative, but a flowering forth of that which I already value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of looking at this is through Stirner’s lens instead of Proudhon’s. While the foregoing discussion has focused on balance because at least some of the interests at play in the anarchic encounter are assumed to be at odds, that is not necessarily the case. Or, at least, it isn’t something we have to focus on to the exclusion of all other kinds of association. When egoists meet and associate, it is of necessity something which must be of benefit to both. The nature of their fluid commitment to only their interests (their &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/anna-ronan-anarchism-as-a-spiritual-practice&quot;&gt;feelings and needs&lt;/a&gt;) ensures that when that association fails to be of utility to any one involved, it will dissolve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our relationship is one of mutuality and reciprocity. We both gain what we desire from our union, and thus are satisfied. We consume, but are also consumed… When we no longer find such an association as beneficial to ourselves we withdraw and end the union. The union only exists at the behest of our own individual power. If we find that we are working towards another’s ends, no longer enjoying oneself, or desiring a new activity—we withdraw—ending our association. — Castanea Dentata, &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/castanea-dentata-the-union-of-egoists&quot;&gt;“The Union of Egoists”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the nature of such a union is that it must be of mutual — in some sense equal — benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/three_perfections.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Three Perfections, by Huang Binhong&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final note on justice-as-balance is necessary. Whether someone’s interests are equally represented and equally cared about, or one interest is subordinated to another and must supplicate it on terms the dominating interest dictates, must be assessed holistically: if we look at anything but the full picture of a relation, things can get confused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can, for instance, we “balance the interests” of a man who wants to murder someone and the person he wants to murder? You can’t half-murder someone, so what are we supposed to do, let the other man beat him up just half as much as would be necessary to kill him? Cut his throat halfway and then take him to the hospital? Not at all. The answer to this question is to repeal the hidden fallacy and widen our scope: if one man gets his way, their interests are equally represented — both go their own ways alive and whole, living their lives as before, assuming there is no prior hierarchy to speak of — while, if the other gets his way, one will have all his interests obliterated without any consideration whatsoever, and one will get everything he wants and go about his day. Thus, the balancing of the interests of both people is actually the denial of the interests of the would-be murderer, because to do otherwise is itself a clear instance of domination, the subordination of one man’s interests to the other’s, and thus balance is found in destroying this domination, and only then can the anarchic encounter emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, equality itself is a slippery thing: one can be equal or unequal along an infinitude of dimensions, so it is crucial not to pick just &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; dimension of equality (equal wages, or equality under the law, for instance) and ignore the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;justice-and-rationality&quot;&gt;Justice and Rationality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conditions of equality, where two Uniques or free absolutes who will not yield to each other meet and decided to cooperate or compromise, to find some mutually beneficial arrangement to either further their common interests or balance their opposing ones, what are the means by which they find such a mutually beneficial balance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One tool might be, as the previous quotes from Wilbur hinted at, the application of norms, conventions, or traditions — knowledge about what worked on previous, sufficiently similar, occasions, and common understandings of what manifestations of equality matter, or what equality even really means. But ultimately, if we’re going to be talking about a seriously &lt;em&gt;anarchic&lt;/em&gt; encounter, where no one is governed by anything and no one submits to any authority but their own, those things are at best tools; the encounter and the individuals in it cannot become the property of these traditions. To quote again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Norms, conventions, rules, laws, rights—no matter what language we use to talk about the more persistent aspects of our mutual self-government, the things that that language represents can never assume any authority in and of themselves… Arguably, that means much more than to say that they must not be backed by state or police powers, violence or the threat of violence. If we accept Proudhon’s summary, it is really a question of preserving in each encounter a sort of positive lawlessness, and, in part, we may do this by acknowledging that each encounter is a new encounter, that there is no ready-made system for projecting ourselves into the future, even just a moment at a time… We pile up knowledge and experience in all of those moments, but nothing is certain… any anarchism worthy of the name is going to be pretty relentlessly suspect of anything that looks like permission or prohibition—both practices which demand some position of authority from which to regulate our encounters in some a priori manner. — Shawn P. Wilbur, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libertarian-labyrinth.org/contrun/summary-notions/&quot;&gt;“Summary Notions”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are rejecting any notion of authority above the parties involved in the anarchic encounter itself, and are choosing traditions or other ideas as they are useful to us instead of assuming that we are bound to any of them, then a process of engaging in dialogue is necessary: the free absolutes who meet in an anarchic encounter need to come to a common understanding, and that can only be achieved through language — communication — and the presentation of ‘reasons,’ although traditional conceptions of capital-R rationality need not be the standard. Thus the outcome of any anarchic encounter is ultimately guided by a participatory, dialogical process of offering reasons, justifications, explanations, experiences, perspectives, and desires, all with the explicit purpose not of meeting any standard, but of making oneself understandable to others and finding common ground and mutual understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is through this process of reasoning together, accepting the incommensurability and equal ‘legitimateness’ of other perspectives and then arriving at common ground if possible anyway, that the hopeful, creative nature of the anarchic encounter is born:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let’s underline again this notion of a society without permission or prohibition, and emphasize that all of our anarchic encounters will require something more of us than just asserting our “rights” or fulfilling our “duties” with regard to one another. Every act of association will involve an act of creation, specifically the creation of some bit of some possible world, and creative acts involve some sort of erotics as much as economics. There is a lot that needs to be looked at with regard to how all this creative stuff plays out, but let’s start by saying that none of the familiar language for it—society, community, market, etc.—gets us too far. — Shawn P. Wilbur, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libertarian-labyrinth.org/contrun/summary-notions/&quot;&gt;“Summary Notions”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is through this notion that a sense of justice as an (in some sense) rational process emerges from a purely egoistic notion of not being willing to subordinate oneself to anything, &lt;em&gt;including&lt;/em&gt; normative accounts of justice or rationality itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this concept of justice has very little positive content — it has as many forms and expressions as there are pairings or groupings of people in existence — but it explicitly provides the form for an anarchic sense of interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve explained the basic concept, there are a few things surrounding it that I want to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;equality-and-collectivity&quot;&gt;Equality and Collectivity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For someone used to thinking in terms of the “greater good” or the “public good” — that is, those poisoned by the mythology of utilitarianism, majoritarian democracy, and liberalism, this focus on treating all of the interests of all of the free absolutes (or Uniques, whichever you prefer) that take part in an anarchic encounter as equal, and focusing on the balance between them, might sound similar to the principle of utility. This leads to a possible question: each individual being equal, shouldn’t the greater number of individuals weigh more in a ‘just’ decision than the lesser?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is fundamentally confused for a few basic reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, for a free absolute to submit their will, power, and interests to the will of a greater number is still a submission, still an imposition of duty, obligation, or subordination, a creation of a hierarchy in which the collectivity has greater weight than the individual or smaller collectivity. This is merely a reproduction of the exact sort of thing the anarchic encounter rejects, and is contrary to its preconditions and the nature of the Unique one: collectivity holds no normative weight for such a one, and any attempt to subordinate or obliterate their interests in service to something else, whether it has more people or less, remains an attempt to subordinate them which they will shrug off with a laugh and defend themselves from. Why should I be subject to the interests of another, simply because they have more people backing them? I don’t want to live in a world like that. I don’t want to agree to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, and crucially, justice-as-balance takes place between interests, not between individuals as such. When balancing between the interests of a collectivity and an individual, there are still only two interests at play: the shared collective interest of the former and the singular, but just as real, interest of the latter. If neither side is required to submit, neither by normative dogma nor by force of arms, then the compromise between them must remain balanced. Equal. Equal consideration, compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, collectivities and individuals are different kinds of entities, even if in Proudhon’s thought they are similar in some ways. Just like the set {1,1,1,1,1} would not be equivalent to the number 5, a collectivity is a kind of absolute, but it is not a Unique nor a free absolute. When there is a collectivity that has shared interests, the interests of that group do not count for more than the interests of any individual, because, instead of being rolled up into a single (somehow more “valuable”) composite individual, treating it like a new entity has come into being instead of what it actually is, which is just a composition of individuals who happen to share a certain interest, each member of that group counts singly against the individual. After all, since each member of the group shares an interest, if that interest is favored over the interest of the other individual, each member of that group has also had their interest dominate at the expense of the other person’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Beureaucrats_at_work.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bureaucrats At Work&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is not a projection of what ‘would’ happen practically speaking, in a sort of ‘state of nature’ vacuum absent anarchist norms or associations or institutions, should the interests of a group come into conflict with an individual — in such a ‘realistic’ case, it might be that the individual would end up just being subordinated to the collectivity, but the point is that that kind of subordination is what we are wishing to avoid, by positing the anarchic encounter as the template for interactions between free people, and so the trick is to be able to identify when what we want happens and when it doesn’t, and try to build structures that resist this sort of ‘state of nature’ attack on the individual. Which leads me to the final section of this essay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-power-and-justice&quot;&gt;Conclusion: Power and Justice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of this picture of justice-as-balance and the continual, crossing and crisscrossing, ongoing, distributed interaction between free absolutes who compromise and engage in dialogue with each other and create overlapping yet separate collectivities for different purposes and needs, emerges a picture of the social world in which each person asserts their will to power — their innate desire to express themselves, both in their own person, and through impressing their personality and interests on the world around them — and expands the horizon of their &lt;em&gt;property&lt;/em&gt; as far is it will go, until that horizon meets with the horizons of others and they stop at the limits of others’ will to power, bleeding into each other and finding a mutual balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is the nexus where many conceptions of anarchy meet: the eternal social war that Novatore spoke about, where each person is the judge of what they possess; the jovial, sociable, unscrupulous egoism of Stirner’s union; Proudhon’s justice-as-balance and rationality; the aristocratic value of might that Nietzsche brings to the table; and finally everyone’s right to “beautiful, radiant things” that Goldman so desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can create a social world in which the anarchic encounter is made possible, and in turn gives birth to a social reality in which all of these things turn out to mean the same thing in the end, by decentralizing power as far as possible and balancing force, interests, and incentives, carefully crafting social norms and institutions that foster individuality and the will to power instead of destroying it, and egalitarian cultural habits and levelling mechanism which can maintain all that without giving into rigidity. By doing this, we can help each person seize the power to shape their future both in cooperation and contradistinction to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the ongoing project of anarchism itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to take part in creating a world where the structures and norms that we take part in and perpetuate are &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; in the interest of each of us, because if they are not we reject and resist them; where we have a conception of liberty that means that we are each genuinely motivated, through our own interests, to respect the boundaries of the liberty of the other, because in return we get a substantial, rich, and meaningful respect from them for our own liberty — instead of, for instance, making liberty equivalent to property, so that some gain by this liberty and some sacrifice for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task of anarchism, in other words, is to imagine — not plan, though, because anarchy must necessarily be pluralistic — a society that creates harmony between people by eliminating the tools and incentives for both oppression and submission. We want to do this because, as Tucker says in &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/benjamin-tucker-instead-of-a-book#toc5&quot;&gt;“Relation of the State to the Individual”&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If this, then, were a question of right, it would be, according to the Anarchists, purely a question of strength. But, fortunately, it is not a question of right: it is a question of expediency, of knowledge, of science,—the science of living together, the science of society. [A question of what sort of society I would like to live in.] The history of humanity has been largely one long and gradual discovery of the fact that the individual is the gainer by society exactly in proportion as society is free, and of the law that the condition of a permanent and harmonious society is the greatest amount of individual liberty compatible with equality of liberty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a world in which respecting others leads to a truly equal and meaningful respect for one’s own stands in stark contrast to the relations that we have historically found in Western history, echoes of which we face today: the “reciprocal” relationship of, say, a feudal lord and his serf, or a capitalist and a wage slave.  In each of those bargains, the interests of one with power-over comes to the direct detriment of those they subjugate, even if the bargain is reciprocal in some sense — “you respect my property,” the capitalist says, “and I’ll respect your person… I won’t kill you or (completely) enslave you, but allow you to beg me for scraps from the wealth I gain as a consequence of your respect.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is through our collective respect of the property and privilege of our oppressors that they force us to eat scraps from under their table. They own our places of work, our places of play, our homes, and rule over us night and day, leeching off our labor like vampires, and we give them all this for so much less in return. They gain liberty, the liberty to dispose of all this privilege and power, all this wealth and material splendor, at cost to us: our autonomy, our freedom, our very humanity. Yes, they might give us some scraps of respect in return, maybe they promise not to murder us (outright) or give us some wages (a pittance), but the appearance of reciprocity is just that — an appearance, and it is our sacrifice by respecting their liberties that directly leads to our oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/dr-bones-the-stirner-wasn-t-a-capitalist-you-fucking-idiot-cheat-sheet&quot;&gt;Stirner&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By what then is your property secure, you creatures of preferment? — and give themselves the answer, By our refraining from interference! And so by our protection! And what do you give us for it? Kicks and disdain you give to the “common people”; police supervision, and a catechism with the chief sentence “Respect what is not yours, what belongs to others! respect others, and especially your superiors!” But we reply, “If you want our respect, buy it for a price agreeable to us. We will leave you your property, if you give a due equivalent for this leaving.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Really, what equivalent does the general in time of peace give for the many thousands of his yearly income.? — another for the sheer hundred-thousands and millions yearly? What equivalent do you give for our chewing potatoes and looking calmly on while you swallow oysters? Only buy the oysters of us as dear as we have to buy the potatoes of you, then you may go on eating them.Or do you suppose the oysters do not belong to us as much as to you? You will make an outcry over violence if we reach out our hands and help consume them, and you are right. Without violence we do not get them, as you no less have them by doing violence to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrast this with what would necessarily result from a widespread, stalwart refusal to obey, respect, acquiesce, and a vigorous defense of ourselves and our fellows in doing so, not just civil disobedience. Consider the results of truly accepting justice-as-balance and our place as Unique ones over whom no fixed idea or authority can be acknowledged. Consider, in other words, the fruit of insurrection, the ringing shout of “No!” that justice leads us to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anarchistic justice cries this, and only this: do not respect anything or anyone that does not respect you in return. They have not earned it!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it benefits you, by all means protect it, participate in it, defend it, enjoy it! Mutual aid, solidarity, norms of respecting individual possessions or commons, whatever it is…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as soon as it stops serving you, cast it aside — what more interest in it do you have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capitalists’ claims to property oppress you? Break their machines, steal ‘their’ products, which you made, occupy their land. The law oppresses you? What is the law to you, really? Fuck it. Nothing can command you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say again: &lt;strong&gt;if a person or system does not respect your interests and your equality to it, then do not respect it either, because it has not earned that respect. Participate in what benefits you and reject what does not.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A widespread elaboration of this attitude is precisely the insurrectionary, criminal anarchism that I support, which would lead, through a world of anarchic encounters, to norms and institutions that, of necessity, benefit everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A constant, ongoing battle against those who would exploit us or dominate us, that is anarchism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Village__sunset_Li_Ke_Ran.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Village Sunset by Li Ke Ran&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="anarchism" /><category term="egoism" /><category term="ethics" /><summary type="html">“Another world is possible” every time equal uniques, free absolutes, meet on a terrain shaped by any number of histories but no structures of authority. — Shawn P. Wilbur, “The Anatomy of the Encounter”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Autonomy: Our Flourishing and Power</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/23/autonomy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Autonomy: Our Flourishing and Power" /><published>2022-06-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/06/23/autonomy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/23/autonomy.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of all tyrannies, a tyranny sincerely exercised for the good of its victims may be the most oppressive. It would be better to live under robber barons than under omnipotent moral busybodies. The robber baron’s cruelty may sometimes sleep, his cupidity may at some point be satiated; but those who torment us for our own good will torment us without end for they do so with the approval of their own conscience. They may be more likely to go to Heaven yet at the same time likelier to make a Hell of earth. This very kindness stings with intolerable insult. To be “cured” against one’s will and cured of states which we may not regard as disease is to be put on a level of those who have not yet reached the age of reason or those who never will; to be classed with infants, imbeciles, and domestic animals. — C.S. Lewis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although he himself certainly did not apply the ideas contained in this quote consistently, and while this was more likely a case of a monkey, when put at a typewriter long enough, having an inevitable chance of producing something good, I think that this quote represents, in encapsulated form, why anarchism is so important. In that, it is probably the only C.S. Lewis quote that I will ever agree with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anarchism is most often defined by what it opposes: hierarchy, authority, and all other forms of domination. This is important in itself, crucial even, since this opposition is what makes anarchism the most radical, consistent, and liberatory movement that we have - the only one that truly offers an alternative to life as humanity has lived it, with all its pain, alienation, and violence, for thousands of years. The only one that doesn’t ultimately just boil down to a sacrifice of the self on the altar of a sacred idea or just to another person or class of people. Yet, this opposition is so staunch and far-reaching, so through-going, that it in itself acts as the negative image of a picture of what anarchism stands &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;individual autonomy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/speech-on-the-passions-of-love.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Speech on the Passions of Love, by Guy Debord&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay could never be a comprehensive account of what autonomy is, so I won’t attempt that and I’m going to tell you beforehand not to expect it. Autonomy is an intensely subjective and first-person experience of one’s relationship with the material world and the social realities one finds oneself in; as such, it has complex social, cultural, historical, psychological, economic and political dimensions that give it too wide a breadth as a concept to be summed up in essentialist “necessary and sufficient conditions.” Nevertheless I will attempt to give a useful sketch of the important features of the experience and properties of autonomy, so that I can more accurately explain why it is so important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-autonomy&quot;&gt;What Is Autonomy?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first definition of “autonomy” in the Oxford English Dictionary is: “the right or condition of self-government,” specifically in the context of political bodies, nations, and states. This is not the sense in which I mean it - autonomy defined this way is almost meaningless for the egoist, the individual who must live, act, make choices, and interact with others and the systems of power within which they find themselves every day. Yet, there is perhaps an aspect of correctness to this definition: when applied to individuals, instead of polities, it stands for something like: the ability to direct one’s own affairs and activities according to one’s own plan, without outside control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definition is still imperfect, however, even taken as a vague sketch, to be used as an archetype in a non-essentialist fashion. The use of the word “government” here carries shades of the second definition in that same entry: “the capacity of an agent to act in accordance with objective morality rather than under the influence of desires” - viewing the individual’s life and desires as something to be channeled into certain directions and not others, to be restrained and converted from a raging flood of passion and self-enjoyment into a strict and well controlled canal; in other words, to be “governed.” The only difference is that instead of the individual being governed by something outside of themselves, they choose to govern themselves voluntarily, which is hardly better and very little different - still a subjugation to sacred ideas and absolutes which ultimately come from without.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since these definitions aren’t adequate, something else is needed. To fully encapsulate the idea that I use the word “autonomy” to evoke, I need to bring in two further psychological concepts: self-determination and self-actualization. Both of these concepts, intertwined and mixed together, interlocked in all the ways that they naturally touch in our real lives, are vitally important components of what autonomy means as a holistic subjective state for an individual to be in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-determination is the ability to choose the path one follows in life, to guide the direction one’s life takes and have control over the important things in one’s life. Self-determination implies both control of one’s own actions and body in a strict sense, and a more general control of or at least substantial influence over the social and material context within which one exists. Think about it - if all I can control is my own body and actions, but I have no control over my food, shelter, and other material needs, including the things I need to feel happy and fulfilled in life, in what way can I be said to have control over, or even input in, the direction of my own life? Likewise, if I can’t decide who I associate with and who I do not, in what sense can my life be said to be determined by my desires? Obviously perfect control over these things is impossible, the vagaries of random chance and the autonomy of others makes that impossible, but there is most certainly a scale of varying amounts of self-determination, and as those who have very little or very much will tell you, where you fall on that scale matters. A lot. What matters most is &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; has control over your life if you don’t: is it just that the reality is sometimes life happens and things don’t go your way, is it just chance and normal happenstance and other people’s personal choices that are causing you to not have control over your life - or is it someone with actual power over you to determine what happens in your life according to their will?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/migrants.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Northeastern Migrants by João Musa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-actualization, on the other hand, is the ability to fulfill all your potentialities and capacities - to learn the skills you want to learn and exercise them to the fullest, to be able to make do and build and make and achieve things that are meaningful to you according to the inclinations and interests that you have, to develop new interests and leave behind old ones as you develop, to express yourself how you want to express yourself in speech, clothing, social relationships, and even (or especially) your body itself, and to have the space to experiment with that expression and change it as you change. It is the ability to grow and develop and strengthen and exercise and change and develop and learn and revise and discard and add all the parts of who you are, from your identity to your skills, as befits the growing, changing, fluid &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/castanea-dentata-some-thoughts-on-the-creative-nothing-2&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;creative nothings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the Uniques, that we are. Self-actualization should be separated carefully from the sort of reified, static conception of the self, with its particular and constant limits and abilities and inclinations, and its static identity and means of expressing itself, that we see in some quarters - originating in Aristotalian eudaimonism, with its emphasis on actualizing yourself as an instantiation of a sacred idea of “the human” before which you should slice off any of your offending uniqueness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-autonomy-so-important&quot;&gt;Why Is Autonomy So Important?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can probably see by now, in a sense these two things are two sides of the same coin. Without self-determination, self-actualization is hardly really possible, since one will be constantly buffeted about by the winds of fate and the whims of those who hold power over your life; without self-actualization, self-determination is a meaningless pursuit of stability, order, comfort, conformity, and mere survival. To have a truly rich, complex, and beautiful life, one must have both. To quote Novatore, the great individualist anarchist who synthesized Stirner and Nietzsche in his poetic writings, “I have understood life. And anyone who understands life cannot live on [their] knees.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ascention.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Human Ascension&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While others might be content to sacrifice their autonomy to others in one way or another in return for imagined safety and security, I am not so inclined, and I most certainly do not believe that others have any moral right to force me to do the same. Have your ill-advised “social contracts” - but leave me out of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sacrifice my autonomy to some authority over me is to put my life in their hands: at the mercy of their morality, their interests, their beliefs about reality, their mistakes, and their blindness to my lived experience, my values, and my situation. Autonomy is the prerequisite for having any interests at all, because only when we have it can we be guaranteed the ability to pursue whatever interests us, and only what interests us. To the degree that we give it up, and grant others power over us, we lose our ability to pursue our own interests; insofar as we find that we still can, it is at the mercy of, and with permission from, those who hold our puppet-strings. Ultimately, when you put yourself under someone’s authority, you place some or all of your interests at their feet. What serves them is what you will get, and it is all that you will get. To quote Novatore again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rather I despise beggars, misers, all those who don’t dare to fight, but who only know how to beg and weep.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;They are the ones who beg for fallen crumbs from the sumptuous table of my enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But what could these misers ever gain from the victory over me brought back by my enemy, i.e., by their master? Nothing more that the usual crumbs and eternal slavery!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s explore this more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps my would-be masters promise to look out for my interests - and let us assume that they are genuine. Can they really know them as well as I do? If they cannot comprehend the situation you’re in and the experiences you have, cannot imagine the needs you have, how can they? Can the moral busybody who judges a homeless person for self-medicating with drugs or alcohol, or the concerned parents who cannot imagine it actually being in their child’s best interest to transition, or the doctor who insists that this or that medication is the right one for you when you know the side effects are worse, for you, than the benefits, or the FDA official who decides that a treatment is too risky to be allowed, when the alternative for people suffering from whatever disease it’s meant to treat may just be death, actually look out for your interests?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What matters to someone varies wildly from person to person. Values differ, understandings of self and identity differ. There is no enshrined human nature that ensures that, at the core of every person’s being, the same desires hold sway. Can others know your innermost mind and the desires that spring from it, when you yourself must often discover them through trial and error, through having room to explore and experiment? When they are changeable, when identity and desire and interest are not fixed entities, a static tablet of What Is Good For You, perhaps shared in some abstract “human nature,” but spring from the eternally shifting and flowing river of your creative nothing? The only person who has full knowledge of your situation, your needs, and, most importantly, the values that are unique and specific to you, is &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;. Listen to other people’s advice, if you wish; they may have more insight into the practical, factual nature of certain things than you do, but remain always aware that what is important is what works for you. Experiment, assess the risks and boldly choose them. Because those who give you advice also may not know what will work for you better than you do: even supposedly non-exceptional cases can have unique variables because no human being, and no human being’s situation, is identical to another; so do not leave the decision of whether you follow that advice up to them. Experts should be treated as people to consult with, not technocratic priests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because when you submit yourself to the authorities so that they can protect you and choose what is best for you, all your options disappear. Whether they are right or wrong - something which you will feel most acutely, and which will at best be a distant warning signal to them, often swept away in their certainty in their rightness - you are committed to the course; they have you in hand, and they will have their way with you. If they care about what you actually value, your values may still diverge; often as not, however, when others accept authority over you in order to help you, it is in order to help you achieve what &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; would want, or what they believe the best state to be in is, and they care little for what you &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; want. You may be wrong about what you actually want, you may be short-sighted, but that just means you need room to experiment and time to learn and grow; how would they know what is best of all for you? If they believe their kind of thinking is the best kind of thinking, they will label yours insanity and confine you to the madhouse. If they believe that their kind of life - cisgender, heteronormative, allosexual, neurotypical, whatever - is the best kind of life to live, they will “cure” you of those undesirable states which prevent you from living it. Or try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sedation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sedation by Jacob Lawrence&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it common for those who accept authority over you “for your own good” to be more interested in inflicting their ideas of what constitutes a good life on you? Because that is pretty much required to accept such a position in the first place. If they were interested in listening to what you wanted and focusing on enacting your agency and helping you live well, they wouldn’t be an authority, they’d be a comrade, an ally, a friend. To assume authority over you they have to be less interested in what you actually want, in facilitating you, than they are in their certainty that their own ruling ideas, their own sacred fixed phantoms, are what “should be.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, losing your autonomy robs you of your growth, your flourishing as a human individual. An autonomous individual may make mistakes and get themselves hurt, but their journey is their own, and they are able to find out for themselves what life they want to lead and live it. Each choice they make is chosen for themselves, and they feel responsible for it, they truly learn from it, they internalize it. When an autonomous person makes a right choice it is their own and represents development and growth; when they make a wrong choice, that, too, represents development and growth. But when you are forced to make the right choice - if it even is right - you don’t learn or grow from it. You resent it and resist it. Or you are beaten down and broken until you don’t care anymore and just want to obey. Without room to learn, grow, experiment, make mistakes, to learn for oneself what is and is not your own, you cannot develop into a full, whole human being. You will forever be a subsidiary to someone else, because you will always be dependent on them to make decisions for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horrors of “we just want what’s best for you” are too many to number and too visceral to explain. At this point my words fail me, as they must, and if you are not already convinced, or at least sympathetic, I can only gesture helplessly and ask you to consciously choose to engage your imagination, your empathy, to consult stories both real and imagined as aids. If you already live a life so completely unremarkable, so “normal,” that having the common idea of what the proper, happy human life is imposed on you holds no teeth, perhaps all that I’ve said so far will bear little weight for you. I can’t help that. I’ve done what I can with what are, in the end, weak tools compared to personal experience, even just the experience of staring into that abyss of self-annihilation that becoming the puppet of someone else’s ideal human life represents. Rationality isn’t all it’s cracked up to be; “all rational people” are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; guaranteed to all arrive at the same conclusions, because what is rational is influenced by what methods of reasoning we comprehend and what premises we already believe. Those things, in turn, are determined by your life experiences, and sometimes - even most of the time - life experiences can’t be communicated, can’t be summed up in surveys and meta-analyses or even in personal stories; at least, not in a way that will actually convince someone else that those experiences are “true.” So sometimes, you can say something that’s completely true, based on the intimate factual phenomenological experience that you have available to you - such as the fact that a loss of autonomy is deeply, deeply psychologically harmful - and you simply will not be able to convince someone who refuses to be convinced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/thestatehospital.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The State Hospital by Edward Kienholz&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sometimes,” a concerned, compassionate, helpful, moral, kind, sincere reader might object, “forcing someone to do something for their own good might be beneficial.” Must we give up every instance of helpful intervention? Surely we can keep some and discard others!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this I have two responses. First - how are you so sure that those “interventions” are actually good, except by assuming that all of my foregoing critique is wrong, and you truly can know what is best for others? That everyone is fundamentally the same in their values and what they want out of life, and that you can determine what’s good for them beforehand. Otherwise, how do you establish before the fact that your beloved intervention will be for the best? You can’t wait till after, to hear the praise and confirmation of the person you helped - causation does not flow backwards at your convenience. Pointing at studies and statistics will only demonstrate that many people found an intervention helpful, at best, and most of the time will only demonstrate that that intervention is useful at achieving a certain outcome, which your target may or may not actually value. Only by asking, and listening to the answer you get, can you have a complete picture of whether an intervention will help - and even then, someone might not be able to communicate the full weight of their situation and desires to you well enough to rationally convince you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - all interventions for the good of another follow the same logic: you have an idea of what constitutes a happy human life, and you enforce it on others. There is no principled difference between one and another; even the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; intervention can be helpful or harmful for different people. If you choose to allow the one, you allow them all. If you disallow one, you must disallow them all. I trust people to choose their own lives and live them, to arrange their relations and activities as they need to. Do you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let us stop assuming that those who accept authority over us genuinely want “what is best for us,” or that we, as individuals, actually get a choice in whether anyone has authority over us. That is a naive dream, the thought of an indoctrinated child, not of an adult who has seen the world we really live in and interacted with the people who live in it. It grants far too much to Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the real world, in many areas of our lives, we don’t even really get a &lt;em&gt;choice&lt;/em&gt; about whether to give up our autonomy or not. That choice, perhaps the most important choice conceivable, is already made for us. There is, of course, some sense in which, in the aggregate, the people who are dominated “grant” power to the authority that is held over them, because any wide-spread and consistent insurrection would render coercive authority powerless in the long run, but practically speaking most of the authorities that we find ourselves subject to throughout our lives - capitalists, bosses, police, politicians - find themselves there through sheer violence. Oh, there might be stories that they tell to explain why what they do is acceptable - the greater good, the social contract, the horrors of the “state of nature” - but ultimately we do what they ask us to do because we fear the consequences. &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/05/13/fuck-the-state.html&quot;&gt;There was never any &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; choice for any particular individual subjected to their power&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that it doesn’t matter what we want or think, whether we change our minds or whether the system keeps working in our favor. We will be subjected to it, whether we want to be or not, unless we stage a full scale insurrection against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates a general point, as well, one which applies to any authority you are considering calling legitimate and submitting yourself to: submitting to an authority opens one up to exploitation. Once you’ve done it, once you’ve given them that power, they are free to exploit you and terrorize you to whatever degree you grant them authority, to whatever degree they control the important parts of your life. This is why endorsing systems that grant others power and authority over you is so dangerous, why having one’s autonomy from others is so crucial. If the alternative you are presented with because of those systems of power is starvation and homelessness, they can make your life so miserable it’s &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; short of that abject misery; if the alternative is death, well, there’s a very long way they can go. A very, very long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/poor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Poor People At the Seashore by Picasso&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-this-mean&quot;&gt;What Does This Mean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not act perfectly free, then? If autonomy is the “most important thing” then why not just ignore all the laws and face the consequences? Because I might gain some autonomy in the short run, but I would lose it that much more in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measure of whether a choice was voluntarily chosen or not is in the acceptability of the alternatives - especially in what autonomy remains to you if you choose those alternatives. As Sartre said, in any situation you find yourself in, even in jail or on the torture rack, or with a gun to your head, you are “free”: ultimately, you make all the choices for your actions. But can any of that really be called freedom in a meaningful sense? If my choice is between submitting to the will of another and death, all my options are blocked off: if I choose death, I am dead - no more choices, no more life, no more autonomy or growth, it is the ultimate nullification of my self-determination. So it is as if I am presented with a fork in the road, and one fork immediately ends in a wall, while the other gets narrower but leads on for an unknown distance. I could choose to go down the blocked path and just expire at the wall. Or I could choose the only choice that leaves me with any further choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/exercising.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Prisoners Exercising by Picasso&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the degree, thus, that I choose to obey the law, it is because the risk of a loss of my autonomy that the alternative presents is unacceptable to me. I sacrifice autonomy to remain autonomous. Perhaps I don’t act that out perfectly consistently - but some allowance must be made for cowardice. I am not Novatore, willing to live my life in the mountains, on the run from police. That, itself, seems like a restriction of my choices just as much as mostly following the law does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autonomy is not the only value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not telling you what you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; want or &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; do - I am merely explaining, as best I can, why I value what I value, why I don’t want to live in a world where I must sacrifice my autonomy to people, ideas, systems, or institutions, or in order to obtain other pleasures in life, in the hopes that, through my rhetoric and reasoning, I can make some connection with your own lived experiences and find common ground, common cause, a shared ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thrust of my anarchism is that I don’t want to have to choose between a comfortable or pleasurable or joyful life, and autonomy, freedom, liberty - because both are valuable to me. I am not a stoic or a puritan, I enjoy all the things live has to offer, so to be forced to choose between the fruits of a pleasurable life and the struggle of self-improvement and self-responsibility is disgusting to me. I don’t want to cast aside either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay is an expression of why I love autonomy, because everyone loves pleasure. By extension it is an expression of why I am an egoist anarchist. You can either join me, or go your own way. If you choose to go your own way, consciously, as an egoist, I won’t demean you, even if you become my enemy. If you choose autonomy, perhaps we can meet someday, and find mutual enjoyment in each other’s company. But if you choose to reject autonomy, both material and intellectual, then I can only echo Novatore and tell you to get away from me - I don’t wish to be associated with rabble.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="anarchism" /><category term="egoism" /><category term="ethics" /><summary type="html">Of all tyrannies, a tyranny sincerely exercised for the good of its victims may be the most oppressive. It would be better to live under robber barons than under omnipotent moral busybodies. The robber baron’s cruelty may sometimes sleep, his cupidity may at some point be satiated; but those who torment us for our own good will torment us without end for they do so with the approval of their own conscience. They may be more likely to go to Heaven yet at the same time likelier to make a Hell of earth. This very kindness stings with intolerable insult. To be “cured” against one’s will and cured of states which we may not regard as disease is to be put on a level of those who have not yet reached the age of reason or those who never will; to be classed with infants, imbeciles, and domestic animals. — C.S. Lewis</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Democracy Won’t Save You</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/07/democracy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Democracy Won’t Save You" /><published>2022-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/06/07/democracy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/07/democracy.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;God, the State, Society, Humanity, etc., etc. have their own cause for themselves. If I don’t want to subjugate myself God’s cause, I am a “sinner”. If I don’t want to submit to the State, Society, Humanity, I am a “wicked man”, a “criminal”, a “delinquent”. “Sacred”! This is the most monstrous and terrible phantom before which all have trembled up to now. Here is the old, harsh tablet that the new human beings must shatter!
— Renzo Nevatore, &lt;em&gt;Cry of Rebellion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In leftist circles, democracy is often used as a synonym for all that is good and egalitarian in the world. It is used as a magic word that will somehow turn everything it touches consensual and non-exploitative, that benefits everyone and ends oppression, something which all of society should be patterned off of. Anarchists, especially those of a communist bent, although they should ostensibly be opposed to the sort of bureaucratic socialism that leftism is usually associated with, often fall into this trap as well, treating “democracy” as a magical solution that, no matter what the form or the application, will automatically make anything better, a &lt;em&gt;morally good&lt;/em&gt; sacred idea which should be shoehorned into every situation. This is how you end up with “anarchists” pushing for community councils delegating jobs and resources by majoritarian democratic vote, and calling anything they like “democratic.” I want to push back on both of these usages, however. I think that not all democracy is equal, and that sometimes it can be a force for harm. This is something I mentioned very briefly in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/01/17/what-is-individualist-anarchism.html&quot;&gt;individualist anarchism&lt;/a&gt; essay, but I think it bears more thorough examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I think responding to the democratic myths of, especially leftist, but also neoliberal, statists, is worthwhile, because illustrating to them how their favorite sacred ideal isn’t perfect and can fail people in very significant ways is a good way to free up their minds for accepting the anarchist position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/democracy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Borrowed from Crimetheinc&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many things in the real world, democracy manifests along a spectrum. Democracy may only rarely be found in the purely small, specific, and situational manner that I believe most embodies anarchist egalitarian ideals - “democracy as tool” -, and not all instances of democracy that do not fully uphold those ideals might fall into the same traps and dangers as fully reified large scale democracy. Nevertheless, I think exploring these two extreme ends of the spectrum should give us a good idea of what, exactly, we want to look for in a healthy application of democracy, and what pitfalls, traps, dangers, and harms might become more likely as we move away from that ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;democracy-as-cooperative-tool&quot;&gt;Democracy As Cooperative Tool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a crucial difference between democracy understood in as a useful tool, and democracy understood as a sacred ideal. The first way uses democracy to help solve the particular conflicts which might arise over how to achieve particular goals shared between multiple people, or how to make decisions concerning certain material objects which multiple people rely on, use, or occupy, such as a house several people live in, or factory machinery. It arises because several people with somewhat conflicting interests all have their autonomy and interests bound up in something common, so that any decision concerning that thing effects the others in a way that would constitute an unconscionable subordination of their interests if done without their input. In such a situation, those involved need a way to resolve their disagreements, and voting on it is often viewed as a fair-enough way to do it, even if imperfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democracy-as-tool only arises if this possibility for dispute is at least somewhat persistent, instead of a simple one-off which could be decided in any number of other ways (such as drawing straws, or debate); yet, it must be targeted to solve a specific problem and about a particular thing. In other words, it must only make decisions concerning actions that actually effect others. For instance, if we’re talking about factory machinery, if someone were to use the machinery but was careful to repair any damage, perform maintenance, and leave everything as they found it, and not actually prevent anyone who also wanted to use the machinery from using it, that wouldn’t effect anyone else, so it is not a proper subject of possible conflict resolution. Furthermore, democracy-as-tool, to remain as such, must not include any more people than those who are actually party to the conflict, effected by the decisions that are made concerning the specific issue at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these principles are violated, and democracies become large, organized affairs that persist for longer than the problem they were designed to solve actually exists, which dictate rules and regulations for things that don’t actually effect others, the association starts to become reified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, there three properties that typically identify democracy when it is used as a tool are that it is &lt;strong&gt;small&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;specific&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;situational&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following sections, I will discuss why each of these properties are so critical to democracy remaining a useful and benign force for liberation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;democracy-as-tool-small&quot;&gt;Democracy-As-Tool: Small&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why must democracies specifically remain small?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, because as the size of a decision-making group grows, consensus democracy - which is the only way to properly balance the interests of everyone equally, protecting each person’s autonomy and preventing subjugation - becomes less and less practical. Instead of focusing on being inclusive, hearing out as many points of view as possible and trying to integrate everything as much as possible, majoritarian (and representative) democracy will begin to take over, as people give up caring about the minority in favor of practicality and rapidity of decision-making. Now, sure, even consensus decision-making is imperfect - this is why individual, autonomous, stygmergic action is by far the superior option and should be preferred as much as possible - nevertheless, majoritarian democracy is a categorically different beast. Majoritarian democracy inherently completely subjugates the interests of the minority to those of the majority, constituting essentially a form of mob rule that can often be achieved through simple force in cases where community defense and decentralized power aren’t a thing. Majoritarian democracy has the effect of sacrificing a small minority of people in order to serve the interests - including stability and order - of the majority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, because when the size of a democratic decision-making body grows beyond the size absolutely necessary to consider the interests of those directly effected by its decisions, it automatically becomes a form of absentee authority and governance, and begins enacting the fundamental principle of authoritarianism: controlling how other people live their lives and exercise their autonomy purely for the sake of doing so, instead of in self-defense or in compromise with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/art1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[no title] by Constant&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clarify what I mean here, let me first make a distinction between two kinds of interests:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;autonomous interests:&lt;/strong&gt; interests that don’t inherently require the subjugation of anyone else; that just concern your own exercise of self-determination and autonomy, which includes your own person and the things you use, occupy, or otherwise depend on for that autonomy. Defending these interests may require other people to change their behaviors to accommodate you - such as not harming you or entering your house or stealing your possessions - but they fundamentally do not require those things, only for you to be left alone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;despotic interests:&lt;/strong&gt; interests that inherently require not just the cooperation, but the involuntary subjugation of others, that you gain by controlling how other people live their lives directly, or through threatening to take away the things they depend on for autonomy and self-determination. This kind always requires violence that is clearly not in self-defense, but instead in defense of the privilege that you gain from exploiting others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic paradigmatic case of this distinction is that between the occupant of a house and their landlord. If no one else is using a house, it’s a direct extension of the autonomy and self-determination of the occupant, something they have an interest in because they need a roof over their head and somewhere to live. Meanwhile, all the landlord gets out of owning a house is the ability to extract rent, which they can do because they are enabled by the state to violently evict the actual occupant of the house. While the occupant’s interest in their house are autonomous, because they only require the respect and non-interference of others, and have to do with exercising and maintaining their self-determination as an individual, the landlord’s interests are despotic, as they have no real interest in the house itself, since they do not use it and it is not an extension of their autonomy, they only have an interest in what they can gain by controlling the living conditions of someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to examine this distinction is by putting it in terms of authority or subjugation: while the occupant of the house only needs others to recognize and respect their interests as equally important, and so if they all also have places to live, to respect their desire for privacy in their dwelling place, and any limitation of the autonomy of others required by these interests is only in the assertion of the equality of these interests, to make sure they are represented at all, the landlord’s interests are asserted to the exclusion of the interests of the occupant, who must rely on the landlord’s whims, and indicate special privilege which comes at a &lt;em&gt;cost&lt;/em&gt; to the interests of the occupant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this is about who has control over your life: you - self-determination, autonomy - or someone else - domination and authority -, but trying to strictly delineate every relationship into either one or the other is a fool’s errand. These definitions aren’t a list of necessary and sufficient conditions, an essentialist taxonomy - instead they are accounts of the social and phenomenological aspects that make these two kinds of relationships importantly different to one’s subjective experience of being in such relationships. We assess which of these an actual relationship is more like not by analyzing some essence embedded inside it, but by ascertaining its family resemblance. Furthermore, these are merely two poles on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathyreisenwitz.substack.com/p/consent-is-non-binary&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;spectrum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of human relations, which can be more or less despotic or autonomous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cryinginchains.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crying in Chains by Margaret Blanchfield&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this relate to democracy? Well, I think that engaging in consensus-based decision-making with all those that are effected by some decision is a clear case of attempting to represent the autonomous interests of all those involved. The purpose is to ensure that the actions of others don’t harm the people who are effected by them, and that everyone’s interests are considered equally and represented fairly in whatever decision is made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as we introduce people that are not directly effected by the outcome of a decision to the decision-making process, however, we begin to run into problems. First of all, knowledge, and incentive problems begin to show up, since these new people won’t have much tacit knowledge of the matter at hand, nor have much of an incentive to learn about it or engage in the decision-making process, and, most importantly, they won’t be subject to the outcomes they cause in any case. More importantly, however, it subjects those who actually have their autonomy and self-determination bound up in something to the wishes of those who otherwise would not be effected by their decisions at all. In other words, it opens up the opportunity for people to extend their despotic interests by controlling things that do not effect them and do not factor into their own personal autonomy and self-determination but do effect others’. Imagine, for instance, that suddenly your neighbors across the street had an equal say in what you did to maintain your house as those who live with you in your house do. What possible interest could they actually have in that, except to control you? What interest could they have in it &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt; a despotic one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the relationship of an absentee voter and the rest of the voting body is not precisely the same as that between an absentee landlord and a tenant - to insist that it was would be absurd. In fact, it’s quite less severe, as long as most of the people involved remain local to the problem. But the principle is the same, and as the number of such “absentee voters” grows, so, too, does the despotism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;democracy-as-tool-specific-and-situational&quot;&gt;Democracy-As-Tool: Specific and Situational&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar problems face any democratic decision-making process that begins to metastasize beyond it’s original problem and situation. Once such a decision-making arrangement begins to exist outside the context within which it evolved, it begins to become reified of necessity. No longer is it a specific behavior perpetuated by specific people who are motivated by the existence of a specific problem; in order for it to be possible to uproot it from the problem it was supposed to solve, the question it was the answer to, it must cease to become a solution, an answer, and become instead a thing in its own right, which raises its own questions. It has to become, in essence, self-contained in order for being removed from its environment to become possible at all. Thus, it becomes an “organization” with a life of its own, which maintains itself as different people join and leave, gets its own name and institutionalizes itself. It becomes a thing quite apart from the people that actually compose it, somehow, by the process that all collectivities do this by, a sort of social epiphenomena that creates corporate forms, and begins to seek the perpetuation of itself. Suddenly, people start to serve it, instead of it serving people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/letter-to-my-son.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Letter to my Son by Asger Jorn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this process, it will begin to assert itself in all sorts of situations where the people that compose it are not effected, but are merely exercising the power of authority and control over others. After all, now that it is a self-contained, reified entity, it has no original problem to solve - it must go in search of a new one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is crucial that the parties to any decision-making process which begins to become such a collectivity make the conscious choice, and accompanying effort, to destroy it before it begins to wreak real havoc. Otherwise it will turn into the exact sort of Socialist Office of Circumlocutions that most Marxist-Leninist organizations, and even some anarchist ones, tend to become - huge bureaucratic dinosaurs bent on self-perpetuation in the name of preserving the collectivity which everyone must sacrifice in the name of. This commitment to destroying collectivities before they become Organizations must be part of the cultural, conscious leveling mechanisms that any anarchist society must employ, just as egalitarian societies before them did, to maintain liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;democracy-as-reified-entity&quot;&gt;Democracy as Reified Entity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this discussion, we might begin to see why democracy, when taken in the modern sense as an organizing principle used to unify an entire society, might be problematic. It gives people far away from personal, relational, group, and local matters which are best solved between the interested and effected parties control over them - it gives people control over other people simply for the sake of control, instead of for the sake of having input to prevent others from trampling over one’s autonomy. Thus a group spread out over all of the country decides to enforce certain rules of trade, or marriage, or health, or anything else, on the country as a whole - on people that they will never see, in situations that will never, ever effect them. It allows people to leverage this centralized decision-making power to exercise control over others not to protect their personal interests in their own autonomy, but to further interests that inherently require the subjugation of other people - the furthering of certain projects by taxes, for instance.  Instead of protecting the interests of people where conflicts of interest may arise, this reified form of democracy actually facilitates the destruction of interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/metropolis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Metropolis George Grosz&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a myriad of fundamental problems with democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, there is the free rider problem: each person’s vote makes very little difference in the overall outcome, especially since if you vote with a minority your vote will mean absolutely nothing, so it isn’t going to be worth it to put much effort into researching the best candidates or laws to vote for. Conversely, in a reified large-scale democracy where - as opposed to a small, temporary, fluid democracy concerned with only one thing - you are making decisions on a myriad of subjects, that will interfere with the highly individual and very diverse lives of millions of people spread out across a large spacial area, so the amount of research you would have to do to be properly informed on every subject is astronomical. It’s much easier to trust the words of dishonest politicians, pundits, and demagogues, especially when you’re busy actually living your life! Thus, the amount of research you should do is extremely high, but your incentive to actually do it is extremely low, leading inevitably to a mass of ignorant and apathetic voters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the cultural pressure to “get out and vote,” telling people that “every vote matters” won’t solve this fundamental problem: even if voting itself is easy enough to do to assuage social pressure, properly researching every policy topic and deciding which candidate to choose based on informed decisions is simply too great a time investment, and not something the people around you can really verify so social pressure doesn’t really apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there’s an incentive problem: most of the policies politicians suggest won’t even directly effect most voters, so they have little reason to overcome the rational ignorance and apathy that majoritarian democracy leads them to when it is only other people that will bear the cost. Conservative male voters will never be effected by abortion laws or transgender health care bans, so they vote based on “traditional values” and lower taxes, for example. And rationally so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, a fundamental problem with any kind of large scale, reified democracy is that it fundamentally limits our choices. There are a fixed number of bills to vote on, a fixed number of candidates on our sheets, selected by some obscure bureaucrat following some arbitrary rule. Our horizons are fundamentally limited by the imagination and interests of the powerful and those that serve them, the bounds of what’s possible restricted to whatever options they deem safe, sensible, and likely to be voted on. In direct democracies, the laws that we vote on are not written by us, or in service of us, but suggestions that politicians came up with to offer to us. How could it be otherwise? Even if most people had the time to write properly written and researched draft laws, how could a democratic system ever hope to sift through all of them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;representative-democracy&quot;&gt;Representative Democracy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representative democracy cannot save us either. If we don’t have the time or incentive to research the controversies and problems that need to be solved and draft policies ourselves, what reason is there to think we’ll have the time and incentive to monitor the policies and actions of those we elect as “representatives” in enough detail to actually hold them substantially accountable? How would we even begin to really get all that information? Even if we could, the only thing we could do is not elect them again; they’ll still have had their stint in power. Thus, once elected, they are largely free to do whatever they please behind closed doors because no one will actually read the legislation they pass or truly hold them accountable for keeping their promises. As long as they appear to parrot the right talking points to their base, they are free to maintain the status quo and gather power for themselves and their station because few will spend the time to look more deeply into the subjects and policies they propose. People, quite &lt;em&gt;rationally&lt;/em&gt;, go along with whatever the demagogue who most echos what they want to hear says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only that, but you need a lot of money and, most especially, &lt;em&gt;free time&lt;/em&gt; to run for office. Working people, marginalized people, even the middle class, don’t have that kind of time. Thus, the pool of who, practically, can actually run for office is limited to a very specific class of people - who will have different interests from the people who elected them. Moreover, those who have the most time to spend on campaigning and the most money to spend on ads will typically be the ones to win - thus, as competition takes hold and does what it is wont to do, heightening specializations, we end up with a whole class of rich career politicians that represent nearly our only choices. Even when we have an option that isn’t a career politician, it’s someone who has been close with that class for a long time, who tends to be rich and share those interests. Thus representative democracy necessarily leads to an elective aristocracy, usually in service to the oligarchy of rich, famous, and powerful people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pyramid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such a limited pool of choices, all from the same inbred, interrelated, colluding class, do we really have the option to choose someone who will truly act in our interests? Or do we have an oligopoly to choose from, just like we have in the economy - a few huge options that are all fundamentally similar and essentially automatically cartelize just by the nature of their socioeconomic position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;democracy-and-marginalization&quot;&gt;Democracy and Marginalization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By its very nature, reified democracy puts all of the power in society in the hands of the majority or plurality in that society; ultimately, whether you have direct democracy or representative, first past the post voting or ranked choice, proportional representation or winner takes all, it is those who make up the largest section of society that will have ultimate authority. This puts marginalized people forever on a knife’s edge: we are forced to appeal to the sympathy and higher moral feelings of the majority and hope that in their lord-like authority over our lives, which has the power to crush and erase us just as much as the power to lend aid, they choose to do the latter. This places the marginalized and oppressed perpetually on our knees, begging those who benefit from our oppression, who have little interest in our liberation, for permission to live. Even when we win, it is not solid or permanent, and neither does it represent true liberation, because it was not an expression of our equality, autonomy, and power: it was alms granted by an authority over us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/begging.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that we cannot rely on reified democracy to protect the interests of the marginalized in society, because it all depends on the whims of others. Defenders of the sacred “democratic ideal” will argue that if only democracy were more perfect - more representative of the majority, more responsive to the “will of the people” - it would be better, we could trust the majority to take care of us, but the reinforcement of marginalization is an inherent problem with democracy. It can only be exacerbated by making the majority even more powerful. Marginalized people are marginalized as a product of our different experiences and interests: the axes of oppression are constituted by the different experiences and needs that we have from the many. If everyone votes in their interests, marginalized people must remain marginalized, and why should we expect them to do otherwise? The majority cannot deeply care about our needs - for them, ignorance and apathy is rational, because the issues that threaten to crush us are abstract discussions to them, things that happen far away, mostly to people they don’t even know. Often, they don’t even know why we need what we need, why it matters to us, or even &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; we need, and they fundamentally will never understand, because we have fundamentally different experiences. At best, for them, voting to help us is an exercise of charity, something they do to feel better about themselves - but how strong of a motivator is that, really? Can we truly rely on the majority of people to feel that way? The people that make up “the majority”, like everyone else, are necessarily caught up in their own needs and struggles. How can we rely on them to overcome their rational ignorance concerning what we need, and the free rider problem concerning voting, just to help us, when they can barely do so for matters that directly effect them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guardians of the sacred democratic ideal will argue that if only the marginalized were able to clearly make their case before “the people,” the majority would be swayed by their case and choose to vote to help them, but if any view is utopian, it is this one. Voting is not a matter of objective rationality. Morality is not an objective thing that you can demonstrate logically or scientifically: each person’s morality is shaped by their culture, lives, experiences, and interests. Tolerance of queer people is just something that benefits us, and that some allies have come to like either because they know queer people or because they like it aesthetically. There is no rational argument that will convince a bigot to stop being a bigot, that will establish tolerance as the ultimate principle of morality, or that will convince people to care about issues that don’t really effect them. The best we can do is appeal to their empathy, as opposed to their own interests and rational apathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if morality were something that could be used to objectively prove that everyone should care about the plight of the marginalized, since when did we expect pure dialectical rationality to win out among the majority? Again, it is utopian to think that people will be more interested in abstract argument, in rationality, in philosophy, in being “morally right,” than their own interests and the rhetoric and tribalism of demagogues. Rational arguments don’t have any inherent metaphysical power that ensures that they must “win” with the majority of people. Everyone votes for their own interests or in favor of their own sacred ideals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor is the solution - as the neo-reactionaries would have it - to return to aristocracy or oligarchy or monarchy: these merely create an entirely new problem, granting absolute power to those who are already powerful in society and perpetuating it. The reason democracy seems better than aristocracy or monarchy is directly tied up with its fatal oppressive flaw - it makes &lt;em&gt;most people in society&lt;/em&gt; happy. But just because it makes society more stable by serving the interests of most people, so that there is no longer any revolutionary fervor, so that &lt;em&gt;fewer&lt;/em&gt; people are ground beneath the heel of the state, does not mean we must accept it. Why should we accept our sacrifice on the alter of the sacred democratic ideal just so that “the majority” can rest comfortably? Why must we remain permanent second class citizens, serfs of the lordship of Numbers? There are other ways than simply rule by many or rule by few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;democracy-society-and-progress&quot;&gt;Democracy, Society, and Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, therefore, when democracy is taken as a sacred idea, and democratic decision-making processes are allowed to be reified into their own entities to which people must sacrifice, it becomes particularly harmful. The ultimate example of this, large scale national majoritarian democracy, is particularly damaging, especially to the marginalized - a form of redistributing the benefits of society, sacrificing the few on the altar of the many. To prevent this, we must strive to view democratic decision-making as one tool among many, not a moral ideal, and one that must be kept as small, specific, and situational as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize that sometimes the perfect ideal of democracy that I put forward in the first half of this essay - based around &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/castanea-dentata-the-union-of-egoists&quot;&gt;Stirner’s union of egoists&lt;/a&gt; - may never be perfectly achieved. But it can form the basis of a conscious, intentional practice of practical anarchism in social situations: intentional leveling mechanisms, intentional choices to move closer to it. Just as we see such social and structural mechanisms ingrained in every fiber of every long-lasting egalitarian society we find, anarchists must also ingrain a commitment to egalitarianism and individual autonomy into their theory and practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an example of how this might pan out, let’s look at situations where the ideal of democracy must often be compromised. In situations where a democratically organized decision-making group must be maintained over extended periods of time and over fairly large scales - for instance, in industrial production - it must remain always predicated on the actual need for that group to exist. Furthermore, where consensus cannot be reached but a decision still needs to be made, which is more likely to happen as the size of a decision-making body grows larger, majoritarian democracy can sometimes be used as a fall-back secondary line of defense - but, crucially, that decision making procedure must &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; be agreed to by all beforehand, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/05/13/fuck-the-state.html#4-coldly-it-lieth-also&quot;&gt;not forced on them as in the case of a national democracy&lt;/a&gt;, and disassociation must remain a viable, accepted, and supported option for those that believe they are being taken advantage of by the majority’s decision. In such cases of large-scale democratic decision-making, decentralization and compartmentalization are good options as well: disassociation will naturally lead to people separating into groups based on affinity, common purpose and goals, etc; these groups can then federate together in a bottom-up non-hierarchical manner as a means of organizing on a larger scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More generally, what is the alternative to democratic government of society which does not screw marginalized people over? The only way to ensure that one’s interests are protected is to destroy the power and authority of those who could suppress them and oppress you - destroy the state, be it democratic or not, which is the fulcrum by which the power of our oppressors is wielded. Instead of kneeling, appealing to those who have placed themselves in authority over us, instead of taking the position of serfs appealing to a lord, we must entirely reject the principle of authority and seize the power to defend ourselves from oppression. The only guarantee is decentralization, distribution of power, so that each person holds in their hands the power to fight for their own autonomy. We cannot rest on our laurels, we cannot wait for the arc of history to bend our way, we cannot bow before the will of the people. Instead we must be ready to defend ourselves and our communities: not to wage an offensive war - a coup or revolution - but to protect ourselves. We must develop our capacities for community self-defense and dual power, defending ourselves and our own and supporting each other as well. We cannot rely on anyone else to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this alternative anarchist world that I &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/05/11/vision-anarchist.html&quot;&gt;envision&lt;/a&gt;, composed of small, specific, situational democracies and fluid non-hierarchical associations built around serving various community needs as the people actually need them, and local conflict resolution between the actual people involved in any conflict, all defended by &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/scott-crow-liberatory-community-armed-self-defense&quot;&gt;community mutual self-defense associations&lt;/a&gt; composed of part-time members of the community and accountable to everyone, there is little room for the sort of unifying entity (the democratic state) that makes “society” what it is today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That does not make it impossible to have a society, however; it just means that we will have stop conflating society with the state. A real society is composed of a distributed network of people who interact with each other at least semi-regularly, who trade things and communicate and travel back and forth. It is not connected from the top down, like a tree graph, by one node up top that everyone is connected to - it is woven together like a rug, the actual ties between people connecting the whole social fabric from end to end in a chain of transitive attachment. Consider something like the internet: a huge network of decentralized local groups, all connected to the wider community not by a central authority or singular institution, but by the web of voluntary connections that they themselves make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of picture of a society as a meta-organism arising from the mutual attachments of smaller entities - communities, which are then in turn composed by friend groups and personal networks, which are then in turn composed of people - might frighten those who are too used to the modern situation in America or other developed nations. Instantly, images will be conjured up of small, rural, isolated Midwestern American townships composed largely of ignorant bigots. Without the liberal majority in the country overall - concentrated in a few cities - to control them, what might happen? This picture, however, is merely a product of an accident of history and geography. We could just as easily have a society where the majority is bigoted, and there are only a few safe enclaves of queer people, people of color, etc. Thus this effect of majoritarian democracy working to (somewhat) restrict the advances of bigotry and intolerance is hardly a necessary property of it, and, moreover, given the reasoning above, much of that usefulness is quite restricted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparison, without the state, I believe minorities will be vastly better off. Most importantly, there will be no existing centralized seat of power for bigots to seize control of and wield against minority communities. In an anarchist society, power is distributed and decentralized, primarily in the hands of each individual to bargain and compromise and engage in reciprocal, mutually beneficial relations with their neighbors according to what benefits all of them; derivatively held by the diffuse social sanctions of different members of society and loose part-time associations, as well as communities that band together for mutual aid. Therefore, bigots would have to get off their couches and organize themselves, put their lives and limbs on the line, and, crucially, minority communities would in turn have much more equal power to resist. No more Reagan disarming black people trying to hold racist cops accountable. No more police being lenient on or even helping white supremacists while cracking down on leftists. Community defense is quite effective, too - there is a long-standing history of asymmetrical urban resistance and protest to draw upon here, and all that needs to be done is to make it sufficiently dangerous and risky to try to enforce the will of the bigoted majority on minority communities that it simply isn’t worth it for them anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/untitled.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Untitled #1, by David Pulphus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it should be noted that whatever sociocultural factors a defender of the democratic sacred ideal might appeal to to explain why democracy would be a positive force for justice and egalitarianism - good education, a tolerant culture, even the rationality of the mob and its susceptibility to “moral argument,” laughable as that is - could just as easily, and perhaps even more justly, be claimed by an anarchist society. Thus whatever positive benefits democracy can claim, anarchism can claim them two-fold insofar as the majority has power over the minority in an anarchist society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;epilogue&quot;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I put my lips to your profane ear and launch a cry. A frightening cry that will make you grow pale… So listen to it, since only by virtue of this magic cry will you vanish as rabble in order to rise up again in the flowering potential of all of your individualized members. Here is the magic cry: “The egoist has always affirmed himself with crime and, with sacrilegious hand, has pulled the sacred idols down from their pedestals. It is necessary to put an end to the sacred; or better still: the need to violate the sacred must become general. It is not a new revolution that approaches; but a mighty, impetuous, superb, shameless, conscienceless crime sounds in the thunder on the horizon. Don’t you see how already the foreboding sky grows dark and silent?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[L]isten again…: “Put your hand on whatever you need. Take it; it is yours. This is the declaration of the war of all against all. I alone am the judge of what I want to have.” Now do you understand, oh rabble, what the crime that SOUNDS IN THE THUNDER ON THE HORIZON is? But you, oh rabble, may not yet know how to adapt yourself to the idea of eternal war, you who have cradled yourself like a poor baby in the sweet dreams of eternal peace. And who even knows how many idols you still have to worship and on whose altars you still have to sacrifice yourself!
— Renzo Novatore, &lt;em&gt;Cry of Rebellion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/foo.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://crimethinc.com/2016/03/16/feature-the-partys-over-beyond-politics-beyond-democracy&quot;&gt;The Party’s Over: Beyond Politics, Beyond Democracy&lt;/a&gt;: A good overview of the problem with modern liberal democracy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/william-gillis-the-abolition-of-rulership-or-the-rule-of-all-over-all&quot;&gt;The Abolition of Rulership or the Rule of All Over All? by William Gillis&lt;/a&gt;: An in-depth argument against idealizing democracy in &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; form as a way of organizing people, and the different ways we conceptualize democracy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://crimethinc.com/2016/04/29/feature-from-democracy-to-freedom&quot;&gt;From Democracy to Freedom&lt;/a&gt;: A history and critique of the nature of democracy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/jason-mcquinn-post-left-anarchy-leaving-the-left-behind&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;Post-Left Anarchy: Leaving the Left Behind by Jason McQuinn&lt;/a&gt;: Describes how anarchism’s theory and practice differs from the reification of organization, group identity, and moralism of the left.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="politics" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="anarchism" /><summary type="html">God, the State, Society, Humanity, etc., etc. have their own cause for themselves. If I don’t want to subjugate myself God’s cause, I am a “sinner”. If I don’t want to submit to the State, Society, Humanity, I am a “wicked man”, a “criminal”, a “delinquent”. “Sacred”! This is the most monstrous and terrible phantom before which all have trembled up to now. Here is the old, harsh tablet that the new human beings must shatter! — Renzo Nevatore, Cry of Rebellion</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Fix Us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/05/dont-fix-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t Fix Us" /><published>2022-06-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/06/05/dont-fix-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/05/dont-fix-us.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You want, if possible – and there is no more insane “if possible” – to abolish suffering. And we? It really seems that we would rather have it higher and worse than ever. Well-being as you understand it – that is no goal, that seems to us an end, a state that soon makes man ridiculous and contemptible – that makes his destruction desirable. The discipline of suffering, of great suffering – do you not know that only this discipline has created all enhancements of man so far? — Nietzsche, &lt;em&gt;Beyond Good and Evil&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A kaleidoscopic whirlwind of pernicious lies, half-truths, misrepresentations, abuse, and bigotry swirl around trans people. I’m privileged to live in California and on the PSU University Park campus primarily, where I’m insulated from the worst of American transphobia in my everyday physical life, but on the internet, where we are all connected regardless of location, and where anonymity protects those who wish to do us harm just as much as it helps us hide from it, it’s not so easy. Every once in awhile something slips through, usually due to my own actions. One such instance occurred yesterday, when I found myself engaging in a digital self-harming spree, scrolling through the abusive, ignorant, and hateful comments under a Medium article by trans feminist Julia Serano. Through the flurry of vitriol, one comment stood out to me as particularly harmful and insidious. It posed a simple question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why not fix them?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not “fix” transgender people. If we believe we were born the wrong sex, and biological sex can never be fully changed, then we are forever doomed to be somewhat dissatisfied with our bodies no matter what changes we make. Instead of trying to change the body to match the mind, the commenter asked, why not change the mind to match the body? Why not give transgender people some kind of treatment to make us happy with the body we were born with, instead of trying, imperfectly, to make us more comfortable in our own bodies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the central idea behind transgender conversion therapy. We already know that conversion therapy is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapsychiatry/article-abstract/2749479&quot;&gt;harmful&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8189432/&quot;&gt;traumatizing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/aug/08/i-still-have-flashbacks-the-global-epidemic-of-lgbt-conversion-therapy&quot;&gt;disgusting&lt;/a&gt; practice that makes normative assumptions that are unacceptable to anyone in modern society, and is in general &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hrc.org/resources/policy-and-position-statements-on-conversion-therapy&quot;&gt;incompatible with human rights&lt;/a&gt;. We already know that there is no evidence that such practices are effective, and that what evidence there is indicates that they are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/conversion-therapy-an-evidence-assessment-and-qualitative-study&quot;&gt;ineffective&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href=&quot;https://genderanalysis.net/2016/12/myth-pimozide-and-gender-dysphoria-gender-analysis/&quot;&gt;based on misunderstood science&lt;/a&gt;, and that gender transition is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://whatweknow.inequality.cornell.edu/topics/lgbt-equality/what-does-the-scholarly-research-say-about-the-well-being-of-transgender-people/&quot;&gt;best treatment we know of&lt;/a&gt;, and is substantially, significantly effective. I’m not here to litigate that. If you disagree, you can go fuck yourself. I’m here to explain why &lt;em&gt;even if conversion therapy worked&lt;/em&gt;, the entire concept is horrifying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-gender&quot;&gt;What is Gender?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand why this suggestion to “fix” transgender people is so gut-wrenchingly horrifying, to understand it on an intimate level, you really need to think about gender for a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing you have to understand is that gender is more than sex. It’s more than what sex you have, and it’s more than what sex you want. Sex is a component of it - part of what makes many trans people dissatisfied with their birth sex characteristics is how they conflict with their gender, and most cis people are happy with their sex characteristics because they allow them to better embody their gender - but gender is not fully encompassed by sex. 
Do not misunderstand me: transitioning physically is vitally important to most trans people, and any attempt to deny that is harmful and disingenuous. Nevertheless, I don’t think many of us would call it the only thing that mattered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To claim that gender is equivalent to sex forces you to face two horns of a dilemma: you either have to reduce the meaning of gender to nothingness, since none of the social realities of gender that we actually care about - presentation, identification, social roles and relationships, behavior - actually necessarily arise from such biological sex traits, or you have to engage in the new-age mysticism of biological determinism, which treats chromosomes or some other biological reality as this ineffable, immaterial spirit which somehow permeates someone with “maleness” or “femaleness” in some meaningful way and influences actions according to evolutionary just-so stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking the first horn of this dilemma is nonsensical, since it completely obliterates gender as a socially meaningful concept, and leaves us with nothing to replace it, since sex cannot step in to fill the gap, as we will see when we look at the second horn of the dilemma. We are left with the question of how to understand the gendered social realities and subjectivities we exist in and which exist around us without the words and concepts to describe them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A man does not cease being a man if he’s lost his dick, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://medbox.iiab.me/kiwix/wikipedia_en_medicine_2019-12/A/Penile_agenesis_and_testicular_agenesis&quot;&gt;was born with a congenital deformity that robbed him of one&lt;/a&gt;. A woman does not cease to be a woman when she gets a hysterectomy or mastectomy, or even if she was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pennmedicine.org/for-patients-and-visitors/patient-information/conditions-treated-a-to-z/mayer-rokitansky-kuster-hauser-mrkh-syndrome&quot;&gt;born without a uterus&lt;/a&gt;. When we meet someone, we don’t check in their pants or ask for a 23andMe karyotype test, we look at how they present, how they act, and how they ask to be referred to. Neither do we ask to see their birth certificate, which merely looks at genitals at birth and makes a guess - that would be to make the same mistake of defining gender by genitals, with the added fallacy of assuming that legality makes truth, and that people cannot change. When there are intersex conditions that mix and match sex characteristics such that you can have &lt;a href=&quot;https://medlineplus.gov/genetics/condition/androgen-insensitivity-syndrome/&quot;&gt;a woman with XY chromosomes&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11268892/&quot;&gt;a man with XX chromosomes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medlineplus.gov/ency/article/001669.htm&quot;&gt;or something else entirely&lt;/a&gt;, we still identify them as their chosen or apparent gender, and clearly, obviously so. Indeed, most of the time, no one knows that they have these intersex conditions, including them! If sex is all there is, what does this actually mean? There is a meaningfulness to gender, it is a social reality, however much it is constructed, and without the concept of gender we can’t explain that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking the second horn of the dilemma is likewise a bad choice. It is extremely harmful, and feminists have fought for decades against this very bioessentialist mysticism precisely because it has limiting and harmfully normative implications both for the women who are oppressed by it, and the men who are both limited and also given a free pass by it. To define a woman in terms of (the mythic idea of the implications of) her vagina or uterus is dehumanizing, and to define a man in terms of (the mythic idea of the implications of) his penis or his testosterone similarly perpetuates harmful ideas. Moreover, it is simply wrong: what do chromosomes really mean? No one can see them, most people haven’t even had a karyotype test and so don’t even know their chromosomes. Moreover, does having XY chromosomes actually mean anything independently of one’s other sex characteristics, one’s personality, and how one internalized social norms of gender (through identification with a certain gender and internalization of the associated norms)? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/strange-but-true-testosterone-alone-doesnt-cause-violence/&quot;&gt;Recent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/12/091208132241.htm&quot;&gt;science&lt;/a&gt; shows, for instance, that there is no clear link between testosterone and aggression, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/alisonescalante/2021/11/12/men-are-just-as-emotional-as-women-says-new-research/?sh=6d32b5d72e96&quot;&gt;another study&lt;/a&gt; shows that women are not more emotional than men, to name just two bioessentialist fallacies. Thus, gender disappears under the myopic eye of biological &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender_essentialism&quot;&gt;essentialism&lt;/a&gt; while sexism is almost fundamentally furthered by it. Defining someone in terms of the mere biological characteristics they have is reductionist, dehumanizing, and has negative normative implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is gender, then? Your gender is characterized by a broad set of complex, interconnected, socially constructed, non-binary traits: how you want to be embodied in the world, who you identify with, how you want to relate to others and how you want others to relate to you, what likes and dislikes you have, how you want to express yourself, and a dizzying array of other qualities. It is an interior, subjective understanding of oneself, and one’s own ideal self-image, which forms and shapes who you are at a fundamental level, even if it is not the most important thing to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender is not socially indoctrinated into you, either - we are not born “blank slates” which society inscribes gender onto; it is a part of who we are just in the way other important parts of our identity and personality are. We can see this in how &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/1201664/&quot;&gt;children ages 2-3 years old begin to develop an idea of what gender they are, and pay more attention to same-gender role models in order to learn how best to express that gender&lt;/a&gt;. Gender is thus recognized beyond the borders of strict stereotypes, but we understand how we want to express our gender from the role models around us. We can also see this exemplified in the John Money experiment, where no matter how hard Money tried to change the gender identity of David Reimer, it &lt;a href=&quot;https://embryo.asu.edu/pages/david-reimer-and-john-money-gender-reassignment-controversy-johnjoan-case&quot;&gt;didn’t work&lt;/a&gt;. There are also &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18761592/&quot;&gt;neurological&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18056697/&quot;&gt;underpinnings&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18980961/&quot;&gt;to&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41386-018-0140-7&quot;&gt;gender&lt;/a&gt; as well - the brain itself has gendered averages, although not on a large enough scale to considerably effect cognitive function, nor in a way that can be essentialized and strictly separated.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on this, what you identify your gender as - what name you give it, what category you assign it to - depends on your own conceptual categories for what gender is. These are different from person to person, since one’s upbringing and cultural background modify what you perceive gender to be. In one time period or place, someone with the exact same gender might identify, or be identified, with a completely different gender category entirely. Thus, I call myself a woman because who I want to be, my internal sense of gender as described above, aligns with the cultural concept we assign to the arbitrary group of sounds “woman.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since gender categories differ from person to person as well as culture to culture - although they tend to overlap - everyone has a different understanding of what constitutes womanhood or manhood or any other gender; yet, crucially, we can still recognize the gender that someone is embodying for the most part. This is because we actually use family resemblance &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Family_resemblance&quot;&gt;family resemblance&lt;/a&gt;, not our own categories, or conceptual essences, to recognize someone’s gender: there is no single set of necessary and sufficient conditions that will identify who is a woman and who is not, for example. Any suggestion that there is one must either run afoul of exceptions, or enforce itself violently on the women (even cis ones) it wants to “describe,” as we have seen throughout history. It is harmful and demeaning, not to mention usually sexist, to deny someone their gender just because they don’t live up to &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; conception of gender - to call a man a girl because he has long hair, or tell a woman she’s not a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; woman because she works in the office instead of taking care of the kids at home. There is no essence to any gender. Instead, gender is defined by the overlap between the various conceptions and lived embodiments of that gender in the world, none sharing precisely the same characteristics in precisely the same way, but all close enough to resemble each other in a transitive chain of similarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of this overlap is ‘gender identity.’ In other words, part of what makes a woman, for example, identifiable, whether she wears a dress or jeans, whether she is a stay at home mother or a software developer, whether she is a femme or a butch, is the identification with other people of the social category of womanhood, the recognition of likeness and kinship, the desire to be recognized as one of them. Even if they express and understand their gender differently, this fundamental identification with other recognizable members of one’s gender constitutes one’s gender identity, and it is one of the most important aspects of what determines one’s gender. Many things that make cis and trans people happy in expressing their gender flow from the fact that they saw &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; women express their gender that way and felt a kinship based on gender identity with them, and internalized them as role models. Skirts aren’t inherently gendered, but they grow to be associated with a gender in our minds, and so most trans and cis women get the gender-related feeling of prettiness and ‘performing womanhood’ that they get out of wearing them precisely from that association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you doubt that cis people desire to be their gender, just ask them! If you do, you’ll find that most of them (&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10508-014-0452-6&quot;&gt;about 98%, according to one study of a few thousand people in Belgium&lt;/a&gt;) actively identify with the gender they were assigned at birth. This is intuitively true from experience as well. It is a rare cis person who merely feels ambivalent about their gender, who just “happens” to be a man or a woman but who could really care less; most cis people are very happy to be men or women, enjoy being themselves &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt; alignment with their own gender, and wouldn’t know how to live except as their own gender. Men want to embody an idea of masculinity - even if they refuse the culturally constructed one as toxic - and women do likewise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even voluntarily gender non-conforming cis people don’t like being assumed to be the other gender, or trans in general, and they enjoy breaking gender norms precisely &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; their AGAB. Conversely, cis people are unhappy when forced to be gender-nonconforming, such as women with PCOS, men with gynocomastia, and men with prostate or testicular cancer who have to deal with keeping their testosterone up, for example. It’s not easy to just simply “change” this either, and attempts to do this, &lt;a href=&quot;https://embryo.asu.edu/pages/david-reimer-and-john-money-gender-reassignment-controversy-johnjoan-case&quot;&gt;even on cis people&lt;/a&gt; have been shown to fail. Cis people often get gender-affirming plastic surgery or generally want to change their appearance to better conform to their gendered ideas of aesthetics all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women who are unhappy with the patriarchal structure of the world and the misogyny they experience don’t want to stop being women - being forced to stop being a woman in order to escape misogyny would be a &lt;strong&gt;defeat&lt;/strong&gt;! Instead, they want to remain women, but have more freedom, autonomy, and respect. Feminist women fight for women precisely because they identify as women and want to remain women without the enforced negative social effects of that in our sexist society. Simply “escaping womanhood” would not be acceptable to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this means that gender is a fundamental expression of someone’s identity. It defines their ideal self-image, and it colors most interactions you will have with other people, many of your likes and dislikes, how you feel about yourself, and much more. It’s both a filter that we see things through which permeates our lives, and crucial to our understandings of ourselves and how we live. Gender is a component of &lt;em&gt;who we are&lt;/em&gt;, just like our personality or other components of identity, such as identifying with cultures or families. Gender is not something merely imposed from the outside for most people, it is something actively identified with and perpetuated, and that is the fundamental motivational force and constitutive element of gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-transgender-conversion-therapy-is-horrifying&quot;&gt;Why Transgender Conversion Therapy is Horrifying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this, you can start to see how horrifying the idea of changing someone’s gender is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an outgrowth of the paternalistic, behaviorist, shallow-minded mindset common among doctors, where the ‘expert’ is content to treat everything as a shallow physical or neurological problem that can be solved with simple chemical treatment of the symptoms alone, without looking more deeply into the psychological, social, environmental, and economic causes that might cause these problems, and without any interest in respecting the individuality of the person or their struggle as an individual against the existing social and material reality which was not shaped for them. If something is causing you pain, stop wanting anything different, they say. It is an attitude which is existentially terrifying for the marginalized because it seeks to conform someone to a world that hates their existence, was not made to include them, which denies them, irrespective of who they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It suggests that, just because some (gendered) desire can’t be perfectly satisfied, we simply &lt;em&gt;erase that part of the person completely&lt;/em&gt;. We make you, and what you want, fit “reality” as it is, instead of allowing you to be who you are and be dissatisfied with reality and maybe work to change it. This is the logic of emptiness and destruction of identity. No desire can be perfectly satisfied; part of life is continually pursuing new desires and old: that’s what gives you the motive power to continue living at all. Logic that views desire as the source of dissatisfaction and pain, and therefore as something to eliminate, is death itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is essentially partial lobotomization: destroying who someone is to make them “normal,” to ensure “conformity,” and to make them “happy.” Perhaps they might be happy after such a procedure, but is it really &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;? How much of the person they were before is truly left? Is this the happiness of a person who’s mind has been changed, or the happiness of a partial vegetable? Do I walk into your doctor’s office, and never walk out, traipsing to my psychological maiming at the hands of your psychiatric gaslighting, electroshock therapy, neurosurgical butchering? If a woman in the 1800s is unhappy with her gender role, and wants to go out and work or study on her own, wear pants, and be independent from her husband, what do we do - do we tell her that such things are impossible, so we must conform the mind to material reality, and convince her through psychiatric abuse and gaslighting to stop wanting those things, to make her happy with the situation as it currently stands, do we lobotomize her, as was often done? Are you recoiling in horror at this? You should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the logic of &lt;em&gt;Brave New World&lt;/em&gt; - your desires don’t fit reality, you won’t be perfectly happy, so let us pump you full of chemicals and make you happy again. Forget what you wanted, forget all the parts of who you are that make you struggle for existence against the world around you. Conform. &lt;em&gt;Sleep.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’d rather be myself and fucking miserable&lt;/strong&gt;. I’d rather be a woman trapped in a body like that of a hairy ape than be a man. Fuck you and fuck your fixing. Don’t fix me. I’m not broken just because I’ll never be &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; satisfied with my body (is anyone?). I can make it better, so much better, I can be happy as I am, I’ll have my ups and downs but so do we all, that’s part of what it means to live, I want to fucking live! Get your suffocating hands off me. I don’t want your happiness - I want will to power! I want to struggle against reality and win an ongoing battle with it. I want to become who I am against the odds, not give up what I want because it’s too hard. Some of us have to struggle with some measure of inherent dissatisfaction all our lives - does that make us lesser? Would you erase the manhood of a man who lost his penis in war? Would you tell someone paralyzed from the waist down that they shouldn’t wish they could walk again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fully demolish the pernicious thought patterns that could lead someone to say something like this, I would have to demolish the entire idea that there is some innate human nature which people have to live up to, that there is a specific way that we must live and things we “should” want. I would have to pull up the entire edifice of Western philosophy by the roots and reveal it to be the hubristic farce that it is. That is not the subject for a short essay, so instead I hope that this impassioned plea, with its clarifications and analogies, might hopefully act as an intuition pump, something to bring at least a little understanding to people so that they go back and question their own assumptions. In the final analysis, though, this essay boils down to one thing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t fix us. We don’t want your fixing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is because there is significant overlap in the distributions of “female brains” and “male brains.” The studies I showed only show that trans people’s brains are closer to the “male” or “female” average. This uncertainty is why the medicalization of transgender people is dangerous; relying on “brain scans” to determine if someone is “mentally female” or “mentally male” fundamentally misunderstands how science and statistics works. There is not a strictly female or strictly male set of traits in the brain - to think so would be more essentialism - instead there are just &lt;em&gt;slightly different averages&lt;/em&gt;, and some brains are closer to one of the averages than the other. A brain that is technically closer to the “male average” (or vice versa) may still validly contain a female gender identity because there is substantial enough overlap between the two distributions to leave a significant probability of that being the case. After all, the higher-probability outcome does not always happen, that’s the point of probability. That’s how the averages got there, in fact: some cis women’s brains tested closer to the male average, and that’s how there got to be a distribution of “female brains.” Thus, in the end, despite brain scans indicating to some degree the validity of gender identity and transgender people in particular, identity is far too complex to glean directly from a brain scan, just like most identities and complex thoughts are, and the best route is just to ask the person in question what their gender identity is. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="transgender" /><category term="gender" /><category term="ethics" /><summary type="html">You want, if possible – and there is no more insane “if possible” – to abolish suffering. And we? It really seems that we would rather have it higher and worse than ever. Well-being as you understand it – that is no goal, that seems to us an end, a state that soon makes man ridiculous and contemptible – that makes his destruction desirable. The discipline of suffering, of great suffering – do you not know that only this discipline has created all enhancements of man so far? — Nietzsche, Beyond Good and Evil</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fuck the State… But Not Like That</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/13/fuck-the-state.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fuck the State… But Not Like That" /><published>2022-05-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/13/fuck-the-state</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/13/fuck-the-state.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A state? What is that? Well! … &lt;strong&gt;A state, is called the coldest of all cold monsters.&lt;/strong&gt; Coldly lieth it also; and this lie creepeth from its mouth: “I, the state, am the people.” … Where there is still a people, there the state is not understood, but hated as the evil eye, and as sin against laws and customs. … The state lieth in all languages of good and evil; and whatever it saith it lieth; and &lt;strong&gt;whatever it hath it hath stolen&lt;/strong&gt;. False is everything in it; with stolen teeth it biteth… — &lt;em&gt;Thus Sake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;, Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-the-coldest-of-all-cold-monsters&quot;&gt;1. The Coldest of All Cold Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murder, kidnapping, robbery, bigotry, oppression, poverty, destitution, slavery, exploitation, surveillance, restriction - politicians proclaim on TV, pundits write in the newspaper, and on the lips of every indoctrinated member of the masses, every Last Man, the same logic is blurted out: “the state! the state will protect us from these things!” - yet it is the state itself which is the worst perpetrator of all of them, the most efficient murderer, kidnapper, robber, bigot, oppressor…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state is the institution that holds the monopoly on the ‘legitimate’ use of violence in society: it is the sole authority in society which is granted the power to decide who should and who should not use force, for what purposes, and what the punishments are should those dictates be violated. The state then uses this monopoly on violence to invade the lives of those that fall within its territorial claims - to control what they can and cannot do via laws, and steal their labor product away by taxes. Thus, the two properties of a state: violence, and domination. Already, the problem with the state must be clear to anyone who is interested in individual self-determination and autonomy, and a society founded fundamentally on consent. The state reaches its tendrils out through its servants - cops, soldiers, and bureaucrats - to compel and limit everyone. As Proudhon said, to be governed is to be “watched, inspected, spied upon, directed, law-driven, numbered, regulated, enrolled, indoctrinated, preached at, controlled, checked, estimated, valued, censured, commanded, by creatures who have neither the right nor the wisdom nor the virtue to do so.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-lieth-in-all-languages-of-good-and-evil&quot;&gt;2. Lieth In All Languages of Good and Evil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first problem with the state as an organization is that it represents an inherent danger to autonomy (even beyond the limits it purports to respect). By centralizing power so extremely, almost nothing remains to counterbalance the power of the state. No one can stand against it, and all are cowed by it. Our only shield against its domination of our lives is its self-imposed limits, but since these limits are only ‘enforced’ by components of the state, they only hold sway insofar as members of the state care to obey them - in other words, it is a promise with no teeth, because there is no consequence for violating it. It’s like a crocodile promising not to snap its jaws shut when you put your head in its mouth. All that prevents the state from seizing as much power as it wants is the general wish of some portion of the population, and tradition. But the wishes of the population are fickle, and changeable, and as we shall see, tend towards increasing state power, not restricting it; and tradition, while powerful, is malleable and manipulable, and ultimately can be discarded even while the appearance of it remains. This ensures that the autonomy of all the individuals within the state’s purview depends wholly on the whims of the people around them and the pleasures of politicians and bureaucrats - not safe hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of this is that the state’s laws already reach into nearly every part of life, from what we can and cannot do with our bodies, to what we can or cannot do in our homes, to what arrangements we can make with others, and what we can produce or sell. Immune from resistance or retaliation, the state, nominally on behalf of the majority, but usually on behalf of the rich elites, strips away so much of our autonomy it is nearly unthinkable, disallowing us from making choices for ourselves about how we wish to live. This is its second sin: the egregious violation of our autonomy far beyond what is necessary to reconcile the conflicts between the autonomy of individuals - and indeed the robbery of conflicting individuals from the autonomy to decide how to resolve their own conflicts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider that in a decentralized anarchist society the only time force would be used would be in self-defense, or in the resolution of some conflict where the personal interests and autonomy of certain individuals came into conflict, because one person’s power could be countered by another, so in matters that truly do not concern one, the possibility of encountering resisting force would not be worth it, whereas in matters where one’s own interests are in conflict with another the possibility of equal forces coming into conflict must ensure equal consideration and a mutually agreeable resolution; moreover, norms focused on protecting autonomy and personal choices would be favored because they are mutually beneficial, and so benefit all to preserve, whereas invasive norms benefit one person at the cost of another, and are not beneficial to all. Thus, the maximum autonomy would be preserved, as violence and invasion would not be used beyond the places where one person’s autonomy was already threatening to subordinate another’s, and here, maximum autonomy would be preserved by the equal consideration of both interests, and allowing both parties to decide for themselves what the resolution might be. Compare this with a statist society, wherein there are no countervailing forces. Whoever possesses the Ring of Power - the state - can do whatever they please, even if it involves deciding which hole someone can put their dick in another! There is no reason beyond the self-promises of the state, and the general mood of the citizenry, to restrict where and what one decides concerning others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This naturally and inevitably creates the domination of some by others, but this domination rarely happens unidirectionally, across clean and comprehensible divisions. Instead, a whole web of interconnecting partial dominations and oppressions by everyone against everyone else ensues, as different people at different times claim control of the omnipotent edifice of the state and turn its baleful glare on their enemies or those they wish to exploit. The very existence of the state, as an immensely powerful, nigh-irresistible weapon, turns society into an immense circular firing squad, with everyone exploiting everyone else to some degree. Yes, some are by far more the winners, and some much more than losers than others, but the core point is that it could be used &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; anyone &lt;em&gt;by&lt;/em&gt; anyone. This creates a never-ending desperate scramble for power, as the conflicting interests of all the groups that would seek to dominate each other, or avoid domination, force them to battle for control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, as each side successively gains power, they extend the state’s powers for their own purposes, and then when the next side gains power, they usually neglect to restrict the powers of the state once more, at most simply turning the new apparatuses of control their opponents created in new directions. Additionally, with each new crisis, whether the crisis was originally created by a previous state action or power or not, leads to new calls for state action, state involvement, and new state powers thereby. Inevitably, these, too, are not retracted when the crisis evaporates, and in many cases the crisis doesn’t even evaporate, instead it just goes on, and on, and &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt;, often extended by state actions, often aided by a shift on goalposts. Thus, state power always grows, and rarely shrinks - two steps forward, one step back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus we see, as Tucker said, that any violation of the maximum equal liberty of all in society, and the mutuality and reciprocal benefit of relations therein, is inherently a threat to society itself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The history of humanity has been largely one long and gradual discovery of the fact that the individual is the gainer by society exactly in proportion as society is free, and of the law that the condition of a permanent and harmonious society is the greatest amount of individual liberty compatible with equality of liberty. The average man of each new generation has said to himself more clearly and consciously than his predecessor: My neighbor is not my enemy, but my friend, and I am his, if we would but mutually recognize the fact. We help each other to a better, fuller, happier living; and this service might be greatly increased if we would cease to restrict, hamper, and oppress each other. Why can we not agree to let each live his own life, neither of us transgressing the limit that separates our individualities? It is by this reasoning that mankind is approaching the real social contract, which is not, as Rousseau thought, the origin of society, but rather the outcome of a long social experience, the fruit of its follies and disasters. It is obvious that this contract, this social law, developed to its perfection, excludes all aggression, all violation of equality of liberty, all invasion of every kind. Considering this contract in connection with the Anarchistic definition of the State as the embodiment of the principle of invasion, we see that the State is antagonistic to society; and, society being essential to individual life and development, the conclusion leaps to the eyes that the relation of the State to the individual and of the individual to the State must be one of hostility, enduring till the State shall perish.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-whatever-it-hath-it-hath-stolen&quot;&gt;3. Whatever It Hath It Hath Stolen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state has many more sins, however. Next highest among them, but perhaps the one felt most painfully by those outside communities whose bodies and mutual pastimes are not as specifically targeted (such as us queer people), is the way the state enforces a rigid, cold law against all people, protecting those it deems innocent and crushing those it does not. Instead of a set of norms and resolutions to conflicts that is responsive to the social context and needs of the people involved, which weighs their interests and focuses on restitution and a resolution of the root causes that led to the conflict in the first place, the state’s justice is the justice of Procrustes’ bed - content to enforce an outcome, no matter how grotesque, no matter how destructive, and no matter how blind, and call it a day, satisfying the crowded onlookers drunk on its claims of fairness and objectivity, who will then go home thinking the problem is solved. This justice is merely a band-aid, however, a thin coat of plaster over a wider crack. It eliminates the symptoms wherever they pop up, often with brutal relish, but has no concern for the underlying sickness - and through its myths, it encourages the populace to be satisfied with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the laws that it chooses to enforce are often clearly designed to serve the rich and powerful - the richer or more influential they are, the better they serve you. The fullest extent of the claims to property of the rich man is enforced against even the smallest claim of the mother who cannot afford baby formula to feed her child, because &lt;em&gt;the rules are sacred&lt;/em&gt;. The Law presents a grotesque appearance of impartiality - equality under the law - but its relevance and protectiveness clearly, in effect, scales unequally. Property laws grant little autonomy, and little meaningful protection, to a homeless person, and in fact hurt them grievously more often than not; but to a rich person, they are the very life blood that flows through their veins, elevating them to a godlike status. In an anarchist society, few would have an interest in supporting such laws, and would resist them, along with their mutual defense associations, and without the state’s power at their back, the would-be rich, the would-be powerful would quickly find it far too costly to enforce their will at risk of life, limb, and ongoing resource drainage; thus, the only norms that would prevail would be ones that are truly mutually beneficial to all, which truly grant equal autonomy for everyone. Of what benefit is it to me to support norms that protect absentee property? I do not have any - nor does anyone I know, nor would it be possible for that to change. On the contrary, absentee property is a norm which only hurts me and all those I care about, subjecting us to the whims of landlords and capitalists, draining us with rent and stealing the product of our labor. In contrast, everyone has possessions, and wishes to protect them - thus, possessions, but not property, might arise as valid mutual norms. Only the state can so efficiently, with its unilateral power, protect absentee property, that it becomes possible, and even profitable, for some to hold it, and use it to dominate others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this brings me to the final sin of the state: taxation. Although &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/05/12/theft.html&quot;&gt;I have great sympathy for certain kinds of theft&lt;/a&gt; (such as shoplifting), which is performed by stealth and cunning, taxation is committed by outright armed robbery: render unto Caesar, or die. The muzzle of a gun, as always, is the state’s ultimate threat should you not consent: first it will send letters; then it will send lawyers; finally, it will send men to kidnap you, and, if you should resist that, a beating and the muzzle of a gun await you. Moreover, while shoplifting is something that merely happens, and the conflict of it is resolved after the fact, if it is even noticed at all, taxation is institutionalized and legitimized, enforced as the right of the state, not merely something that happened, which must be frankly confronted and may be let slide after the fact. This gives it an entirely different character: instead of it being merely a natural risk, something which people recognize people may do, it becomes an imposed threat. In that, further properties of taxation lie as well: as an imposed threat, it does not represent the free and autonomous assertion of certain marginalized interests against the interests of those whose interests are already well-represented; instead, taxation represents the will of those who are already privileged, an exercise of power and caprice, to loot what they please from the population. They decide what to take, and how much, and what to use it for - they hold the ultimate decisions, so even if they deign to direct some of their tribute toward ‘humane’ causes such as welfare, it is still an exercise of privilege, &lt;em&gt;noblesse oblige&lt;/em&gt; at best, not the actual assertion of the interests of the marginalized. No matter what, it remains the assertion of the interests of the powerful. Moreover, because it is a threat, taxation is levied not only against those who barely notice it, who have more than enough, but against those who will certainly notice it with great pain. Even progressive taxation does not overcome this fact - the state steals the labor of the common worker, often a large portion of it. Thus, while theft itself is not always wrong, the state’s theft is the theft of the robber and highwayman, not the poor shoplifter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-coldly-it-lieth-also&quot;&gt;4. Coldly It Lieth Also&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of these accusations - the strident egoist asking for a justification, a reason that she knows cannot be given - asking by what right the state dictates our lives to us, the state’s worshippers will claim that we agreed to let it do this to us. What an absurdity! Appealing to democracy or the ‘social contract’ is merely misdirection, an appeal for the validity of one fixed idea to another fixed idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is democracy, but the rule of the majority over the minority? What does it matter to me, if more people proclaim an interest contrary to mine, and wish to subjugate me? By what mystical transmutation does the multitude lay claim to “ought” - to a requirement in others to obey it, a &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; to be obeyed - when none of the individuals that compose it could lay claim to it? Their interest must be weighed equally to mine. An assembly of individuals does not give birth to a wholly new entity with entirely new metaphysical properties that are beyond what any philosophical construct has been able to lay claim to - an “ought” that cannot be dismissed as a phantom. I will not accept, celebrate, or sanctify my own servitude to the collectivity. Why should I celebrate a system that requires the subordination of my interests, instead of their equal consideration and therein the preservation of my autonomy? Perhaps, as now, their force will be greater, and then I will acquiesce to subjugation out of necessity, but that to celebrate it would be to give in, to die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither is my vote in such a democracy “consent” to it. If I am notified that, without my asking for such a system to be put in place, whether I like it or not, a ruler (or a law, in a direct democracy) will be placed over me based on the votes of the majority of the people in this arbitrary territorial area, it is only self-defense for me to vote. As Lysander Spooner says in &lt;em&gt;The Constitution of No Authority&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In truth, in the case of individuals, their actual voting is not to be taken as proof of consent, even for the time being. On the contrary, it is to be considered that, without his consent having even been asked a man finds himself environed by a government that he cannot resist; a government that forces him to pay money, render service, and forego the exercise of many of his natural rights, under peril of weighty punishments. He sees, too, that other men practise this tyranny over him by the use of the ballot. He sees further, that, if he will but use the ballot himself, he has some chance of relieving himself from this tyranny of others, by subjecting them to his own. In short, he finds himself, without his consent, so situated that, if he use the ballot, he may become a master; if he does not use it, he must become a slave. And he has no other alternative than these two. In self-defence, he attempts the former. His case is analogous to that of a man who has been forced into battle, where he must either kill others, or be killed himself. Because, to save his own life in battle, a man attempts to take the lives of his opponents, it is not to be inferred that the battle is one of his own choosing. Neither in contests with the ballot—which is a mere substitute for a bullet—because, as his only chance of self-preservation, a man uses a ballot, is it to be inferred that the contest is one into which he voluntarily entered…&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A democracy, in other words, is no less subjugation of the individual than slavery&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, nor is participation in it a mechanism by which the consent of the governed can be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social contract is no more convincing. What relevance does a contract that I had no hand in drawing up have to me? It does not, and cannot, represent my beliefs or interests, and so therefore fails at the primary purpose of a contract: mutual consideration. Leaving aside that being forced to uphold any contract by violence is inimical to autonomy -  “specific performance” is a form of slavery - even &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the bourgeois capitalist logic of the contract, what possible reason could be found for me to be subjugated to a contract I never signed? The only reason that I can imagine to follow such a contract is the blunt one of violence: obey, or we will hurt you. But I already know and admit that the state lays this choice before me; this does not provide a reason that I should accept it, treat it with the sacred reverence that others do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, if I had ever had a hand in drawing up the contract, and consented to it, wouldn’t its protections have been reciprocal - the benefits equally distributed? What possible interest could I have in choosing to protect and legitimize property over possession, when all of us possess things, but only a few own them, and those that do use them to lord it over the rest of us? What interest could I have in maintaining such social relations - not just acquiescing to the violence that protects them, but &lt;em&gt;praising&lt;/em&gt; them? To quote Proudhon,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But I wish that this consent, of which so much is made, had been given, either tacitly or formally. What would have been the result? Evidently, the surrenders would have been reciprocal; no right would have been abandoned without the receipt of an equivalent in exchange. We thus come back to equality again, — the sine qua non of appropriation; so that, after having justified property by universal consent, that is, by equality, we are obliged to justify the inequality of conditions by property. Never shall we extricate ourselves from this dilemma. Indeed, if, in the terms of the social compact, property has equality for its condition, at the moment when equality ceases to exist, the compact is broken and all property becomes usurpation. We gain nothing, then, by this pretended consent of mankind.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A clever philosopher may object that while I may not have explicitly signed my consent onto the so-called “social contract,” I provided my &lt;em&gt;tacit&lt;/em&gt; consent by using government services. Of course, again, the voting objection applies - had I been given a choice, I would have gone elsewhere for such services, or gone without them. (I would gladly do without the tender care of the police force!) But the government has stolen money that would have gone to the services of my choice to provide these services to me whether I asked for them or not, and, further, it has used its violence to shut out anyone else from providing alternative services, either similar or vastly different. The very laws it enforces against us prevent alternative norms and social bonds from forming that would make participating in the capitalist economy it protects obsolete. It has done all this to force me to use the services it provides, and then turned around and used that forced &lt;em&gt;acquiescence&lt;/em&gt; as proof of my consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about &lt;em&gt;hypothetical&lt;/em&gt; consent - truly, we are drifting farther and farther into unreality, into speculative metaphysics, indeed, into sophistry, to justify the state! - would, if we were all unbiased actors, possessed of perfect reason, and no value but pure self-interest, would we have agreed to this or another social order? Well, perhaps, and perhaps not - such a human being is psychologically impossible, an absurdity: a person having no values, desires, except self-interest? Self-interest in what? How, in what way? A person knowing nothing but the laws of sociology and economics, but nothing of themselves? Ha! Even if such a person &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; choose a state, however, the point is moot. I am not unconscious, or a vegetable, or a newborn baby, that only hypothetical consent matters to - it is a pale shadow in comparison to my real, vital, strident, and informed &lt;em&gt;non&lt;/em&gt;-consent! It would be a sick joke to treat anyone how one believes they would &lt;em&gt;hypothetically&lt;/em&gt; consent, in spite of them begging you to stop. This is no exception. I will not accept being bound by what one philosopher believes a psychologically impossible absurdity would consent to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-with-stolen-teeth-it-biteth&quot;&gt;5. With Stolen Teeth It Biteth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the state is so transparently evil, so destructive of the highest and mightiest of the things that humanity has yet owned - autonomy! - how can it possibly endure? Not by pure repression, that much is certain. Instead, the state endures by virtue of two key advantages: indoctrination, and temporal primacy. Without these two crucial weapons, the state could not endure, and without the first, the state could never arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indoctrination is the cornerstone of the state’s foundation, the crucial conduit through which all its power runs. If we, the people subjugated by it, did not cooperate, by following its laws, by calling its servants when others violated them, by filing our paperwork so that it could monitor us, and allowing its “police” to walk through our streets, if we were every day and every hour violating its commands, it could not long endure - it would have to have a cop for every person, maybe two or three, and that is clearly not the case. The state cannot survive and ensure obedience by pure repression; instead, it convinces people that following the law is always good, and violating it always bad; that the state is the ultimate arbiter of right and wrong, that being a good citizen is a moral duty, and that it serves the people, and the cops protect them. Moreover, the state requires a great amount of labor for its support. If all at once we refused to sell resources to it, refused to work for it, the proclamations of politicians would mean little more than those of the man in the psych ward who claims to be Napoleon, and is laughed off by the nurses. As Etienne de la Boetie eloquently cried in &lt;em&gt;Discourse of Voluntary Servitude&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All this havoc, this misfortune, this ruin, descends upon you not from alien foes, but from the one enemy whom you yourselves render as powerful as he is, for whom you go bravely to war, for whose greatness you do not refuse to offer your own bodies unto death. He who thus domineers over you has only two eyes, only two hands, only one body, no more than is possessed by the least man among the infinite numbers dwelling in your cities; he has indeed nothing more than the power that you confer upon him to destroy you. Where has he acquired enough eyes to spy upon you, if you do not provide them yourselves? How can he have so many arms to beat you with, if he does not borrow them from you? The feet that trample down your cities, where does he get them if they are not your own? How does he have any power over you except through you? How would he dare assail you if he had no cooperation from you? What could he do to you if you yourselves did not connive with the thief who plunders you, if you were not accomplices of the murderer who kills you, if you were not traitors to yourselves?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we could but countermand the propaganda of the state, an insurrection would begin which no state could survive - all across the world, people would realize within themselves their Unique, and stand up, refusing to bow to the whims of others:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…The egoist has always affirmed himself with crime and, with sacrilegious hand, has pulled the sacred idols down from their pedestals. It is necessary to put an end to the sacred; or better still: the need to violate the sacred must become general…&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly it’s not just indoctrination that causes people to submit to the state. For some, the rich and powerful, the state actively works for their benefit, but crucially, for many others, there is a subtler motivation: the status quo is &lt;em&gt;comfortable&lt;/em&gt;. It may not be better for them than the alternative vision of the future I propose, but it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; good enough that there aren’t isn’t a sharp ache in their hearts pushing them forward, driving them to rage against the system, to raise their fists to the powers that be. Their bellies are full, their minds occupied with whatever flight of fancy pleases them, and they see no reason to push beyond that. They have left their will to power behind. They willingly choose the life of the comfortable caged pet over the free animal. This is not to say that these people are inherently slothful, or evil, or anything like that; far be it from me to make such accusations, when I too feel this pull, as the comfortably well-taken-care-of daughter of a rich father. No, it’s merely a matter of incentives and awareness. There is nothing that hits close to home, for them, about the struggles the state causes, because it does not personally effect them enough to really hurt. Because of that, they are not by themselves motivated enough in the first place to become aware of the state’s oppression, and thus to become outraged by it. This is why education is so important: by making people aware, we can make them rebel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What of primacy? Well, in a society that was not already indoctrinated into the legitimacy of some ruler - maybe not exactly a state, but a village elder, or a priest, or a god - it would be very difficult to obtain the power of a state. It would, in effect, be a chicken and egg problem: without already-existing control over society through which to enforce obedience and obtain resources, how can one obtain enough resources to enforce obedience? If I can’t defend my absentee property or stockpiled riches, I can’t pay anyone to defend them, and I can’t amass power either. Moreover, even if I do begin to gather power, forces in society can arise to counterbalance me, since I do not yet have the absolute hegemonic power of the state to suppress rivals. The state as it already exists, however, arose because people expected to be led and were willing to acquiesce to it. By that means, it gained power and wealth and resources, so that now, for any rival just starting out, it represents a gigantic, unbeatable Goliath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-false-is-everything-in-it&quot;&gt;6. False Is Everything In It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, then, we see how true Zarathustra’s words were! The state is the ultimate social predator, a super-organism which forms a parasitic relationship with the host body of society itself. I urge all those who understand my words to resist it by any means available to them; I have contributed in what small way I can by trying to undermine the indoctrination which the state has so far managed to spread very wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/benjamin-tucker-instead-of-a-book#toc5 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://oll.libertyfund.org/title/spooner-no-treason-no-vi-the-constitution-of-no-authority-1870#lf1485_head_004 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://fee.org/articles/the-tale-of-the-slave/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/economics/proudhon/property/ch03.htm &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://oll.libertyfund.org/title/kurz-the-discourse-of-voluntary-servitude#lf0000_label_010 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/renzo-novatore-cry-of-rebellion &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="politics" /><category term="anarchism" /><summary type="html">A state? What is that? Well! … A state, is called the coldest of all cold monsters. Coldly lieth it also; and this lie creepeth from its mouth: “I, the state, am the people.” … Where there is still a people, there the state is not understood, but hated as the evil eye, and as sin against laws and customs. … The state lieth in all languages of good and evil; and whatever it saith it lieth; and whatever it hath it hath stolen. False is everything in it; with stolen teeth it biteth… — Thus Sake Zarathustra, Friedrich Nietzsche</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Theft is Good, Actually; or, Stigmergic Socialism Vs. The Welfare State</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/12/theft.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Theft is Good, Actually; or, Stigmergic Socialism Vs. The Welfare State" /><published>2022-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/12/theft</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/12/theft.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;stigmergy&lt;/strong&gt; (noun)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;(biology) A mechanism of spontaneous, indirect coordination between agents or actions, where the trace left in the environment by an action stimulates the performance of a subsequent action.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;(systems theory) A mechanism of indirect coordination between agents or actions, in which the aftereffects of one action guide a subsequent action.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my previous essay, I mentioned how the enforcement of absolute laws, for example in the case of theft, can actually be harmful - not just to the individual punished by the retributive ‘justice’ of the state, but to the whole society, as the underlying tensions that led to the theft remain unresolved, or are (often) worsened. I argued that, in contrast to a liberal-capitalist-democratic society, an anarchist society would be aware of this problem, and, taking no fixed idea of Law or Justice as a ‘sacred idea,’ would invest instead in weighing the actual interests of those involved in the conflict and resolving the underlying tensions through restorative justice. Thus, I claimed that ‘theft would be a legitimate means of surviving.’ In this essay, I want to elaborate on that point, because I think understanding what precisely I mean by this, and what social problems it is aimed at resolving, is crucial to understanding what a humane anarchist society might look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the ‘sacred ideas’ of Law and Justice, people in an anarchist society would look at ‘theft’ as just as inherently amoral as possession itself - neither legitimate nor illegitimate, but simply the assertion of certain interests against others. The question would be what would be necessary to resolve any social conflict caused by &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt; the assertion of possessory rights &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; the negation of them, as well as ensuring that neither interest is subordinated to each other, but each is weighed equally. Thus, although general communal norms, expressed in the personal choices and actions by most individuals in that community, might lean towards respecting the possessions of others in order to obtain reciprocal respect for one’s own possessions - i.e., in order to avoid social conflict or a free-for-all, and to maintain norms that are generally beneficial to self-determination and autonomy - it would have to be recognized that asking someone for whom such reciprocal benefits are very far down their list of interests to respect them is laughable, and a form of subjugation of their interests to the interests of the community as a whole. Thus, the whole social attitude towards theft would necessarily change from one of moralization - either against, like in the conservative view that one should never ever steal, that there is ‘always’ another option; or for, as we see occasionally in ‘leftist’ circles - to one of understanding, acceptance, and frank confrontation of accountability, ready to do what is necessary to move forward. In such a society, the clear solution to the bicycle problem presented in my previous essay would be to allow the shoplifter to keep it, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, those who, for whatever reason - mental illness, disability, or other circumstances -, could not support themselves by their own labor, would have a fallback on which to survive, by simply taking what they needed from whoever had enough that it wouldn’t harm them too much - for instance, stealing food from the local branch of the large grocery cooperative. Most of the time, this would barely be noticed, would be covered by insurance, and would be largely invisible to whoever was stolen from, and to the community at large; yet, it would mean the world for those who otherwise would be condemned to a life of poverty, hardship, and possibly even starvation. Additionally, in most cases, poverty is the product of the poverty trap, an inability to get into a stable and safe position from which one can begin to heal, to develop useful skills, and learn how to contribute to one’s community, not inherent laziness, evil, or incapacities, as many would have you believe. Most people actually want to contribute something useful to their community and not be dependent forever. Therefore, in most cases, needing to steal to survive would be a very temporary condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that there would be no incentive against theft - frank confrontation of the reasons behind theft, instead of moralization, does not preclude finding that theft is actually an unacceptable subordination of those stolen from - stealing the neighbor’s better TV, for instance. Conflict resolution in some cases might require the injuring party to give restitution of some kind to the person they stole from, or simply return the item. Moreover, even in cases of theft like the ones discussed in the previous paragraph, there is still the risk of being caught and needing to go through a whole process of conflict resolution, with accompanying social friction, delay, and so on, even if the decision comes out in the thief’s favor in the end. Therefore, I don’t think anyone would be that motivated to steal constantly and wantonly; it would likely be limited to necessities, against compassionately chosen targets, and only when the person is actually in need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This emergent property of an anarchist society would essentially act as an alternative to the welfare state. The welfare state, as we have it now, fosters centralization and dependence, by proclaiming that it is the only actor that may legitimately steal - through taxes - in order to support its citizens, ensuring that those citizens depend on it for their lives and livelihoods; to compound this, it predicates such support on bureaucratic red tape and gate-keeping which is often traumatizing to the applicants and which leaves many who need aid and support out in the cold. Moreover, once someone has obtained welfare, it is used like a carrot to control their actions, further destroying their autonomy, and the benefits themselves are often seemingly almost purposefully designed to foster and promote dependence. Unlike the welfare state, theft for those in need would distribute mis-allocated resources to the people that needed them most in a decentralized, stigmergic way. There would not be any need to gatekeep, there would be no centralized bureaucracy, nothing like that at all. Instead of the traumatizing process of being inspected and controlled and tied by the neck to the state, people would be empowered to act on their own, to simply take what they needed, and negotiate the consequences as necessary with the community around them. Instead of state ‘legitimized’ theft carried out by armed goons against the entire populace, irrespective of whether they are a large corporation or collective which could cover the loss, or a laborer, and most of which is allocated to things that would not be considered genuine interests, let alone interests that weigh well against those of the stolen-from, there would be small and occasional instances of theft here and there in a larger society, targeted against actors that would barely notice the difference. And since it wouldn’t be carried out by the state, covered in miles of rules and legislation and red tape, it would probably be far cheaper to bear the costs of such theft than it would be to actually pay for welfare!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such theft would act as a natural, almost market-like means of stigmergically redistributing wealth, preventing class segregation by ensuring that nobody sinks into the vicious cycle of poverty while others stockpile wealth. It turns the interstices of the economy in an anarchist society into a more habitable place, preventing anyone from falling through the cracks due to unavoidable circumstances. Combined with the much lower barrier to being self-sufficient in an anarchist society, as working out of your home would be possible and jobs would pay much more thanks to all being worker-owned, this all but ensures that everyone would be ‘taken care of’ without any need for a paternal/maternal state. Indeed, such theft by those in need would act as a natural incentive to those who have a lot of resources to provide resources for to aid those in need voluntarily, since the social friction caused by stealing (over and above the simple loss of the item), due to danger, possible damage to property, and the need for conflict resolution if anyone is caught, doesn’t just apply to the thief, but also whoever is stolen from. All this combines to directly incentivize exactly the sort of things that a capitalist market makes supererogatory. Collectives could provide training on the job, loosen up hiring requirements regarding e.g. work hours or dress codes, or do whatever else is necessary to lower the barrier to entry to get a job; they could also begin handing out the excess of whatever product they produce, such as food or clothes, which, thanks to the laws of supply and demand, there is likely to be. There are a myriad ways of doing this sort of thing, certainly way more than I can think of!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while I don’t think theft is ‘good’ in all cases, in certain situations, for certain people, and when handled and viewed correctly by society, I think it can actually be a very beneficial thing on many levels. I don’t claim to have perfect foresight about what a system like this would end up working like, but I do think this is an interesting thing to think about.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="politics" /><category term="anarchism" /><summary type="html">stigmergy (noun) (biology) A mechanism of spontaneous, indirect coordination between agents or actions, where the trace left in the environment by an action stimulates the performance of a subsequent action. (systems theory) A mechanism of indirect coordination between agents or actions, in which the aftereffects of one action guide a subsequent action.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vision of an Anarchist Society</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/11/vision-anarchist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vision of an Anarchist Society" /><published>2022-05-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/11/vision-anarchist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/11/vision-anarchist.html">&lt;p&gt;A new vision of an anarchist society, different in important ways from the ones that I’ve presented before, replete with new emphases and contrasts with the society that we currently live in, has been percolating in the back of my head for some time. It has been developing in response to my thoughts about anarchism moving in a less market-oriented and more egoist direction, and as such it looks much more ‘socialist’ and ‘leftist’ than my previous visions ever did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new vision of anarchism, and accompanying understanding, has increasingly made my previous essays about anarchism obsolete. Furthermore, I have found myself giving nearly the following exposition to many people in nearly identical form, which indicates that it strikes at the heart of my current mentality. Considering that, I think it’s time to transcribe it into something a little more permanent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before or after you read this essay, I highly recommend you read &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/01/17/what-is-individualist-anarchism.html&quot;&gt;What Is Individualist Anarchism&lt;/a&gt;, which overlaps with this one in a few ways but in general elaborates more on values, property norms, and long term goals, but less on institutions specifically. I view these essays as essentially two sides of the same coin, and the way I phrase my ideas in one or the other my make more sense to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-conflict-resolution&quot;&gt;1. Conflict Resolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary problem of ‘organization’ in an anarchist society is conflict resolution. The fullest extent of each person’s interests are always, at least at the borders, going to come into conflict with those of others, since the full satisfaction of everyone’s desires is not possible. This naturally leads to conflict, but that conflict itself is expensive and generally undesirable compared to a state of reconciliation and cooperation, since it imposes material and interpersonal costs. Thus, it is in everyone’s interests to have some means of resolving the conflicts that arise of necessity as part of living among other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One solution to such conflicts is to subordinate the interests of one party of the conflict to the other. This does not resolve the conflict, but instead anoints one side as ‘legitimate’ and the other as ‘illegitimate’ and perpetuates an eternal war against the ‘illegitimate’ side in the name of ‘ending’ (really, disguising) the conflict. This is the solution which most societies throughout human history, since the creation of the state by the first priest or warlord, have pursued, because it is the easiest. Instead of actually giving up anything, resolving anything, or reconciling anything, one side gets everything they want, and wages constant conflict on the other side, which is cowed, defeated, indoctrinated, repressed, confused, and loaded full of sacred ideas to protect the authority and legitimacy of the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another solution is to subordinate the interests of both sides to a ‘sacred idea’ such as Law, or Equality, or Justice. This is the idea behind most modern representative democracies, and it, too, is easy; instead of resolving the conflict, it pushes down, hides, ‘ends’ the conflict by meting out punishments and rewards so that people can feel satisfied, as if something has been accomplished, and leaves it at that. Of course the underlying causes of the conflict are not resolved, and nothing is fixed or healed by this method, and so, inevitably, it reduces to the first method of conflict resolution: an eternal war on the part of society, on behalf of the class that happens to be privileged by the Laws that are constructed, against those who are disenfranchised by it. This, too, is no real solution; such a centralized, rigid legal system is, despite statist myth-making, more damaging to its host society than beneficial. It is a band-aid, a Procrustean bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, imagine that someone shoplifts a bicycle. In a modern liberal-capitalist-democratic society, such a person would likely be fined and/or sent to jail - after having the vehicle taken away, of course. Is this truly the right solution? If someone was in such terrible need as to risk social conflict to obtain the bicycle, maybe they need it - maybe allowing them to keep it would allow them to obtain transportation to a job, which would help raise them out of poverty. This is a classic problem with poverty, after all: it takes resources to get into a position to make money, and without money this can turn into an unsolvable chicken-and-egg problem without resorting to ‘illegal’ actions. Moreover, stealing a cheap bicycle from your average supermarket store, like Target, is barely a blip on their radar, whereas protecting their property by preventing such theft, and even &lt;em&gt;punishing&lt;/em&gt; the thief, can be an utterly disastrous thing for the thief. The assertion of the fullest extent of the corporation’s minor interest over the desperate needs of the thief is a clear subordination of the latter’s interests to the former, a grotesque decision. Not only does doing so merely perpetuate the social conflict, without resolving any of the underlying problems, it increases it, as someone who was merely poor before now gets kidnapped, put in a cage, and has this ‘put on their record.’ This is why, incidentally, recidivism rates are so high after prison - how is someone supposed to get back on their feet after having their life utterly destroyed in such a way? And hence the conflict worsens, and the cops get more militarized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, since an anarchist ‘society,’ by definition, rejects such systemic violence, subordination of the interests of some to others, and adherence to the law as a fixed sacred idea, the focus must inevitably be on the actual resolution of conflicts &lt;em&gt;between the parties to the conflict&lt;/em&gt;, and nothing else. The interests of both parties are all that is relevant to such an endeavor, and the resolution of the conflict by finding a mutually beneficial and satisfactory end must be the only goal. Although the resolution can be informed by social norms and values, this is only through the reaction of the community at large - at least, those who are aware of the conflict - to the resolution of the conflict, and the beliefs and values of the parties that are involved, insofar as they have internalized any social norms or values. No set of norms or values can be elevated to a position of a ‘sacred idea’ over the actual interests of those involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this model, some conflicts may not be resolvable; sometimes, the cost of social war is less to each involved party than the cost of accepting any compromise whatsoever. In such a case, conflict is inevitable, and that’s okay. Such a situation can only arise, in my opinion, when one side is attempting to unilaterally subordinate the interests of another: the would-be master requires surrender from the slave, and the slave cannot accept this. We are, in a sense, in just such a situation now - no ‘resolution’ to the conflict between the rich and powerful and everyone else is possible; the former must be eliminated (not by killing them, to be clear, but by taking away their power).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this, instead of a set system of courts and judges, with bureaucratic procedures and state enforcement, in an anarchist society I envision a system where conflicts are first and foremost resolved by face to face communication between the aggrieved parties, or through the mediation of family members, neighbors, or friends. However, in response to occasions when these fail, perhaps because the aggrieved parties don’t trust any of the people listed previously to mediate the dispute evenhandedly, a class of wandering, competing arbitrators could arise to serve the required social function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They could be aware of the way previous arbitrators had resolved similar disputes, perhaps compiling lists of history and tradition that they thought aligned with their personal philosophies, but they would be primarily concerned with arriving at a solution &lt;em&gt;in their particular situation&lt;/em&gt;, for the specific needs of the people involved. Their job would not be to ‘hand down’ a final decision - any number of other people could always be consulted for a second opinion - or be the mouthpiece of some absolute law, and their decisions would not be enforced unless the people involved themselves found them worthy of enforcing. Such arbitrators’ only job would be to try to use their broad experience with resolving conflicts and their speaking and arguing ability to find some mutually agreeable solution so that social conflict can end. In essence, they would be trying to find some unique point in the ongoing bargain between the two parties that would be better for both of them, and the primary enforcement of their ideas would be, if they are successful in their job, the fact that such reconciliation is better than ongoing conflict for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of approach to resolving conflicts in society has some historical precedent; it is, in fact, fairly similar to the &lt;em&gt;filid&lt;/em&gt; of Ancient Ireland:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First of all, the law itself was based upon immemorial custom passed down orally through a class of professional jurists known as the &lt;em&gt;filid&lt;/em&gt;. These jurists added glosses to the basic law from time to time to make it fit the needs of the times; several schools of jurisprudence existed, and the professional jurists were consulted by parties to disputes for advice as to what the law was in particular cases, and these same men often acted as arbitrators between suitors. They remained at all times private persons, not public officials; their functioning depended upon their knowledge of the law and the integrity of their judicial reputations. They are the only “judges” Celtic Ireland knew; their jurisprudence was her only law, national in scope, and completely detached from the &lt;em&gt;tuath&lt;/em&gt;, the kings and their respective wishes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;How was this law of the &lt;em&gt;filid&lt;/em&gt; enforced? The law was enforced by the action of private individuals allied with the plaintiff and defendant through a system of sureties. Men were linked together by a number of individual relationships by which they were obligated to stand surety for one another guaranteeing that wrongs would be righted, debts paid, judgments honored, and the law enforced.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although historical precedent is not absolute, and we should dare to dream beyond the limits of what has been done before, instead of confining ourselves to mere cannibalism of the past, historical parallels to suggested projectual anarchist ideas are, in my opinion, very useful in demonstrating that such ideas are possible and can arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-protection&quot;&gt;2. Protection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, not all social conflict is amenable to resolution. There will probably be those who don’t want to try to solve a conflict by a mutually-agreed-upon compromise of some kind, but want to take whatever they please from others by force, because they think they’re stronger. There is also violent crime to consider, and attacks on a community from the outside. Furthermore, although the fact that resolutions to conflicts are mutually beneficial, and ongoing conflict in a community is costly and destabilizing, will usually be enough to motivate compliance, sometimes decisions made and agreed to in arbitration will need some mechanism of enforcement. To a large degree, diffuse social sanctions can suffice for this; refusing to trade with people, disassociating from them, or criticizing them in ways that can damage their reputation, are actually powerful motivators, and it has the added benefit of allowing each person in the community to make their own decision as to someone’s guilt or innocence and the degree of it, which means no need for central community councils or anything. Nevertheless, sometimes a little more is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all these purposes, I suggest mutual defense associations. These could be composed of, and in turn controlled cooperatively by, the people whom they existed to protect. In other words, these mutual defense associations could be composed of part-time volunteers, maybe rotating by some schedule or maybe just being called into service by proximity, from the community, that answer to the needs of the other people in their community and can call each other up for help as well. By this means, everyone would band together to protect, or come to the aid of, any one of their members, in return for the willingness of the others to do so for each of them, in classic mutual aid fashion. There could be multiple overlapping such institutions, with different bylaws and membership, etc, for each community, not locked down to any territory, nor enacting any set of rigid laws, but merely operating on the basis of the needs of the people in them. They might have rules that their members have to follow to remain a part of the association and gain the benefits therein, or you might get the benefits of the associations imply for being part of the community. There are a myriad of different ways to do it, all equally valid for different situations and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible concern might be that such mutual defense associations might turn into states, but I don’t think that such a situation is any great risk. Without sacred ideas legitimizing the rule of any particular institution, it would be very difficult for any would-be state to grab much power, as everyone would begin leaving it, refusing to pay dues, refusing to obey orders, and joining other mutual defense associations to counteract it. Trying to force every single person within its claimed territory, or even a significant fraction of them, to obey its orders would be a Herculean, or perhaps better yet Sisyphean, task. After all, the state does not perpetuate itself by sheer repression, but through indoctrination into sacred ideas such as ‘law’ and ‘social contract’ and ‘legitimacy,’ as well as a show of intimidation through its police and armies which would nevertheless not be enough to actually control the whole population. Without already having a population indoctrinated in these ideas - as humans have been for millennia, and which we have seen in every so-called ‘power vacuum’ after a state falls - and without already being established and able to levy taxes in order to bolster its resources, a mutual defense association would find it an uphill battle indeed to &lt;em&gt;gain&lt;/em&gt; such resources through taxes, or achieve such an indoctrinated populace, and become anything more than just another gang or organized crime syndicate. Moreover, such a rogue mutual defense association would be a threat to everyone in an anarchist society, so it wouldn’t be unlikely for other mutual defense associations to rush in to disabuse the burgeoning state of its grandiose notions. Thus, a power balance can be achieved through decentralization, where everything balances against each other. In a sense, an anarchist society is a stable equilibrium: perhaps difficult to get into from other equilibrium, but once you’re there, stable enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefit of such a system is that, unlike cops, mutual defense associations wouldn’t be an occupying army that ‘descends from above,’ alien to the communities they patrol, designed to enforce laws deaf to the norms and needs of the communities they walk through. They would be of, by, for, and accountable to the people that they &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; serve and protect. It would be something everyone in the community could take a part in, and a part time affair at that, meaning that everyone who did would be fully part of the community, with other jobs to weave them into it. Thus there would be no special class that performs functions of defense and peace-keeping, which views itself as separate from and superior to everyone else. No more “sheep,” “sheepdogs” and “wolves.” It would just be members of the community doing each other a service, not because it’s their job, but because they get something out of it too. Members of such associations, being members of their community, could also be held accountable for their actions if necessary via the same diffuse social sanctions and even, if necessary, force, that every other member of the community would be subject to. Without the special privileges of authority, they would not be viewed with undue respect, and thus would not benefit from the same lack of accountability as cops. And aren’t the people who use violence in society to protect others those &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; in need of proper accountability and limits, of being forced to be careful and considerate and slow to anger and violence?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, since protectors are just volunteers who, otherwise, are like anyone else, such associations couldn’t claim a monopoly on helping other members of the community. Any member of the community could act to protect the others, so if you saw someone in need of help or protection, you could do what you needed to do, without fear of reprisal from “the authorities.” Of course, if you judged the situation wrong or acted too brutally or whatever, the community could hold you accountable just that same as anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, since these MDAs would be composed of members of the communities they protected, minorities and oppressed classes could have their own MDAs serving their own interests, counterbalancing the power of majorities.  (Imbalances in numbers could easily be made up for with modern military technology such as automatic weapons.) No longer would we have to live in a system where the majority or the minority gets to dictate what happens to everyone, opening up the gates to oppression. People with different interests could abide by different rules and live in different ways, disassociating from each other if necessary, but, as long as live and let live attitudes prevail, living together as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, these communities would not need to ‘win’ any conflict &lt;em&gt;outright&lt;/em&gt;, in the sense that states must absolutely crush their enemies, but only make the conflict costly enough to the people trying to oppress them for it to not be worth it. In turn, because of this structure, that threshold would be far less than under a state: the state is an incredibly efficient, centralized system for enforcement of laws which is considered legitimate, and therefore cooperated with, by nearly everyone in society, and which has no competitors, and has the ability to tax everyone in society, even those it seeks to oppress. It even maintains a separate class of people to actually do its dirty work, separating the people who make the decisions to oppress people from actually having to invest any time, energy, resources, or their own lives in actually enforcing their decisions. MDAs share none of these features - there are competitors, they don’t have sole legitimacy, they can’t tax anyone, let alone everyone, and the people making the decisions are also responsible for carrying them out. How many Republicans do you think would find it worth it to legislate against trans healthcare, for instance, if they actually had to get up out of their armchairs and manhandle doctors and kidnap trans children?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such mutual defense associations could also double as insurance agencies, pooling resources through dues paid by the members that can afford to do so not only for weapons, armor, and training for those that don’t already have them, but also to have a pool of money to pay any reparations that may be assigned to any of their members in case they can’t pay themselves. This would provide a way of avoiding even more conflicts, of course, and taking the burden of reparations off people who may not be doing so well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems similar to this have also existed in history, such as the &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; system of ancient England:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For purposes of security, the most important social unit was the borh. A borh was an association, typically of twelve people, who stood surety for one another’s good behavior. If a member of a borh committed a crime, the other members were committed to bringing him to justice — but also to helping him pay restitution for his crime. (Financial restitution rather than retribution was the normal sentence for most crimes; those who refused to pay restitution were outlawed, that is, placed outside the law — meaning that anyone could kill them with impunity.)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The borh may have originated as a kinship group, but if so, its kin-based aspects soon dwindled; at the height of the Anglo-Saxon system, borhs were purely contractual arrangements. Individuals were free to apply to a borh of their choosing, and members of that borh were likewise free to accept or refuse the applicant; once accepted, an individual was free to leave, and could also be expelled. Since the members of the borh would be held responsible for one another’s actions, there was a strong incentive to police members’ behavior. Likewise, there was a strong incentive to belong to a borh and not be kicked out, because few were willing to deal with someone who belonged to no borh; such a person was in effect an uninsured risk, since he had no fellow borh-members standing surety for him. The borh system thus created powerful incentives for responsible behavior.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another similar system existed in England much later as well, although it focused more on the absolute enforcement of laws and (were forced to) use(d) government courts for prosecution, which obviously wouldn’t work, let alone be acceptable, in an anarchist society:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But before the reign of the Bobbies, English law enforcement relied heavily on organizations known as Associations for the Prosecution of Felons — also known as thief-takers’ associations. Imagine a cross between a Neighborhood Watch group, an insurance agency, and an Old West style posse. People in a particular neighborhood would pool their resources, and supply their own labor, to support their local thief-takers’ association. The association would keep its eyes open for robbers (particularly those who robbed houses displaying the plaque of association membership!). If a crime (against an association member) did occur, the association would hunt down, or pay to have hunted down, the wrongdoer, often cooperating with similar associations in other districts — and then use the pooled resources to pay for the felon’s prosecution in a government court. (Criminal justice was not free in those days.)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-norms&quot;&gt;3. Norms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what sorts of general norms do I think are likely to emerge in an anarchist society that used the sorts of systems I’m proposing? To be quite frank, that’s a question that cannot possibly be wholly answered - in a society that is focused on the needs and interests of the actual individuals involved in conflicts, coming up with norms that serve them, and avoiding hierarchy, domination, and authority instead of enforcing a law or a plan, the norms would be different, sometimes subtly, sometimes drastically, in every place, and even from time to time in the same place. However, if the positive emphasis of anarchism is on self-determination and autonomy, the positive mirror image of domination and subordination, I can venture some guesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I think that traditional property norms would have to disappear. Property, in allowing for absentee dominion over resources which one does not use but which other people do, directly conflicts with self-determination and autonomy, and directly serves domination: if you use something, rely on it for your life in some way, have your interests tied up in it, and yet someone else controls it, that creates a relationship of dependency from you to them which is imbalanced, because you have no control and they have all the control, and they (the owner) can exploit that to control you. We see this sort of relationship between e.g. the capitalist and their workers, or the landlord and their tenants. The absentee owner ‘uses’ their property only to gain dominion over others through state-backed violence, that is the only use they have for it and the only interest they have tied up in it, and interests that require domination are not to be respected in an anarchist society. Refusing them such a ‘right’ to absentee property only serves to prevent domination. Meanwhile, the occupiers and users of such property, if given primacy, take nothing real away from the ‘owner’, just as stepping into a place on the sidewalk which your friend will never set foot in, nor use themself, does not take anything away from them, whereas if they try to prevent you from walking down the sidewalk to somewhere you need to go, they are robbing you of some liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, property does perform some functions that might be useful to protect autonomy in an anarchist society, in allowing the individual to separate herself form the collectivity, so that she does not become dominated by it in the same way she was dominated by the state or the capitalist, beholden to it through dependence on its resources and subjugated to the wills of many others instead of a few. This is why Proudhon said both “property is theft” and “property is liberty.” To quote Proudhon from &lt;em&gt;Theory of Property&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Property is not measured by merit, as it is neither wages, nor reward, nor decoration, nor honorific title; it is not measured by the power of the individual, since labor, production, credit and exchange do not require it at all. It is a free gift, accorded to man, with a view to protecting him against the attacks of poverty and the incursions of his fellows. It is the breastplate of his personality and equality, independent of differences in talent, genius, strength, industry, etc.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where occupancy and use possession comes into play: granting ‘ownership’ of things - the ‘right’ to have primary say in the use of something - to those who actually use or occupy those things and thus have their interests bound up in them, actually &lt;em&gt;bolsters&lt;/em&gt; self-determination, by ensuring that each person has control over the things they depend on, instead of being at the mercy of others. Physical possessions, such as houses, tools, and other things, independent of their fuzzy and ill-defined status as ‘means of production’ - but this relation is perhaps even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; intense for means of production that can be used individually - are often practically direct extensions of a person, and vitally important to ensuring that they are able to act towards their own goals and exercise self-determination. Through protecting this sort of relationship to any physical object, unlike in anarcho-communism which only respects it for objects that can’t be used to produce things, the individual is made capable of separating themselves from the collectivity, so that the collectivity does not become an absentee, dominating force over them. If they, for instance, can operate some means of production productively by themselves, and in fact do so, there is no need to force them to relinquish that means to the collectivity; allowing them to have their means of working for themselves grants greater autonomy. Likewise, having one’s own resources means one is not at the mercy of anyone else, even a democratic collective - one’s own home, say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is not re-instating capitalist property: since &lt;em&gt;all those&lt;/em&gt; who have an interest in something, or who use it, have an equal claim by this logic, shared means of production, for instance, which all use and all maintain, are the property of the group that collectively maintains and uses them; likewise, the products of labor are the property of all those who cooperated to produce it where the relations of mutual aid and cooperation involved in the process of production weren’t broken up by trade to alienate any claims to the products of production; similarly, all those who live in a house own it, all those who regularly work in a field share claim to it, etc. For any one person who uses or occupies things to claim sole possessory rights to it would be to make all the other users dependent on them, and defeat the whole point, not to mention being simply arbitrary. Any decisions made regarding shared objects must either be individual, but not likely to effect the use of others - so if you use a factory machine, maintain it and leave it ready for another to use, and don’t try to use it while someone else is - in the manner of usufructuary, or must be done with the express consent of the others who use the object, either directly (consensus democracy) or through some means agreed-upon beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I do not see any reason to think that even occupancy and use possession will be taken as an absolute law or ‘sacred idea’ to be enforced with prejudice and unilaterally; as I said before, in an anarchist society, conflict resolution is the focus, not Law or Justice (revenge). As such, possession will be protected in the community only insofar as having it as a norm is mutually beneficial to all, a second-order set of ‘rules of thumb’ which are responsive to the underlying needs of the society. If the respect for possession is based on the reciprocal gain to each individual of having their own possessions respected, than if the possessory claims of one set of people become onerous enough, or another set has nothing of their own anyway, then the incentive to respect such possessory titles would evaporate, and they would just take what they need. After all, saying “I will respect you and all your possessions” to a homeless or starving person is utterly laughable as a promise for which to expect anything in return! Likewise, promising to respect the possessions of another when you own everything is stupid and they would have no reason to respect that. Crucially, this wouldn’t just be on an individual level: in an anarchist society, any ‘violations’ of possessory claims would be recognized as no more or less inherently ‘legitimate’ than the claims themselves, and the lack of interests on the part of the violating parties in respecting the possessions of the other party would have to be recognized, and their interests in the objects they took examined and weighed. Thus, the people resolving such disputes would have to focus on making sure the violators gained an interest in supporting general possessory norms, insuring that they no longer need to violate them, in order to resolve the conflict.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this implies, when worked out in the long run, I can’t say for sure. Personally, I envision an economy dominated by local, community-based worker- and consumer- cooperatives, joined and regulated by federations where the power flows from the &lt;em&gt;bottom up&lt;/em&gt; instead of the top down like in a representative democracy (i.e. an elective aristocracy); the gaps between these cooperatives would be filled by independent artisans using advanced home manufacturing equipment, embedded in a market freed from the cash nexus so that people can barter or exchange using whatever they have, or operate on (interest free) debt or credit. I would expect people to claim empty property and build what they need out of what is available to them, so few would be homeless, as they could simply squat unused buildings or build on unused land; likewise, without licensing and regulation, as well as the overbearing control of landlords, people could run businesses doing whatever they know how to do - from hair braiding to cooking - out of their own homes if they needed to. In such an economy, I don’t think there would be anyone, no matter how ‘disabled’ that wouldn’t be able to contribute something, and since they would work on their own terms and receive the full product of their labor, responsible for their labor time, it would be far more fulfilling and worth it. For those who truly couldn’t support themselves, mutual aid would probably be widespread, as well as the distribution of all excess production, which the state currently forces corporations to throw out instead of providing to people&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, to those who need it; on top of that, as I discussed before, ‘theft’ would be a legitimate way to survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I can’t plan out an anarchist society ahead of time, nor do I want to. Nevertheless, I hope I’ve sketched a promising picture of how the basic substructure of such a society could work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://peacerequiresanarchy.wordpress.com/2012/12/30/stateless-societies-ancient-ireland/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stateless Societies: Ancient Ireland&lt;/em&gt; by Joseph R. Peden&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://freenation.org/a/f21l1.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anarchy in the UK&lt;/em&gt; by Roderick Long&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libertarian-labyrinth.org/rambles/rambles-in-the-fields-of-anarchist-individualism-no-3/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rambles in the Fields of Anarchist Individualism&lt;/em&gt; by Shawn P. Wilbur&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is similar to something William Gillis discussed in &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/william-gillis-from-whence-do-property-titles-arise&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;From Whence Do Property Titles Arise?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/4463449/food-waste-laws/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Single Bad Reason We Waste Billions of Pounds of Food&lt;/em&gt; by Jacob Gerson in Time Magazine&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane</name></author><category term="politics" /><category term="anarchism" /><summary type="html">A new vision of an anarchist society, different in important ways from the ones that I’ve presented before, replete with new emphases and contrasts with the society that we currently live in, has been percolating in the back of my head for some time. It has been developing in response to my thoughts about anarchism moving in a less market-oriented and more egoist direction, and as such it looks much more ‘socialist’ and ‘leftist’ than my previous visions ever did.</summary></entry></feed>