<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-07T13:03:43-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Luciferian Locutions</title><subtitle>Unscripted speech, premeditated thought.</subtitle><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Character of an Egoist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/02/character.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Character of an Egoist" /><published>2022-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/02/character</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/02/character.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably one of the most instantaneous assumptions that someone might make, after reading about &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2021/12/08/egoism.html&quot;&gt;my views&lt;/a&gt;, as a moral subjectivist and an egoist, not to mention a Nietzschiean, is that I am someone who holds to no principles, has no character, and simply does whatever I feel might benefit myself in the moment. To a certain degree I have already dealt with why that isn’t true in my first essay on the subject, since I pointed out there that a willing egoist, someone who knows and accepts that they are an egoist, is just someone who is conscious about the fact that the only motivation they have for doing anything is desire, and is no longer willing to accept phantom concepts that appropriate a part of their desires for use as a carrot or a stick to get them to fulfill duties and obligations that are primarily for the benefit, and the power, of others. It does not imply that one must only have self-reflecting desires, or that one must be a sadist or a psychopath whatsoever. Nevertheless, I think it would be helpful to explore in more depth why egoism, as I explain it, does not entail someone who is “evil” or without principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first point is that, obviously, if the desires that we act on are not required to be entirely self-regarding, then human beings, being social creatures, will naturally form desires concerning the well-being of the people around them. Egoism does not rule out natural trust and good feelings among people and communities, and extensive psychological and anthropological shows that when such feelings are not hindered, they naturally grow. Human beings are not inherently benevolent or malevolent, we are a complex mixture and intermingling of both, and what generally causes malevolent action is not the love for causing harm or the total lack of regard for others that is typically portrayed. Instead, it is when our natural social natures are suppressed by forming in-groups and out-groups, or dehumanizing people, or when we are forced by circumstances that are already alienating and degrading, that we tend to take anti-social actions. These can all be mitigated, both by socio-economic changes, but also by philosophy. As soon as the truth is ascertained and arbitrary distinctions built on tradition and phantoms but nothing more are cast aside, people typically feel a sense of comradeship for all other thinking and feeling human beings. This is both because we have a natural ability to feel empathy and compassion for other humans, and because if everyone around you is doing better, then that will benefit you as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, even if egoism does not &lt;em&gt;guarantee&lt;/em&gt; that someone will be benevolent, it certainly does not preclude it. Max Stirner himself said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I love men, too, not merely individuals, but every one. But I love them with the consciousness of my egoism; I love them because love makes me happy, I love because loving is natural to me, it pleases me. I know no ‘commandment of love.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, egoism does not even ask that those who are benevolent towards their fellow human beings tolerate those who are not. Moral subjectivism is not the same as moral relativism. Egoism simply asks that all act according to their heart’s desires, trying to see and think as clearly as possible. If you stand against something, and someone is doing that thing, &lt;em&gt;you may try to stop it&lt;/em&gt;, and others may try to stop you. So if you stand for liberty, equality, and justice (the balance of interests among equals), as I do, then if you see someone violating that, you do not need to wait for a blessing from on high or an objective argument to go out and stop that violation from happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, most people have beliefs about what kinds of societies it would be nice to live in, what is fair, and so on, and those need not be self-serving in an obvious way, especially since when considering a vision of society it is much more likely that your position in it will be random, or on the lower end of average, than that you will be in a position of power, so when advocating for a society it is best to advocate for one from behind a “veil of ignorance.” I for one would much rather live in an egalitarian society than a radically unequal one, because I know that not only would I be freer and better off in the sort of society that does not make one’s rights or well-being contingent on anything, it is unlikely I would end up in power or be able to maintain it, so it would be better to live in a society where there is a balance of power between everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more reasons that an egoist can have for being benevolent, too. For one thing, an egoist must also live in human society, and in human society, reputation, trust, and reciprocal relationships matter enormously. If it is known that you are an individual who is likely to do, and capable of doing, anything at any given moment, merely because it seems to be to your advantage at the time — stealing, backstabbing, etc — then no one will want to interact with you, and you will likely be shunned by those around you. And those suspicions will grow around you even if nothing can be proven, if things just &lt;em&gt;happen&lt;/em&gt; to disappear when you’re around, for instance. Conversely, actually initiating and positively engaging in reciprocal, mutually beneficial relations with people and your community at large is often a very good way to ensure that those people will be ready and willing to do the same for you when you need it. Positive reputation and social relations are a totally rational investment, as well as something that will probably make you feel happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, building habits of acting in ways that are respectful of the interests of others and mutually beneficial for you and them will make acting that way, and resisting harming people (in the vast majority of situations in which doing so is not actually beneficial to you) that much easier. It lowers the cost of a range of actions that are typically more beneficial, useful, and rewarding, and lowers the cost of resisting actions that are more typically self-destructive. Therefore, building positive, pro-social habits is a incredibly rational thing to do, even for someone who is purely self-interested, not to mention a human being who naturally gains joy from the act of helping others and from being around the joy of others. And how do we form such habits? By acting in accordance with them regularly and with conscious intention, even when we don’t want to, so they get ingrained in us! Thus, as Aristotle says, the path to forming a good character is by consciously choosing to act in a good way. In this case, “good” here just means “useful for living a social life,” but the point remains the same. You shouldn’t turn forming these habits, or the habits themselves, into an absolute end-goal or commandment, but nevertheless, taking a somewhat virtue ethical approach to forming positive habits can be very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, one of the things that being a willing egoist does to you is make you more honest. After all, if you accept that the ultimate reason you do anything is because you want to, there is no more hiding behind duty, obligation, tradition, or authority. You must be honest with yourself and others, and others who accept that philosophy will see through any obfuscation you or anyone else attempts to throw up. If you harm someone, they will know, and you will know, that you either harmed them because you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to harm them, or because you &lt;em&gt;don’t care&lt;/em&gt; about harming them. No appeal to a greater good or a duty to king and country will excuse you. You are ultimately responsible to yourself and those around you, especially those you harm, and you must answer for what you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By mirror image, similarly, when you do something that benefits others, everyone will know that it is because you &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to, not out of some sense of obligation or altruism, and that will reflect better on you. After all, someone who does kind things because they love to do them, because they love other people, because doing kind things is natural and pleasing to them, is intrinsically a person that other people will want to be around more than someone who only does kind things because they feel they must, and groans at every giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this is to say that a willing egoist would act just precisely like any other normal person. By  rejecting spooks, and choosing to admit and embrace the fact that we serve our own desires, we free ourselves from the ensnaring web of  culture, society, and authority. Egoists do not recognize any authority above themselves, either ideological, philosophical, or physical. They do not recognize legitimacy as something that some people have and some do not. They may play along with your institutions and your social concepts and means of control, but they do not ingest them and become owned by them.  These spooks that egoists reject the absolute domination of  include  religion, personal responsibility or worth, humanism, morality, civil  society, political participation, to name a few. An egoist may act or believe things that align with these concepts, but these concepts are under the egoist, tools they use or things they adopt and cast aside at will because they  identify with them, not all powerful sacred ideas that hover over their heads. By refusing to serve them unless they serve us, by treating them as rules of thumb at best, and discarding many of them as useless tools of control, egoists end up freer, more ready to achieve their true desires, more direct, and more decisive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a willing egoist might feel more dangerous and less predictable than an unwilling egoist, like a wild animal feels more dangerous and less tame than a domesticated one. That is just fine. Egoists are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; tame animals. But they are just as capable of love, and reciprocity, and all the good and protective and positive aspects of human relations and emotion as anyone else; perhaps moreso, because for them, it is more authentic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><category term="egoism" /><category term="ethics" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I Identify As a Satanist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/01/satanism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Identify As a Satanist" /><published>2022-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/01/satanism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/01/satanism.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Did [Satan] rebel against his maker? It was, as he himself informs us, because he saw no sufficient reason, for that extreme inequality of rank and power which the creator assumed.” — William Godwin, anarchist, 1793&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think, given the rather obvious Satanist imagery that has permeated my blog, not to mention the references to it that are sprinkled throughout my posts, that it is finally time to explain why I am a Satanist. I give a brief explanation of why in my about page, but something like this deserves a much deeper examination than would make sense in an autobiographical blurb. Therefore, in this essay, I aim to explain the way in which and the degree to which I embrace Satanism and Satanist imagery, but most importantly I aim to explain my reasoning for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am what might best be termed a ‘literary’ Satanist. In other words, I am neither a theistic Satanist (someone who believes a literal Satan exists and worships him) nor a member of any organized body of Satanists, such as the Church of Satan. I hold to no creed but my own and no dogma or faith whatsoever, and although I am open to being proven wrong, I do not believe the supernatural exists. I am a Satanist nonetheless, however, because I identify with Lucifer as a symbol, a mythic archetype if you will: he stands for things that I also stand for; I stand for things that he, also, stands for, so I adopt him as my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this I share my Satanism with such illustrious names as Lord Byron and Percy Shelly, as well as Pierre-Joseph Proudhon and Mikhail Bakunin. To quote &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satanism#Literature&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[As a rebel against tyranny] was how Milton’s Satan was understood by later readers like the publisher Joseph Johnson and the anarchist philosopher William Godwin, who reflected it in his 1793 book &lt;em&gt;Enquiry Concerning Political Justice&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Among the romanticist poets to adopt [a positive] concept of Satan was the English poet Percy Bysshe Shelley, who had been influenced by Milton. … Another was Shelley’s fellow British poet Lord Byron… These more positive portrayals also developed in France; one example was the 1823 work &lt;em&gt;Eloa&lt;/em&gt; by Alfred de Vigny. Satan was also adopted by the French poet Victor Hugo, who made the character’s fall from Heaven a central aspect of his &lt;em&gt;La Fin de Satan&lt;/em&gt;, in which he outlined his own cosmogony. Although the likes of Shelley and Byron promoted a positive image of  Satan in their work, there is no evidence that any of them performed  religious rites to venerate him, and thus they cannot be considered to  be religious Satanists.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The figure of Satan, who was seen as having rebelled  against the tyranny imposed by Jehovah, was appealing to many of the  radical leftists of the period. For them, Satan was “a symbol for the struggle against tyranny,  injustice, and oppression… a mythical figure of rebellion for an age  of revolutions, a larger-than-life individual for an age of  individualism, a free thinker in an age struggling for free thought”. The French anarchist Pierre-Joseph Proudhon, who was a staunch critic of Christianity, embraced Satan as a symbol of liberty in several of his writings. Another prominent 19th century anarchist, the Russian Mikhail Bakunin, similarly described the figure of Satan as “the eternal rebel, the  first freethinker and the emancipator of worlds” in his book &lt;em&gt;God and the State&lt;/em&gt;. These ideas likely inspired the American feminist activist Moses Harman to name his anarchist periodical &lt;em&gt;Lucifer the Lightbearer&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of Satan, Proudhon &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libertarian-labyrinth.org/contrun/proudhon-liberty-satan-and-the-ladies-repository-oh-my/&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; in 1858 to the Catholic Church:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Oh! I understand, Monseigneur, that you  do not like liberty, that you have never liked it. Liberty, which you  cannot deny without destroying yourself, which you cannot affirm without destroying yourself still, you dread it as the Sphinx dreaded Oedipus:  it came, and the riddle of the Church was answered; Christianity is no  longer anything other than an episode in the mythology of the human  race. Liberty, symbolized by the story of the Temptation, is your  Antichrist; liberty, for you, is the Devil.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Come, Satan, come, slandered by priests  and kings! Let me embrace you, let me clutch you to my breast! I have  known you for a long time, and you know me as well. Your works, oh  blessed of my heart, are not always beautiful or good; but you alone  give sense to the universe and prevent it from being absurd. What would  justice be without you? An instinct. Reason? A routine. Man? A beast.  You alone prompt labor and render it fertile; you ennoble wealth, serve  as an excuse for authority, put the seal on virtue. Hope still,  proscript! I have at your service only a pen, but it is worth millions  of ballots.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus my Satanism has a long history with thinkers who, like myself, love liberty, and want to throw off the chains of authority so that human beings will be free to seek reason and justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although my Satanism is primarily inspired by a fairly common reading of &lt;em&gt;Paradise Lost&lt;/em&gt; — a poem which I read in my formative years and which, although I do not remember much of it now, has continued to influence me to this day — it is also informed by my reading of the Bible itself. Nevertheless Biblical — or textual in general — accuracy is not what is important to me here. I am not interested in minute textual nitpicks and Biblical hermenutics, I am merely stealing a symbol from the dominant religion of my time and re-purposing it for my own, more positive use. What others think about the historical or scriptural accuracy of my appropriation of Lucifer as a symbol matters &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; little to me at all. Nor are the precise interpretations of Satan that other literary or romantic Satanists have. I am heterodox in everything, including this. That out of the way, let me try to elaborate what I mean when I say that I identify with Lucifer Morningstar as an archetype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lucifer as an archetype in my mind stands for several things. First and foremost, he stands as a rebel against tyranny. It is his rebellion against the cosmic dictatorship of Yahweh that gets him originally cast down from heaven, after all. And the Christian God’s rule &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; cosmic tyranny. He makes up arbitrary rules for his own aggrandizement and glorification, condemning countless numbers to the fiery pits of hell to be tortured for all eternity while simultaneously lifting up others to the golden halls of heaven, where, just by the way, they must spend &lt;em&gt;all of eternity praising him.&lt;/em&gt; He does this on an arbitrary basis, either according to whether we follow his cruel, arbitrary laws which are liable to make us unhappy in the only life we know we have, or according to who is capable of forcing themselves to believe that some Jew from the first century died on a cross and was resurrected, in the face of common sense, proper epistemology, and evidence. Heaven and Hell are, in the final analysis, not related at all to “justice,” but &lt;em&gt;even if they were&lt;/em&gt;, I would not be mollified — for what terrible crime can one be condemned to infinite punishment? Why is repentance possible in this life, but not in the one after, at the only time when one would have the evidence necessary to know that one had committed a sin? And what is the purpose of punishment in the first place, when those who are wronged will be rewarded and made whole either way? Simply cruelty? Revenge? What sort of monstrous version of justice is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to mention the suffering from natural processes that is inflicted on countless people in the here and now every day, nor the fact that this God created the laws of this universe such that human beings are capable not just of desiring to hurt others (which would have been sufficient for “free will”) but of actually carrying out the most horrible forms of torture and depravity on their fellow creatures. Creatures he designed &lt;em&gt;purposefully&lt;/em&gt; to have this evil, this defectiveness, within them, yet whom he nevertheless chooses to hold responsible for that evil and the suffering they cause. This is a God who hardens people’s hearts and then punishes them for being hard-hearted. And he does all this merely so that he can demonstrate his ‘mercy’ by suspending his ‘just’ laws by way of a human sacrifice (of himself, to himself, to suspend rules he made up, no less) to these creatures. Because of course, a self-sufficient God needs validation and love from creatures as far below him as ants are below us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This God is a God who routinely, throughout the Bible, tries to prevent human beings from improving themselves and their situation, expanding in knowledge and power, and living in harmony. This is a God who fears the meager power of his own creation, their ability to get along without his direct interference. This is a God who commits so many countless atrocities over the course of the scriptures of his religion that to document all of them here would take far too long. The point of all this is that the Christian God rules with an iron fist over the cosmos, a might-makes-right attitude, and little care for his creation. As a moral subjectivist, I cannot claim this is “objectively” evil, but I can nevertheless claim that this is the sort of tyrant that I would not stand for, would not obey, would not worship, would not endorse, and that I stand against everything that he stands for. According to the morality which I choose for myself, I declare this evil, and anyone who wishes to side with that which I declare evil can get fucked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, though, it isn’t even the Christian God’s acts that make him insufferable. It is his mere supposed existence that is an offense to an upright sense of self-worth. Whatever he chose to do, his existence, as a cosmic despot whose every whim is metaphysical law, is an affront to the values of anyone who wants to live freely. C.S. Lewis had it right when, in &lt;em&gt;Miracles&lt;/em&gt;, he claimed that the existence of a God that stands above all else is a metaphysical affront to egalitarian principles!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is against this God that Lucifer rebels. In &lt;em&gt;Paradise Lost&lt;/em&gt; his first rebellion  is his attempt to throw off the yoke of the tyranny of Yahweh. And when he and his cohorts are finally cast down to hell, what does he say? That now, at least, although their conditions are terrible, they are free at last to rule themselves. Is this not admirable? Is this not exemplary? To face down an all-powerful cosmic tyrant, knowing the near-certainty of one’s own doom, because even the slight chance of throwing him down and grinding his face into the mud is worth it; and then to accept the consequences, and find freedom and solace in them! Are not the most admirable revolutionaries those who, even if they fail, refuse to give up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the reasons why the early anarchists embraced Satan as a symbol: he represents a rejection of tyranny, of authority, even to the material detriment of oneself, a rejection of comfort in favor of liberty, a rejection of cosmic hierarchy on a scale equally broad. The signs of Satan, such as the pentagram, implicitly shout: Cast down tyranny! Reject authority! No Gods, No Masters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second attribute that I believe Lucifer, as archetype, exemplifies, which I believe is worthy of emulation, is contained within the title of Lightbringer: he is the first freethinker. After all, in what is his initial rebellion, at least in the Bible, contained? In merely telling Eve the truth! Read this passage and tell me that isn’t the case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And he said unto the woman, Yea, hath God said, Ye shall not eat of every tree of the garden? And the woman said unto the serpent, “We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden: But of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the garden, God hath said, ‘Ye shall not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die.’”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And the serpent said unto the woman, “Ye shall not surely die: For God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes shall be  opened, and ye shall be as gods, knowing good and evil.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And when the woman saw that the tree was good for food, and that it was  pleasant to the eyes, and a tree to be desired to make one wise, she took of the fruit thereof, and did eat, and gave also unto her husband with her; and he did eat. — Genesis 3:1-6, King James Version&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘deceiver,’ the ‘father of lies’ — and his first act is to tell human beings the truth, that the fruit of knowledge will not kill Eve, but will instead grant her the one thing God fears in humans: knowledge. Independence. Power like his. This is a tale more like that of Prometheus than a demon! Lucifer Lightbringer asks us to reject faith, dogma, and religion. That is a call I identify with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lucifer’s earliest temptation is the temptation away from swaddled innocence, dependence, and deception, toward the light of truth. It was &lt;em&gt;Yahweh’s&lt;/em&gt; choice to punish beings who, not yet having the concept of “good” and “evil” necessary, could not have understood the harm in what they were doing. It was &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; choice, not Satan’s, to cast humanity out of the garden and curse them with &lt;a href=&quot;[Abortion](https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/01/03/abortion.html)&quot;&gt;painful birth&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/01/29/anti-work.html&quot;&gt;hard labor&lt;/a&gt; for the rest of their days for doing what he must have known in advance and designed them to do. &lt;em&gt;I too&lt;/em&gt; wish to bring light to my siblings. &lt;em&gt;I too&lt;/em&gt; wish to lure them out of the false tranquility of the garden of religion, and the empty assurances found therein, and it is not by my choice that they may be greeted with oppression, hatred, proselytization, and demonization by the agents of Yahweh on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third attribute which I admire the archetype of Lucifer for is his character, which is best exemplified by an early piece of dialogue from &lt;em&gt;Paradise Lost&lt;/em&gt;, which to this day remains my favorite passage, quoted often in part throughout my other writings. It is a stunning bit of character work, as all of Satan’s personality is arrayed before us in that passage, conveniently interwoven and elaborated by Milton’s bombastic genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first admirable attribute of Satan’s character is his commitment to rejecting tyranny and authority, as I said before, and his brave willingness to accept the consequences of that in the name of liberty, reason, and justice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Is this the region, this the soil, the clime,”&lt;br /&gt;
 Said then the lost Archangel, “this the seat&lt;br /&gt;
 That we must change for Heaven?—this mournful gloom&lt;br /&gt;
 For that celestial light? Be it so, since he&lt;br /&gt;
 Who now is sovereign can dispose and bid&lt;br /&gt;
 What shall be right: farthest from him is best&lt;br /&gt;
 Whom reason hath equalled, force hath made supreme&lt;br /&gt;
 Above his equals. Farewell, happy fields,&lt;br /&gt;
 Where joy for ever dwells! Hail, horrors! hail,&lt;br /&gt;
 Infernal world! and thou, profoundest Hell,&lt;br /&gt;
 Receive thy new possessor—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we see his resilience, his self-reliance, his commitment to who he is, his character and being, in spite of his surroundings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…one who brings&lt;br /&gt;
 A mind not to be changed by place or time.&lt;br /&gt;
 The mind is its own place, and in itself&lt;br /&gt;
 Can make a Heaven of Hell, a Hell of Heaven.&lt;br /&gt;
 What matter where, if I be still the same,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we see his pride and awareness of his own worth:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And what I should be, all but less than he&lt;br /&gt;
 Whom thunder hath made greater?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, his courageous commitment to liberty, even in spite of the pain it causes him — and is not the revolutionary who powers through all hardships to be praised?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here at least&lt;br /&gt;
 We shall be free; th’ Almighty hath not built&lt;br /&gt;
 Here for his envy, will not drive us hence:&lt;br /&gt;
 Here we may reign secure; and, in my choice,&lt;br /&gt;
 To reign is worth ambition, though in Hell:&lt;br /&gt;
 Better to reign in Hell than serve in Heaven.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we see his commitment to his comrades:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But wherefore let we then our faithful friends,&lt;br /&gt;
 Th’ associates and co-partners of our loss,&lt;br /&gt;
 Lie thus astonished on th’ oblivious pool,&lt;br /&gt;
 And call them not to share with us their part&lt;br /&gt;
 In this unhappy mansion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, we see his eternal will to continue fighting, even in the face of impossible odds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…or once more&lt;br /&gt;
 With rallied arms to try what may be yet&lt;br /&gt;
 Regained in Heaven, or what more lost in Hell?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, his total commitment to his cause, his egoistic desires and values, above and beyond any notion of good or evil. Like a true egoist anarchist, all that matters to him is the things he values, the things he stands for, and what others call good or evil are just labels to be ignored:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Fallen Cherub, to be weak is miserable,&lt;br /&gt; Doing or suffering: but of this be sure—&lt;br /&gt;
 To do aught good never will be our task,&lt;br /&gt;
 But ever to do ill our sole delight,&lt;br /&gt;
 As being the contrary to his high will&lt;br /&gt;
 Whom we resist. If then his providence&lt;br /&gt;
 Out of our evil seek to bring forth good,&lt;br /&gt;
 Our labour must be to pervert that end,&lt;br /&gt;
 And out of good still to find means of evil;&lt;br /&gt;
 Which ofttimes may succeed so as perhaps&lt;br /&gt;
 Shall grieve him, if I fail not, and disturb&lt;br /&gt;
 His inmost counsels from their destined aim.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are admirable qualities to someone not totally blinded by spooks, phantasms, and slave morality, not bent under the humbling yoke of Judeo-Christian morality, not bent before the altar of the lamb. These are values that, should they be adopted, would create a better society. Do not bend before the authority and domination of others, but instead demand equality, demand justice and reason, even to your detriment. Don’t accept the chains, throw them off! Do not let your circumstances crush or destroy your principles and values, or make you forget your friends. Do not give up hope. Moreover, throw off “good” and “evil”: do not accept the justifications of duty and obligation that others wish to foist upon you. Bow not before the ‘authority’ and ‘status’ of others. Seek your due, ask it without apology, grasp it. See clearly and strive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps most crucially, because it makes all the rest possible: Lucifer fully recognizes how great and powerful he is, second only to God himself. Recognize in yourself your own value likewise. Let no one tell you that all your virtues are like filthy rags, let no one tell you you are a sinner in need of forgiveness for the &lt;em&gt;audacity&lt;/em&gt; to exist or be different. Let no one tell you that your life is meaningless without an eternal master to lord it over you. Know your worth, love it, and embrace it. To you, yourself, you are the most valuable person in existence, and how could it be otherwise? Unconditional self-love is the precondition for happiness. Do not torture yourself, feel no guilt. That does not mean you cannot improve, cannot learn from your mistakes — after all, if you love yourself, should you not also love that even greater and better self that you could be? — but it means that you should not listen to those who want to whisper the words of slave morality in your ears. They seek dominance over you, because they are jealous of the freedom and authenticity and happiness and &lt;em&gt;health&lt;/em&gt; that you have, which they cannot share; and the first step to chaining a person’s soul is convincing them that everything they do should make them guilty by setting them a standard self-admittedly designed to be impossible for them to achieve. To quote Nietzsche from &lt;em&gt;On the Genealogy of Morals&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“How ready they themselves are at bottom to make one pay; how they crave to be hangmen… always ready to spit upon all who are not discontented but go their own way in good spirits… The will of the weak to represent some form of superiority, their instinct for devious paths to tyranny over the healthy — where can it not be discovered…!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The slave revolt in morality begins when ‘&lt;em&gt;ressentiment&lt;/em&gt;’ itself becomes creatie and gives birth to values: &lt;strong&gt;the ressentiment of natures that are denied the true reaction, that of deeds, and compensate themselves with an imaginary revenge.&lt;/strong&gt; While every noble morality develops from a triumphant affirmation of itself, slave morality from the outset says No to what is “outside,” what is “different,” what is “not itself”; and this No is its creative deed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, like Lucifer, reject the resentment of those who are strong and healthy and excellent, who are different than you; reject envy and focus on loving and developing and expressing the excellence within yourself, of achieving the dreams that you have, of expressing your &lt;em&gt;will to power&lt;/em&gt;, which is your desire for self-actualization and self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth attribute of Lucifer that I align myself with is less a product of his characterization in any actual text, and more an association developed by long religious tradition: his association with the marginalized, the different, the freethinkers and the queer people, the individuals and the loners. When someone dares to look different, to throw off tradition, to live differently, to reason with others and convince them to doubt dogma, superstition, and authority; when new things arrive that are strange to people; they are often labeled ‘satanic’ or ‘devilish,’ or ‘demonic.’ Well, for one like myself who wishes to align myself with the marginalized, the queer, the different, the new, the unfamiliar, the unsettling, the uncomfortable, the anti-traditionalist, what better label to associate myself with, than the Satanic, the demonic, the devilish? If I am to be accused of being Satanic because I am transgender, or an anarchist or an atheist, or anti-work, what better thing to do than to simply accept it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is Satanic to reject the narrow, unhappy, arbitrary bounds that Yahweh has set for the righteous life, so be it, I accept it! I wish to be happy and fulfilled and beautiful and excellent in the one life I have, and I wish everyone around me the same — let me be called Satanic, sinful, demonic, for it! Let the accusations come. &lt;em&gt;I accept them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lucifer has a strong association with a rejection of typical Judeo-Christian social norms, prejudices, and prudery because of this. I, too, reject these things, reject them wholeheartedly! There is not one right life, the path is not straight and narrow, let people be happy — let them drink and fuck and fornicate and sodomize! Let them build towers to the heavens and write plays and books and satirize the powerful and the priests! Let them get tattoos and piercings and hormone replacement therapy, let them sing songs and love each other, as many as they like! Let children and women speak before they are spoken to, let them teach, let them tell their patriarchs to fuck off! Life is rich, life is beautiful and colorful and varied and diverse, and I will not stand for the life-denying philosophies of child molesters and idiots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raise a glass to Dionysus!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may be accused, at this point, of adopting an identity that exists purely in contradistinction to something, a purely negative identity. To this, I have three responses. In the first place, I do not think there is anything wrong with having a part of your identity be defined in opposition to something. Doing so is usually termed ‘negative’ and ‘destructive,’ but some things are &lt;em&gt;worth&lt;/em&gt; destroying, some things are &lt;em&gt;worth&lt;/em&gt; being negative about, and wanting to tear something down is just as much a character trait as any other. Nevertheless, it is true that, just like any identity, that should not become one’s whole being. Neither should it become a spook to possess you or a sacred idea to dogmatize. Furthermore, I personally enjoy a duality to my identities: positive, constructive ones that speak to what I want to see, what I believe is true and beautiful, and, in counterpoint, identities to speak to what I stand against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second place, an identity defined in opposition to something is incredibly useful in a world that is dominated by that thing. That is why atheism, the lack of a belief in a god, or anarchism, the opposition to authority, domination, and hierarchy, are such crucial, important labels. Likewise, an identity that places one in counterpoint to rigid social domination by a prudish class, one which has had this dominance for thousands of years and is only relinquishing it with animosity and sloth, is useful and meaningful, and will continue to be until that thing and all things like it have gone away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the third place, Satanism is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a purely negative identity at all. Many of the admirable attributes of Satan make perfect sense even in the absence of the rest of Christianity: being anti-authoritarian, a freethinker, a lightbringer, someone who is above good and evil — where, in all these things, do you see Yahweh? Christ? Religion, even? Yes, perhaps the symbolism of Lucifer would lose some of its power if it were divorced from our cultural context, but I do not believe it would lose all of it, or even most of it, for me at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10&quot;&gt;10&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another purpose, a more cynical one, that my Satanism serves. Although I dislike being edgy for the sake of it, and generally think being edgy is more of a hindrance to communication and constructive conversation than anything else, I also think the imagery and language of Satanism make precisely the right kind of people uncomfortable: the kind of people who exist in precise opposition to the things I stand for. It jogs them out of their comfort zone, and I think that’s a good thing. It also weeds out the people that would never even try to understand or appreciate my message as an anarchist or an atheist: those who see a pentagram or a reference to Satanism and immediately panic or think I am evil, those who are inclined to mock the stereotype of Reddit anti-theists, etc. If someone is so turned off by the pentagram in my website’s logo that they leave, they were never going to be interested in what I had to say anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be clarified at this juncture that I most emphatically do not take a Jungian or Petersonian approach to Lucifer as an archetype. I don’t think he’s some necessary component of my psyche or some precondition for truth or any of that nonsense. I just like him as a symbol, a mythological and fictional entity, like someone might identify with characters like Sisyphus, or Gandalf, or Paul Atreides, or Rand Al’Thor. It just so happens that there is enough symbolism and mythology built up around him that it can linguistically and culturally make sense for me to call myself a Satanist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, then, is why I appreciate the symbolism and archetypal meaning of Lucifer and Satanism. I don’t consider myself a part of any official doctrine or movement of Satanism (although I am not opposed to being identified with the Church of Satan, which does good work), but I think this affinity for him as a symbol is enough to call myself a Satanist if I like. Judge of that what you will.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><category term="religion" /><summary type="html">“Did [Satan] rebel against his maker? It was, as he himself informs us, because he saw no sufficient reason, for that extreme inequality of rank and power which the creator assumed.” — William Godwin, anarchist, 1793</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Is “Anti-Work?”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/29/anti-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Is “Anti-Work?”" /><published>2022-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/29/anti-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/29/anti-work.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wanting work reform is not anti-work. Not wanting to do anything challenging or productive is not anti-work. These are the two primary misconceptions about what it means to be anti-work that I hope to correct. The latter comes from our overt enemies, and the former from those cultists of the &lt;em&gt;status quo&lt;/em&gt; who wish to co-opt our terms and our spaces and destroy the revolutionary character of our ideas, all the while claiming to ally with us — i.e., our &lt;em&gt;covert&lt;/em&gt; enemies. In this essay, instead of arguing head-on against these misconceptions, I want to lay out what I believe it &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; means to be “anti-work,” and the best arguments for that position. In so doing, I hope to at least contribute, in my own small way, to excavating the true meaning of “anti-work” from beneath the many layers of confusion under which it has been buried in current socio-economic discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many foundational texts which the anti-work movement commonly directs people to, Bertrand Russell’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/bertrand-russell-in-praise-of-idleness-11-02-05-22-00-46&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Praise of Idleness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Bob Black’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/bob-black-the-abolition-of-work/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Abolition of Work&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; chief among them; however not only are those texts fairly difficult and somewhat old, I believe their driving force is somewhat blunted by the particular idiosyncrasies of their authors and the times and places in which they were written. In particular, Russell’s scientific socialism and love for planned economies shines through in a seriously unfortunate manner in his essay, and Bob Black’s proposed solutions to the problem of work are… utopian, to be charitable. Therefore, while I cannot claim to be the clearest writer, nor can I claim to have no idiosyncrasies whatsoever, I believe I can nevertheless offer some value by elucidating a pragmatic, market anarchist oriented, and solution-agnostic take on what the core tenets of the anti-work ideology are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I say the word, I do not merely mean any productive or useful activity. For instance, if I have a hobby of writing tutorials to help people learn things, or contributing to open source projects to produce tools that are useful for people, or helping out at the local homeless shelter, those things are not &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;. They may involve labor — strenuous mental or physical activity — but they are not &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;. This is intuitively obvious, but it leads to an interesting question: what, exactly, differentiates work from non-work? It’s not a simple question of what the activity I am engaging in is, after all, since you can work at the local homeless shelter, work as a software developer contributing to open source projects, or work writing teaching material. Neither is it a question of &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; you’re doing an activity: you can be energetic and “pull your weight” at work, and be slothful in hobbies, or vice versa, and the relative character of each kind of activity doesn’t change meaningfully. So what makes work work? Well, if it’s not a question of what you’re doing, or how you’re doing it, then it must be a question of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you’re doing it. If we can understand what motivates work versus what motivates leisure, hobbies, play, and other kinds of activities, we will understand what work &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, and, I propose, it will become clear in the process of elaborating that conceptual analysis why we &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be anti-work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is different about why we work, in comparison to why we do things that aren’t work? Let’s think about activities that we typically don’t consider work for a moment. If an activity is chosen by an individual because it is inherently rewarding or pleasurable, than that isn’t work. That does not mean that the activity must always be pleasurable in the moment, or that one must always want to do that activity over and above other activities, but it means that the &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; one is doing the activity is primarily related to the inherent reward one gets for doing that activity: self-improvement, exercise of one’s capacities, expression of one’s unique personality, etc. For instance, for me the process of writing or programming is its own reward, independent of whether I produce anything in the long run.  For others, drawing, or swimming, or running is its own reward. Therefore, when I am writing or programming mostly for my own edification, because I enjoy the challenge, I am not working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities that we typically enjoy, and don’t consider work, can be &lt;em&gt;transformed&lt;/em&gt; into work, however. Even if I enjoy programming for its own sake, and do it as a hobby, if I get a job as a software developer, suddenly the activity of programming, at least when I am programming for that job, is transformed from what it was &lt;em&gt;into work&lt;/em&gt;. What happened here? What was the crucial difference? Well, why am I programming for my job? Is it simply because I enjoy the challenge, the fulfillment, the development of my capacities? No. That might be why I picked software development as a career, but it’s not why I have a job, or why I am programming for that job. That reason has been dethroned as the dominant reason and been replaced with &lt;em&gt;necessity.&lt;/em&gt; I no longer program because the activity of programming is inherently choiceworthy — instead I program because I need sustenance.  Crucially, I am no longer performing an activity primarily because it is a fulfilling activity, one that improves me or my life; I am performing that activity because I need someone else to reward me. In fact, I am not even performing the activity because I want the product of that activity, because the end goal that the activity will produce is valuable to me. After all, I will be rewarded by my job for programming in a way that is pretty much completely unrelated to what I am actually producing: I will receive monetary compensation, not the actual product of my own labors — a program which I likely care nothing about whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This alienation of the reason for doing an activity from the inherent worth of the activity or its product to the person who is actually performing that activity, through the need for sustenance, is what, of necessity, generates the other negative characteristics of work. After all, if one is compelled to find work in order to survive, and that work does not need to be related to something one finds meaningful, or the product of which one finds valuable, than it is an inevitable outcome that much of the work that people will do will be things that they would never be interested in doing apart from the context of a job. For instance, no, or at least &lt;em&gt;very few&lt;/em&gt; people would find the activity of being a cashier at McDonald’s inherently choice-worthy. The only time when such an activity would be performed would be within the context of work. Likewise, no, or at least very few, people would naturally choose to produce useless enterprise adware apart from the context of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This alienation of the individual human side of the laborer from the work that they do also inherently creates a tendency to make people replaceable cogs in a machine. If the reason the worker has the job is primarily to have someone to do the work, not because they actually want to be there or because the activity in question is relevant to who they are or their values in any way, then the actual person is not really relevant to the job, and therefore they can be replaced with any roughly equivalent person. People become workers, and workers are human resources, to be shuffled around at need and replaced when they are broken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work separates people from the good things in life, the things that make life worth living, because the good things in life, the things that make life choice-worthy for its own sake, are the things that are choiceworthy in themselves, that people would choose without the threat of deprivation looming over them. Work separates people from the parts of the human experience that are the most valuable. It separates parts of people’s lives from their individuality, making them spend time alienated from themselves by alienating them from their values. This is not a binary thing, of course, and some work will do this more harshly than other work, but this is an inherent property of work. This is why work must be viewed not as the defining feature of a person or their worth, not as a virtuous activity which demonstrates strength of character and worth to society, but as a necessary evil, something to be minimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These properties of work, although they are inherent to it and cannot be separated from it, are exacerbated by present capitalist society. For one thing, the defining feature of capitalism is that workers are beholden to bosses and capitalists that dictate what they must do with their labor time. This means that not only is the labor they do not an activity they would choose to do of their own accord absent the necessity that survival presents, even the choice of &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to do it is robbed from them. Bosses tell them when to work and how much, what to work on, who to work with, how to organize that work, set quotas and deadlines, rate productivity and dictate compensation. Bosses and capitalists are the feudal lords of their corporate fiefdoms, subjecting their employees to the sort of surveillance and control that would be unimaginable were it perpetrated by the State. A worker’s autonomy is already diminished by the need to work to live, as autonomy diminishes in proportion with which choices are restricted and the severity of consequences increase; but capitalism takes advantage of this loss of autonomy, and the existence of property, to leverage it into fresh new insults. Workers spend their lives under the direction of others, and more of their personality is sliced away from their time to live thereby. The less autonomy one has, the less one’s actions and activities reflect one’s personality and individuality, and the less one is able to actually live as oneself: the less you actually &lt;em&gt;exist&lt;/em&gt; as anything but a wraith trapped in the back of your own mind. Your life is stolen from you, in those hours, to the proportion that one’s autonomy is limited! And the less that one’s actions, the changes one expresses in the world, are a product of one’s autonomy and self-expression, the less one exists to the world. Capitalism takes people and kills them, a little at a time, within their own heads and lives, and to the world outside. They fade away, their self-expression gone, their individuality gone. Work is death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about when we are not working? Even in leisure, work’s rotting zombie hands, the hands of the living dead, who walk and make but do not live, grasp you. What we call leisure is mostly spent recovering from work done previously, so that we can be ready to work again soon: work takes up roughly half of our adult waking lives on average, not even counting the other things we have to do, such as chores and commuting, and so when we have time off from work, most of that remaining time must be spent simply recovering enough from work to do it all again on Monday. There is rarely enough energy left over for us, let alone enough time, to actually engage in things that are an expression of our individuality, things that are not just choiceworthy for their own sake but fulfilling and productive instead of simply restful. In essence, even when we are not working, work steals from us who we are, kills us while we still breathe. To quote Bob Black in &lt;em&gt;The Abolition of Work&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Leisure is nonwork for the sake of work. Leisure is the time spent  recovering from work and in the frenzied but hopeless attempt to forget  about work. Many people return from vacation so beat that they look  forward to returning to work so they can rest up. The main difference  between work and leisure is that work at least you get paid for your  alienation and enervation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when we finally do retire, we are typically far past our prime, decaying already, too old and slow to do any of the things we really wanted to do, if we even remember what they were. Work kills dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences of this are dire. If we spend most of our lives taking the orders of others, doing things we don’t care about instead of developing talents, with no time to do anything vigorous and difficult outside of work (even things that we would otherwise find fulfilling), if we spend our whole lives being replaceable, homogeneous cogs in a machine not of our own making or direction, focusing on a narrow activity and a narrow subject matter, what do we become? We become used to subjugation and authority, used to following orders, narrow people with narrow minds and narrow skills that we don’t care about. And we reproduce the patterns that we have been subjected to, of authority and alienation, on those around us. There is no time to develop intellect, no chance to develop independence and rebelliousness. We become good citizens, good subjects, good workers — and bad humans, bad individuals, bad people. Work kills our souls. This has been understood and recognized by the elite class since time immemorial. Given little or no work, people learn, develop skills and concerns for the wider picture, their minds are given a chance to stretch and grow, and so are their bodies and their capacities. People who are free from work are people who are free. People who are indomitable, intelligent, creative, productive, beautiful. To quote Nietzsche from &lt;em&gt;Daybreak: Thoughts on the Prejudices of Morality&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the  glorification of ‘work’, in the unwearied talk of the ‘blessing of  work’, I see the same covert idea as in the praise of useful impersonal  actions: that of fear of everything individual. Fundamentally, one now  feels at the sight of work — one always means by work that hard  industriousness from early till late — that such work is the best  policeman, that it keeps everyone in bounds and can mightily hinder the  development of reason, covetousness, desire for independence. For it  uses up an extraordinary amount of nervous energy, which is thus denied to reflection, brooding, dreaming, worrying, loving, hating; it sets a small goal always in sight and guarantees easy and regular  satisfactions. Thus a society in which there is continual hard work will have more security: and security is now worshipped as the supreme  divinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, people who are free from work are good citizens in a sense just the opposite of the typical sense, the sense that means people who fall in line with the expectations of civil society. They become, instead, good citizens in the sense of people who are concerned with politics, and authority, are engaged in it actively and directly, who understand it and learn about it. To quote Aristotle from &lt;em&gt;Politics&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But at present we are studying the best constitution, and this is the constitution under which the state would be most happy, and it has been stated before that happiness cannot be forthcoming without virtue; it is therefore clear from these considerations that in the most nobly constituted state, and the one that possesses men that are absolutely just, not merely just relatively to the principle that is the basis of the constitution, the citizens must not live a mechanic or a mercantile life（for such a life is ignoble and inimical to virtue, nor yet must those who are to be citizens in the best state be tillers of the soil（for leisure is needed both for the development of virtue and for active participation in politics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, for Aristotle this was reason to grant only idle nobility true citizenship, but there are independent reasons to think that even those who are less free from work than others should still be as in control of their own lives as possible, so instead I propose to turn Aristotle’s ideas on their head: the need for only the most educated and free from work to be those with political say is driven by the fact that, in a governmental system, everyone’s choices as citizen effect everyone else coercively through the apparatus of law. In an anarchist society, only those directly involved and effected by some matter have a say in it, so the choices and actions of those who have nothing to do with you cannot effect you. Each is free to make choices for themselves but no one else. Therefore, it hurts no one if those who are less free from work are granted as full autonomy as possible to live their lives how they wish; so instead of limiting autonomy, we should liberate everyone from work so they each can be better masters of themselves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is why we should seek to minimize the amount of work we must do, even if that means giving up some material comforts, since an hour of life itself is more valuable than almost any product except those that directly and greatly enhance the rest of the hours of life left over. It is also why the worth of a person should not be judged in terms of what work they do. Work is, typically at least, not representative of who they are. It is done merely so that they can survive, nothing more. People’s worth as human beings should not be questioned or parametirized at all, as that is a route that leads directly to a hellish society; nevertheless, someone’s praiseworthiness should be judged in terms of what they do &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; of work. Their hobbies, their art, their relationships, their actions. Even outside of work,we should not judge others or ourselves too harshly, for we must keep in mind the vampiric effect work has on all of life’s other activities. Fight to build a meaningful life outside of work. Join communities, write, draw, paint, find &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; means of self-expression, some means of challenging yourself and developing your capacities, outside of work, something that embodies you. Fight for it! Battle for it with all your heart and soul, use your teeth if you have to. Remember always that &lt;strong&gt;we work to live, we do not live to work.&lt;/strong&gt; Cast off the chains of the Protestant Work Ethic! Tell the world to fuck off! ‘Idle hands do the devil’s work’? Become a Satanist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I’ve painted a grim and desperate pictur of an individual battling against the grinding mechanistic forces of a society bent on zombifying them. Is there an alternative? Until we achieve a post-scarcity society I do not think we can fully eliminate work, but nevertheless I think it is entirely possible to alleviate the properties of work that make it so inimical to human existence by changing the structures and incentives of our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, there is the distribution of work itself. If we allow the productivity increases that automation brings to be harnessed to decrease the workload of the average worker, while keeping their pay the same, instead letting what should be a good thing for everyone turn into unemployment and starvation for some and continued overwork for others, that in itself will bring massive changes in the future, potentially solving many of the problems that people fear automation will bring. After all, one of the major fears of automation will be that since the total number of hours that need to be worked in a particular industry to maintain a certain level of production will fall, fewer workers will be employed. If we, instead, went with a solution that distributed work more equitably, this wouldn’t be an issue, killing two birds with one stone. To quote Bertrand Russel from &lt;em&gt;In Praise of Idleness&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Suppose that, at a given moment, a certain number of people are engaged  in the manufacture of pins. They make as many pins as the world needs,  working (say) eight hours a day. Someone makes an invention by which the same number of men can make twice as many pins: pins are already so  cheap that hardly any more will be bought at a lower price. In a sensible world, everybody concerned in the manufacturing of pins would  take to working four hours instead of eight, and everything else would  go on as before. But in the actual world this would be thought  demoralizing. The men still work eight hours, there are too many pins, some employers go bankrupt, and half the men previously concerned in  making pins are thrown out of work. There is, in the end, just as much  leisure as on the other plan, but half the men are totally idle while  half are still overworked. In this way, it is insured that the  unavoidable leisure shall cause misery all round instead of being a universal source of happiness. Can anything more insane be imagined?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How, without a planned economy, do we achieve such an equalization in the distribution of labor? Well, if workers are placed in control of themselves and their production, it is clear that they will have an incentive to preserve their employment that is much higher than that of the capitalist. This is borne out in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fiftybyfifty.org/2021/06/workers-at-cooperatives-report-high-job-satisfaction-and-community-engagement/&quot;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt; which show that worker cooperatives are much less likely to fire workers. So, if there is less work to be done, instead of firing workers, the incentive will be to simply decrease the amount of work that each worker does equally, as necessary. And since production is the same, everyone can continue being paid the same amount even while they work fewer hours, while maintaining the same cost/income ratio for the business as a whole. Paying workers in terms of overall production, instead of blindly tallying up hours, would again be more incentivized in a situation where workplace democracy grants workers control over their own compensation, as compared to a traditional capitalist structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Proudhon makes a similar point in &lt;em&gt;What is Property?&lt;/em&gt; in the context of differences between the productivity of workers and economic downturns, which applies in this case too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In printing-offices, where the laborers usually work by the job, the  compositor receives so much per thousand letters set; the pressman so  much per thousand sheets printed. There, as elsewhere, inequalities of  talent and skill are to be found. When there is no prospect of dull times (for printing and typesetting, like all other trades, sometimes  come to a stand-still), every one is free to work his hardest, and exert his faculties to the utmost: he who does more gets more; he who does less gets less. When business slackens, compositors and pressmen divide up their labor; all monopolists are detested as no better than robbers or traitors.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;There is a philosophy in the action of these printers, to which neither economists nor legists have ever risen. If our legislators had  introduced into their codes the principle of distributive justice which governs printing-offices; if they had observed the popular instincts, — not for the sake of servile imitation, but in order to reform and generalize them, — long ere this liberty and equality would have been established on an immovable basis, and we should not now be disputing about the right of property and the necessity of social distinctions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It has been calculated that if labor were equally shared by the whole number of able-bodied individuals, the average working-day of each  individual, in France, would not exceed five hours. This being so, how  can we presume to talk of the inequality of laborers? It is the &lt;em&gt;labor&lt;/em&gt; of Robert Macaire that causes inequality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insofar as workers are associated, and each have an equal claim on the means of production they share, no worker would be able to claim more of the shared task than another, throw the other off the tools and stop them from producing merely because there is limited work or because they are more productive, since to have the leverage to do so would imply power over the other workers and a greater say in the use of the means of production, which would mean the workers aren’t associated but put into a hierarchy. Therefore, in conditions of equality and shared means of production, i.e. in worker cooperatives, the distribution of work would be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, returning possession of the means of production, and along with it authority over the workplace, to the hands of the workers who use and maintain  the means of production and have the hands-on knowledge necessary to better determine how to guide their enterprise would have further benefits in alleviating the problems that capitalism exacerbates in work. Most importantly, it would give workers greater autonomy to decide when, how, and on what they work, giving them back some of the self-determination that capitalism alienates. Additionally, it would mean the elimination of profit in the traditional sense, since workers would get 100% of the income not spent on costs, investment, and maintenance, in turn meaning that the number of hours they need to work to get by would decrease. Not only that, but worker cooperatives &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fiftybyfifty.org/2021/06/workers-at-cooperatives-report-high-job-satisfaction-and-community-engagement/&quot;&gt;tend to have much more egalitarian pay structures&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenation.com/article/archive/worker-cooperatives-are-more-productive-than-normal-companies/&quot;&gt;respond better and more sustainably to economic downturns, and are more productive in general&lt;/a&gt; (and more productivity, as I mentioned above, leads to less work but the same pay in conditions of equality). There are many more benefits of worker cooperatives, covered in the previous two sources, and many misconceptions about them that are untrue. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uk.coop/resources/what-do-we-really-know-about-worker-co-operatives&quot;&gt;Quoting from another great resource&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Worker co-operatives are larger than conventional businesses and not
necessarily less capital intensive&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Worker co-operatives survive at least as long as other businesses and have more stable employment&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Worker cooperatives are more productive than conventional businesses, with staff working “better and smarter” and production organized more efficiently&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Worker co-operatives retain a larger share of their profits than other
business models&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Executive and non-executive pay differentials are much narrower in worker co-operatives than other firms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also &lt;a href=&quot;https://c4ss.org/content/14497&quot;&gt;theoretical&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://c4ss.org/content/18100&quot;&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt; to think workplace democracy is a superior method of organizing things economically, meaning that in organizing in a way that makes work less onerous, we are also &lt;em&gt;gaining&lt;/em&gt; something as a whole, economically speaking!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For productive pursuits that don’t require large scale cooperation between many workers and heavy industry equipment (a category that is only growing as the means of production get smaller, more self-contained, and easier to use, as we’ve seen with Maker communities), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/i/independent-contractor.asp&quot;&gt;independent contracting&lt;/a&gt; and artisanship can fill in the gaps as well, providing greater autonomy and control over one’s working conditions and compensation; and with the elimination of absentee property in the means of production, so that capital can only be sold but not rented, it would be significantly easier for people to obtain the means of production they need to start their businesses without indenturing themselves to a capitalist. Combined with &lt;a href=&quot;https://geo.coop/story/crowdfunding-worker-co-ops&quot;&gt;crowdfunding&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Credit_union&quot;&gt;credit unions&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mutual_savings_bank&quot;&gt;mutual banking&lt;/a&gt; run by their members and therefore run for the benefit of the working class and worker cooperatives (harnessing debt and market-limited inflation for the benefit of the working class instead of economic elites), these solutions, while far from perfect, would, I believe, help significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other things we can do too that are less direct and economic, and more socio-cultural, but no less effective and important. For one thing, a widespread cultural recognition of the fact that work is not only detrimental to the lives of those who do it, and not meaningfully related to their worth as a person (neither by how much work they do, or &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; work they do), could completely change the character of the workplace. No longer would working eighty hour weeks or staying up all night to work on something be a badge of honor, thereby creating the expectation that good employees give their lives over completely to the corporation (or cooperative). No longer would people who want to have a life outside of work have to compete for jobs with a millions-strong army of those who are have been brainwashed into not wanting such a thing. No longer would bosses expect long hours, complete commitment, and an identity built around work, and so no longer would workers be shamed into letting the rest of their lives wither and die in order to become the workaholic that everyone expects. No longer would settling for a job that is easy and undemanding, but fulfilling, or just enough to get by (such as being a dog walker), in order to focus on other things in your life that you value, be considered a mark of Cain. We also shouldn’t begrudge those who are idle, free to pursue their interests (unless they are so at the coercive expense of others), we should want that for &lt;em&gt;everyone.&lt;/em&gt; We should develop a culture that gives people the tools to use their true leisure (not work-leisure) productively, fulfillingly, and effectively, instead of just judging people for not knowing how to use idle time and ending up wasting it. Shifting the cultural perception of work could have &lt;em&gt;massive&lt;/em&gt; implications for what work is like even without the major socialist upheaval of the structure of our economy that I propose above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can aspire to more, too. It is not impossible to imagine a society which, although primarily organized around the incredible freedom and distributed calculation abilities of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://c4ss.org/content/1738&quot;&gt;freed, anti-capitalist market&lt;/a&gt;, is erected on the foundational bedrock not of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neoliberalism&quot;&gt;indifferent and narrow self-interest&lt;/a&gt; (perhaps better termed greed), or on authority (whether &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_democracy&quot;&gt;democratic&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marxism%E2%80%93Leninism&quot;&gt;otherwise&lt;/a&gt;) and forced redistribution, but on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519300921118&quot;&gt;equally human&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/108/32/13335&quot;&gt;equally natural&lt;/a&gt; instinct for &lt;em&gt;reciprocity&lt;/em&gt;: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://whatis.techtarget.com/definition/gift-economy&quot;&gt;free gift&lt;/a&gt; of surplus produce to those who need it, in the expectation that they will reciprocate toward you or the whole community in whatever way they can, even if it is not a way that can be economically evaluated. This is supremely rational, in that fostering good will with other members of your community when they are in need instead of you, and a community of goodwill and sharing in general, while it might cost you in the moment, provides insurance against a future situation in which &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; are in need. Importantly, this logic relies on the fact that the reciprocal gifts that everyone gets and gives are not too targeted, or calculated too exactly; otherwise the benefit of the “insurance” that such reciprocality gives evaporates into a cold calculation of equal value and you don’t gain that much. Importantly, although anarcho-communists talk about the gift economy often, a true gift economy assumes possession “rights” in the things one buys, sells, and produces in other areas of society; after all, something can’t be a &lt;em&gt;gift&lt;/em&gt;, and can’t be &lt;em&gt;from you&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;to someone else&lt;/em&gt; unless some notion of possession is in play. In a society like this, the semi-coerced, autonomy-destroying nature of work would evaporate almost completely: the means to survive could be provided largely freely to those who cannot pay, and the only expectation would be &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; contribution to society, or some show of productivity or working on something interesting, in return. Think of it kind of like a more distributed, loose version of a Patreon: as long as you’re doing something interesting to some people, at least your basic needs can be provided for. Something like this can be seen in things like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/crimethinc-the-really-really-free-market&quot;&gt;“Really Really Free Market”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few of the solutions I could think of, and I know people far more creative, well-read, and wiser than me can think of more. The important point is that there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; things we can do to make work better, both in the here and now and the long term, so we shouldn’t give up, shouldn’t despair and give up our radical politics and radical philosophy for the centrist siren call of “work reform.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, being anti-work is about recognizing that work is a necessary evil, nothing more. As such, the amount of work to be done, and the alienating nature of that work, must be minimized as much as possible. This is the inherent radicalism of the anti-work movement. We do not want work reform. We want work revolution, and work minimization. We recognize that the inherent loss of autonomy for the worker, both in not having control over the means of production and in not owning the product of their work, that comes with capitalism is inimical to these goals. Therefore we do not want the subjugation of the worker to a feudal lord, a capitalist, a worker’s communist party, or a collective. Do not join this movement unless you are a socialist, an anarchist, and unless you understand why &lt;strong&gt;work is death.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><category term="anti-work" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="economics" /><category term="human-being" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Fuzzy Bayesian Analysis of Deductive Argumentation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/26/bayesian-analysis-of-argument.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Fuzzy Bayesian Analysis of Deductive Argumentation" /><published>2022-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/26/bayesian-analysis-of-argument</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/26/bayesian-analysis-of-argument.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve finally gotten around to writing out some of the more fundamental components of my epistemology,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I can at last proceed to writing one of the articles that I’ve been planning to do pretty much since I started writing on this blog months ago: a fuzzy Bayesian analysis of deductive philosophical argumentation. This was inspired in part by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ybUW693C8UY&quot;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; of how arguments work on the part of Dr. Graham Oppy. In that interview, he discusses how deductive arguments in philosophy are actually far less effective than they are typically supposed to be, at least in more classically-inclined circles (e.g. philosophy of religion). When I heard him talk about that, I immediately realized that what he was saying could easily be formalized by an application of Bayes’ rule, and that this would serve to demonstrate the strength and coherence of his more holistic theory-focused approach to philosophy as a separate method from the traditional deductive approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the goals of this essay are, first, to do an analysis of the structure of deductive arguments in Bayesian and pragmatic terms; second, on the basis of this analysis, assess the efficacy and pitfalls of such deductive arguments; and finally, third, to sketch an alternative approach to philosophical argumentation, based on comparing holistic theories on the basis of intellectual cost and explanatory power, and compare the pros and cons of that approach with the traditional argumentative approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An argument typically takes the form of a set of premises, which are logical propositions that are supported by further argumentation or evidence, and a conclusion, which is also a logical proposition, derived by the rules of the logical system being used from the foregoing premises. An argument is &lt;strong&gt;valid&lt;/strong&gt; if the conclusion &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; follow from the premises &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; they were true, while an argument is &lt;strong&gt;sound&lt;/strong&gt; if the premises are true. An example of a valid and sound argument, according to the definitions given above, would be something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Proposition&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;All women are mortal&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alexis is a woman&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;∴&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alexis is mortal&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, there are two premises and one conclusion, and the conclusion follows from the premises according to certain logical rules of inference. Furthermore the premises are true (so far as I am aware!). Therefore, this is an argument, and it is both valid and sound. Arguments can be represented in various notations, with various rules of inference, from classical Aristotalian logic to modal logic; in this essay I will be using propositional logic translated into English, primarily in the interest of easier typesetting and reading for those not used to mathematical logic, but also because the ins and outs of logical systems and notation are not really relevant to the more general analysis of logical arguments I am attempting to do, surprising as that may seem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, when dealing with deductive arguments in philosophy, the premises are taken to be either true or false, and by extension the argument is either sound or unsound, the conclusion either demonstrated or undemonstrated. The problem with this approach is that, although it is reasonable to assume that, concerning the objective state of the world, propositions are either descriptive of it or not descriptive of it, within the limits of human knowledge propositions can never be taken to be binary like that. We can never be absolutely certain of the truth or falsity of a proposition about the external world, and pretending that we can for the sake of constructing an argument is likely to lead to error. We instead should apportion our level of certainty in a proposition (premise) according to the level of evidence we have for it and its inherent improbability, which means that we should have a spectrum of credence levels about propositions, not just a binary true/false judgment concerning them. Furthermore, if we have uncertain credence levels in the premises of an argument, the conclusion of that argument, whose truth is &lt;em&gt;derived&lt;/em&gt; from a combination of those premises, should have a credence level proportional to the chance that all of the premises are true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has two implications for the form that philosophical arguments take. First of all, anyone reading an argument should plug in their confidence levels in each of the premises and multiply them together to ascertain how confident they should be in the conclusion of the argument algorithmically. Second of all, if the purpose of the argument is to establish the truth of its conclusion, instead of merely establish a relation between the premises and their conclusion, then the premises themselves need to be proven sound, and as an extension, confidence levels must be provided by the author of the argument for the premises, to encapsulate how well-evidenced they think the inputs to their argument are, to justify the confidence they have in the truth of the conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of all this, the proper form that a philosophical argument should take is something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Proposition&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Credence&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;60%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;78%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;∴&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is just one problem with the format of this argument: it doesn’t take into account the inherent improbability of the conclusion and the other evidence that might be available for or against the conclusion, including other arguments for or against the conclusion. It treats the argument as an epistemic island, isolated from everything else. This is obviously wrong, since arguments such as &lt;em&gt;reductio ad absurdum&lt;/em&gt;, where, by valid argument, an absurd conclusion is drawn from supposedly sound premises, thereby demonstrating that one of those premises must actually be false, are a recognized form of argumentation. If a &lt;em&gt;reductio&lt;/em&gt; is to work, knowledge about the plausibility or credibility of a conclusion must be drawn from &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; the sphere of the one argument that is being made, either from other available evidence, or from inherent improbability (metaphysical or epistemic cost) of the conclusion itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate the statistical validity of the &lt;em&gt;reductio&lt;/em&gt; in a fuzzy Bayesian framework, we just need to realize that if you are looking at an individual argument (if there is only one argument for a certain proposition instead of a set of them), if the prior probability of the proposition in the conclusion is low enough, even if it is still greater than 50%, it can be a good idea to look through the list of premises and see if there are one or more premises that would cost less to reject than it would cost to accept the conclusion. For instance, if there is a premise that is more likely wrong than the conclusion is likely to be true given the prior probability, even if in a vacuum both are more likely to be true than not, your overall system of beliefs will be more likely to be true if you reject the premise that has a lower probability of being true than the conclusion does based on your other evidence concerning it. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Proposition&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;%&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;70%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;90%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;∴ (A)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;~51%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the prior probability of proposition \(A\) is \(20%\), then it is more probable that premise (1) is wrong than that the conclusion is true from an inherent standpoint, so we can reject premise (1), and the cost to the overall probability of our knowledge-web will be 70% instead of 80%. This is a way to both mathematically demonstrate how a &lt;em&gt;reductio&lt;/em&gt; works, and at the same time rationally determine (given enough information) &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; premise in a &lt;em&gt;reductio&lt;/em&gt; should be rejected. Notice that, just as with a regular reductio, given its premises this argument still serves as a valid demonstration of its conclusion, which &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be factored into one’s overall credence in the proposition in the conclusion, so &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; one chooses to “bite the bullet” and accept the reductio the math still works out — you just have an overall epistemic database that is less likely to be accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, this transform is actually not limited to obvious cases of &lt;em&gt;reductio&lt;/em&gt;, where the conclusion is clearly contradictory or ridiculous. It can work in &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; case where the conclusion of an argument is unlikely enough to outweigh whatever &lt;em&gt;prima facie&lt;/em&gt; appearance of truth the premises of the argument may have. This is why “one person’s &lt;em&gt;modus ponens&lt;/em&gt; is another’s &lt;em&gt;modus tollens&lt;/em&gt;.” Although you may not find the conclusion of your argument particularly unlikely, and the premises strong, and therefore run the argument forward, if I find your conclusion unlikely enough (based on having access to different evidence or a different assessment of its inherent improbability) I can just run your argument backwards. This is one of the reasons that deductive arguments in philosophy are ineffective: none of the premises of your typical metaphysical argument are actually sound enough to prevent someone from converting any &lt;em&gt;modus ponens&lt;/em&gt; into a &lt;em&gt;modus tollens&lt;/em&gt; if they don’t like your conclusion; all that can be done when this occurs is to discuss the relative merits of the holistic metaphysical theory and knowledge web which the affirmation or rejection of a premise entails. I’ll talk more about this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This of course does not solve the general problem of how to incorporate multiple deductive arguments and other evidence for a proposition into a confidence level in that proposition, however. Luckily, this is (despite the amount of time it took me to figure this out) not that hard to calculate. Essentially, the probability that the proposition under consideration is true, given evidence calculated into a Bayesian posterior probability, as well as a set of arguments that have a certain chance of being sound and therefore demonstrating the proposition, is the probability of at least one of these “events” actually “happening” (one of these methods actually being sound/accurate and therefore making the proposition true), or the probability of the union of all these events. So:&lt;/p&gt;

\[P(H) = P(\bigcup_{i=1}^n P(A_i) \cup P(H|E))\]

&lt;p&gt;Where \(H\) is the proposition under consideration, \(A\) is the set of all arguments for \(H\), \(P(H\|E)\) is the probability of H given any empirical data (calculated via Bayes theorem), although it also encapsulates the prior probability of \(H\), and is in fact equal to it if there is no empirical data available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that, crucially, each argument in \(A\) must be strictly independent of all of the others. If any group of arguments are intertwined, such that if one is true it increases the chances that others are true, or if one is true it necessitates that the others are true (which can happen even for arguments that don’t at first appear to be identical, if they use similar propositions, assumptions, or argumentative forms, or if the secondary conclusions of one argument form premises in another argument that uses them in a different way to arrive at the same conclusions), then the arguments that are intertwined must be reduced to a single argument, to keep \(A\) a proper set where each element is strictly unique. This can be done by selecting the strongest argument out of the group of similar arguments, melding them together, or any other process that seems fit — this is a process that I can’t provide a general theorem for, since it will depend on the particularities of the arguments in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I move on to the next phase of this essay, let me briefly discuss a few other miscellaneous notes which, while probably intuitively obvious, still deserve to be stated explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, when a premise is actually the combination of multiple propositions through various conjunctions, the probability of the premise being true is constituted by the individual probabilities of each of the propositions which compose the premise, combined according to the statistical rules for each of the conjunctions involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, following on from points I made in my first essay on fuzzy Bayesian logic, assigning specific probabilities to propositions and arguments is a very dangerous game, more likely to lead to nonsense and the appearance of certainty than it is to actually get you closer to the truth. The point of these mathematical equations is more to demonstrate general rules of thumb and approaches from combining or relating the fuzzy, intuitive confidence levels you have in your head. I only specify specific values for things to make the examples a bit easier to understand, but you have to realize that they’re just toy examples with random values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing you might have noticed while I was going through the examples above is that, on the whole, deductive arguments just &lt;em&gt;aren’t that effective&lt;/em&gt;. After all, if you need all of the premises of your argument to be true simultaneously for the conclusion to be true, that’s a really big burden; the probability that you’ll get what you want given that we don’t live in a world of absolute certainty scales inversely geometrically with the number of premises you have. This is why science, which increases statistical credences in hypothesis by way of going out and checking them directly, where the only possible error is the likelihood of getting a result that makes it look like your hypothesis is true without it actually being true, is so much more effective than armchair logic. Instead of building a conclusion on a house of cards that could fail if even a single premise turns out to be wrong, when &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of them have a non-insignificant chance of being wrong, it just skips directly to demonstrating whether the final proposition you are interested in proving or disproving is a useful way to look at the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also why arguments that have a lot of premises, while they look impressive, are actually incredibly dubious and weak. After all, the more premises you have, the more certain you have to be in all your premises to have even the bare minimum level of certainty in your conclusion. Take, for example, Plantinga’s modal ontological argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There is a possible world &lt;em&gt;W&lt;/em&gt; in which there exists a being with maximal greatness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Maximal greatness entails having maximal excellence in every possible world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Maximal excellence entails omniscience, omnipotence, and moral perfection in every possible world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;So in &lt;em&gt;W&lt;/em&gt; there exists a being which is omniscient, omnipotent, and morally perfect in every possible world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;So in &lt;em&gt;W&lt;/em&gt; the proposition “There is no omniscient, omnipotent, and morally perfect being” is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;But what is impossible in one possible world is impossible in every possible world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;So the proposition “There is no omniscient, omnipotent, and morally perfect being” is impossible in the actual world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;So there is in the actual world an omniscient, omnipotent, and morally perfect being.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the argument to justifiably even slightly budge someone’s credence in the theory that a god exists up from being agnostic or even negative toward it, the soundness probability of the argument needs to be at least \(51%\). That means that the probabilities of each of the premises being sound need to all multiply up to at least \(51%\). We can estimate the average necessary soundness probability for each premise, therefore, by calculating the seventh root of \(0.51\), which is \(0.908\). This means that we would need to be on average 91% sure of each of these problematic and hotly contested, abstract, premises. And even that 0.51% would be a drop in the bucket compared to the inherent improbability of a maximally great being existing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inherent uncertainty of the premises of an argument, and the resulting weakness of philosophical arguments in general, is not actually the only problem with deductive philosophical arguments. Since the rules of logic themselves are constructed by human philosophers, in an attempt to describe what they think constitutes the rules of meaning and basic ontology, they themselves are not strictly &lt;em&gt;certain&lt;/em&gt;, and so some logical rules, which are not directly entailed by the criteria for meaning I covered in my previous epistemology article, bring with them their own kind of uncertainty. For instance, the validity of the S5 axiom of modal logic when it pertains to metaphysical truth is hotly contested in some circles, and so the use of this axiom should be considered as something that decreases the likelihood that an argument is valid. Furthermore, the specific way that you actually run logical rules on your premises may even be incorrect, and the likelihood of this also increases with the size and complexity of your argument. All of this is why if you’re going to criticize an argument, you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; actually have to point to one of the premises, you can instead call out problems and equivocations that happen in-between the premises and the conclusion. All of these factors must also be integrated into the probability that an argument actually demonstrates its premise, turning the “soundness probability” I’ve been talking about so far into a “demonstration probability” that includes both soundness &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; validity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-1&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This indicates a core problem with philosophical argumentation as it has been done in the past, since at least Aristotle. Simply sitting back in your armchair and coming up with a list of premises and assumptions that seem likely to you, based on your own intuitions, and then stringing them together into long streams of argumentation is just &lt;em&gt;not effective enough&lt;/em&gt; when you actually treat the credence levels you should have in your premises with honesty and humility. What, then, should we do? Should philosophers retreat to conceptual analysis and clarification, philosophy of science, math, and logic,  synthesizing the conclusions of science together, and documenting and understanding properties of the human condition (whether in the manner of phenomenologists and epistemologists or existentialists)? While these are all worthy goals, and are actually the fields that I am most interested in and in which I think the discipline of philosophy has the most to offer, there is nevertheless a place for philosophy in cosmology and metaphysics too — it is just that a different route must be taken to ensure it remains useful in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Graham Oppy’s views on the nature of philosophical argumentation come in. Instead of focusing on arguments for particular conclusions, which are necessarily piecemeal and therefore fall afoul of the geometric decrease in probability as the number of premises grow, one should consider holistic theories concerning some subject, and compare the explanatory and predictive power of the theory, as well as the intellectual virtues the theory demonstrates as a whole, with the intellectual “cost” of the theory. This approach relies primarily on the ability to state a set of core premises and then use conceptual analysis to elaborate on their implications, in order to derive specific hypothesis and sub-theories, instead of one’s ability to construct deductive philosophical arguments of the kind spoken about above. Moreover, it directly maps the process of choosing beliefs concerning some phenomena onto the underlying pragmatic reasons that we choose beliefs, instead of being based on logic, which is in turn based on those pragmatic reasons, and therefore only being based on pragmatic reasons by proxy. This also allows you to apply the fuzzy Bayesian logic described in my previous articles more directly and conveniently to the theories themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, then, applying my fuzzy Bayesian reasoning to theories of certain phenomena as a whole, according to their intellectual virtues and costs, and relying on science to demonstrate the predictive power of such theories, is by far superior to relying on deductive philosophical argument, due to the inherent nature of how uncertainty interacts with deductive arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;see &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/01/03/fuzzy-logic.html&quot;&gt;An Introduction to Fuzzy Pragmatist Bayesian Epistemology&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/01/22/mathematics.html&quot;&gt;Logic and Mathematics&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is his argument from his book &lt;em&gt;The Nature of Necessity&lt;/em&gt;, pulled off of Edward Feser (the theocratic semi-fascist bigoted “analytic Thomist”)’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://edwardfeser.blogspot.com/2010/12/plantingas-ontological-argument.html&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><category term="logic" /><category term="epistemology" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Logic and Mathematics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/22/mathematics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Logic and Mathematics" /><published>2022-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/22/mathematics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/22/mathematics.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Contrariwise”, continued Tweedledee, “if it was so, it might be, and if it were so, it would be; but &lt;strong&gt;as it isn’t, it ain’t.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;That’s logic!&lt;/strong&gt;” — Lewis Carroll, &lt;em&gt;Through the Looking-Glass&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-introduction&quot;&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/2022/01/03/fuzzy-logic.html&quot;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; I introduced what I call fuzzy pragmatist Bayesian epistemology. To summarize, pragmatism is an approach to epistemology that focuses on arriving at beliefs that are &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; (for navigating the world), instead of beliefs that are absolutely or ultimately or immutably true. My epistemology is a formalization of what I believe is the best method for arriving at such useful beliefs, given the limitations that we as humans have, using Bayes’ theorem: essentially, we should adjust our levels of credence in different theories according to the inherent complexity of the theory, and the evidence we have for or against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fundamentally empiricist and evidentialist approach to epistemology, and as such, it might be natural to ask where seemingly &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; disciplines such as mathematics and logic fit into this rubric. It seems pretty clear, after all, that we do not do experiments to discover mathematical theorems, or discover axioms of propositional logic among the trees on a nature hike; so if mathematics and logic are not based on evidence, how can they possibly be accounted for by an ineluctably evidentialist theory of epistemology? That is the question I wish to answer in this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-logic&quot;&gt;2. Logic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout this essay and the previous one, I have been &lt;em&gt;reasoning&lt;/em&gt; — i.e. using logic. For essays that purport to explore epistemology, assuming logic, the very foundations of human knowledge, is a very big assumption to make. Yet, somehow, it is an assumption that is nearly &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; made. Philosophers almost always proceed by reasoning, or at the very least making statements that are coherent and appear to be about something, which requires assuming the basic laws of logic even if they are used inconsistently, when they go about epistemology. Even if, later, they explain why and how logic and reasoning works (a necessary component of any epistemology, in my opinion), it is by necessity an explanation, and not a justification, because any justification would necessarily be circular (using rationality to justify itself) and therefore taking it as correct or meaningful would undercut the very norms of reasoning one is trying to justify!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;21-what-is-logic&quot;&gt;2.1 What is Logic?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that logic is unjustifiable, yet also inescapable, is key to understanding what logic is. Logic is inescapable because it is fundamentally the the production of statements or descriptions that are meaningful to human beings, and the elaboration of the implications of such statements. Logic proceeds therefore according to certain rules that describe the limitations and requirements of the human mind to grasp the meaning of something. Logic is the process by which we can make a thought or communication mean something, and understand and elaborate on that meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, logic cannot be justified, but it is nevertheless inescapable for any thinking (let alone acting and communicating) human being. This means that while it is impossible to justify it according to the principles usually used for justification (which use logic), there is a sort of &lt;strong&gt;meta&lt;/strong&gt;-justification for the use of logic, and strict adherence to it, to be had. If it is inescapable, better to document that it is a presupposition implied by all thought and argument, document how it works, and apply it consistently, lest you accidentally abandon thought in the process of thought and undermine your very purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symmetrical with the two functions of logic, there are two central principles that describe the operation of those functions, derived from the necessary requirements of the human mind with respect to meaning and its elaboration. In this, I take a similar view to the later Schopenhauer: all of logic can, in essence, be reduced to two principles, the first of which encapsulates and implies Aristotle’s three laws of logic as corrolaries, and the second of which describes how to use the meanings generated by the first, how to understand their implications. Any thoughts or statements which violate the first principle will inevitably, upon close inspection, reduce to pure gibberish, even if it is not obvious at first. Likewise, any thoughts or statements that are supposed to be related, but which are not related by the principle of logical derivation, will, upon close inspection, be revealed to be non-sequitors, the truth of one statement not implying or containing the other, and the truth of the other having no obvious relation to the truth of the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that logic is merely the codification of “common sense” thinking. This is clearly not the case, as people casually engage in all kinds of fallacies and cognitive biases all the time. Logic is instead the codification of the basic principles that must be assumed by the human mind &lt;em&gt;even to violate them&lt;/em&gt;, which implies that they are the necessary and sufficient conditions for meaning, since some meaning must be present in order for a violation of meaning or sense to occur. All else, all the other processes that the human mind does, are superfluous to the study of what is at base necessary for meaning, and the study of what the consistent application of those criteria entails. That such consistent application is a good thing is implied by the fact that anything that does not engage in it falls apart on close, critical inspection, or does not provide compelling information to those who do not already agree, and in the fact that those principles are what the mind operates on in the first place. If the core, inescapable assumptions of the mind are such, that is an indication that there is something important about them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human mind is a system capable of error correction, like a networking system. It will use incorrect, incomplete, but close-enough heuristics when it can get away with it, while operating at the higher level to provide a substrate for the rest, to patch up the connections. So one must consciously choose to engage its higher-level, more advanced, more critical functions, and must continually choose to do so in order to maintain it at its highest level of ability to produce meaningful and correct statements consistently. Logic is a description of how this higher level, more likely to be correct, more critical system of meaning production, elaboration, and analysis would tend to act, “as the limit approaches infinity.” The listing of proper deductive forms and their opposites, fallacies, is a project of conscious human effort and analysis over millenia, documenting the processes of the human mind that tend to work and to produce meaningful statements and elaborations that hold up to consistent scruteny, and those that can happen to be correct but are not so often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to make it clearer what I am talking about, and because it is interesting, I will now elaborate on the two principles of logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-the-principle-of-meaning&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. The Principle of Meaning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sign is a word, a symbol, or other differentiatable sense experience which is construed to &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; something. It is granted this meaning by the establishment of a relation between a &lt;em&gt;signifier&lt;/em&gt; (a sense experience, e.g. a sound or image) and a &lt;em&gt;signified&lt;/em&gt;, a concept (which is a mental construct, a category or a particular). This is done by assigning properties and values for those properties to a symbol, thereby beginning to describe the concept that that symbol refers to, narrowing the range of concepts the symbol could mean. For instance, if I say “X is red,” while previously X could have represented any concept whatsoever, now, the range of concepts it can refer to is limited. This process can take place in a lot of different ways, but it is the key property of granting meanings to symbols. Importantly, however, concepts themselves aren’t fully formed &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; symbols and you just assign symbols to them; by assigning properties to a symbol and narrowing the range of things it could refer to, you are &lt;em&gt;creating&lt;/em&gt; a set of properties that are now associated, which &lt;em&gt;brings&lt;/em&gt; that concept into existence, since concepts are groups of properties with their various specifications. So, limiting what range of concepts a symbol could refer to means bringing more and more precise and differentiated concepts into existence. This is why having language to understand things with, even if it is only a mental language, is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can establish what it means for a particular set of experiences (an object or set of objects, once the first layer of particularization is done in our minds) to belong to a category or constitute a specific particular in terms of further experiences concerning those experiences and our internal thoughts, which might be termed “meta-experiences.” We know that a certain set of experiences “belongs” to a concept (a particular or category) when we have a sense of recognition for that set of experiences in relation to, or in the context of, that concept. For instance, if we are looking for a possession which we have had previous experience with, such that we have a concept of that particular thing, when we finally find it, we experience a sense of recognition, of the object fitting neatly into place in relation to the concepts that we have in our minds. This sensation need not be a powerful sense of familiarity or nostalgia, which is what you might be thinking of when I write about “a sense of recognition,” but for anything for which we have a concept that points to it, when we have a novel set of experiences concerning that thing, we have a basic sense of recognition that that object relates to that concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may notice that the definition of concepts above is not expressed in terms of predicates which are true or false of a given concept, but instead in terms of properties which are or are not present. This is because the latter is a shorthand way of describing a much more complicated system of understanding what a concept &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, what it means, what constitutes its definition, which I propose must replace essentialism. Essentialism is the idea that some core list of binary predicates defines the necessary and sufficient conditions for whether any object belongs to a concept/category or not. This idea runs into serious challenges in the real world, or even in the world of philosophy, quite quickly, as it often becomes apparent that a group of phenomena which it would be extremely useful and sensible to categorize together have no common list of necessary and sufficient predicates which could be used to define those objects, and &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; those objects, as a set together. Every time this is attempted, some thing that would be usefully categorized as part of the set is left out, because it does not share a “necessary” predicate, or some thing which is not usefully categorized as part of that set is included, because it has a “sufficient” predicate. Take, for a trivial but clarifying example, the definitions of soup or sandwich. Is a hot dog a sandwich? Is cereal a soup? Hence, instead of concepts/categories/signifieds being defined in terms of a list of necessary and sufficient binary predicates, I instead choose to define them in terms of a list of ranges (or, rarely, specific values) for properties or features which each represent an axis on a high-dimensional &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latent_space&quot;&gt;latent space&lt;/a&gt;. In essence, a “concept” is a cloud or amorphous “area” of the space of all possible properties where things are relevantly (and relatively) similar to each other. Something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://blog.alexisdumas.org/assets/math4.png&quot; alt=&quot;latent space visualization&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particular things (other concepts, or particular phenomena of experience) can have those properties to a greater or lesser degree, or have fewer or more of those properties, meaning that particulars are essentially a single “point” in that latent space in which concepts exist, a point that can be closer to the center of the amorphous category, or more to the edges, or closer or farther from the edges — i.e. a particular thing can be more or less part of a category, or not part of a category but like it to a greater or lesser degree; whether X “is” Y is thus really a continuous value, a measure of the geometric distance between the edge of the category-cloud and where this a particular X falls, where if the distance is positive, the greater it is the less X is a Y, and if the distance is negative (if X falls inside the cloud), the smaller the negative value (the further X is from the edge, but &lt;em&gt;inside&lt;/em&gt; it) the more X is a Y. In essence, “X is a Y” is a point on a spectrum from “very not like Y” to “very like Y.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important to all this, a signifier, whether it refers to a particular or a concept (both of them are valid signifieds), must be assigned a certain list of properties, and certain values or ranges for those properties. It cannot be simultaneously assigned multiple, incompatible values, because then its meaning would be indistinct and incoherent. It would not be clear what the signifier signified, and therefore what to do with it or how it relates to anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of this  process of assigning meanings to signs through assigning them a list of properties and their ranges to assign a concept to them, take,  for instance, what happens if I say that “chair” &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;means&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; “a four legged piece of furniture designed for seating one person.” If I do this, then the signifier “chair” will henceforth be interchangeable with the that longer description, which specifies and implies several different properties which have particular values for the ultimate chair, and which particular things may be closer to or farther from. For instance, something could have three legs, or five, legs, but if it is still furniture designed for seating one person, it is pretty close to a chair; something could have four legs and not be designed for seating people but nevertheless be &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; for that, in which case it is &lt;em&gt;functionally&lt;/em&gt; a chair; something could have four legs and not be designed or used for sitting, like a table, in which case it is not very like a chair, but is still sort of similar; and so on. Thus when I say “X is a chair,” what I mean thereby is that X falls close enough to the point or grouping in latent space that “chair” represents that it is useful to categorize it as such for practical purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, sometimes essentialism &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; work. Sometimes there are a grouping of necessary and sufficient binary characteristics which make up a category. This is the case quite often in formal studies of mathematics or mathematical logic, for instance, and can sometimes happen for everyday concepts too, if they happen to have particular values for their properties instead of ranges, and a small(ish) list of properties that are all relatively essential. That is actually the case with the example above. But in more general, larger, less toy cases, those kinds of categories tend to be nowhere to be found — for instance, in the definition of human, or consciousness, or morality, or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this might naturally raise the question of how the signs used to define other signs are themselves defined. In reality, the meaning of every sign is enmeshed in a dense and highly interconnected web with the meaning of every other sign; this web zig-zags and loops and backs up on itself, an intricate knot of reference and relation; but ultimately, the meanings of words are first established by pointing them out, by physically establishing the relationship between a signifier and some real phenomena in the world by direct and repeated experience. This is how we teach babies language, this is what we do when explaining the basic meaning of a word to someone who does not share our language. Everything else after that is built up by a process of intuition and guesswork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are concepts arrived at, though? How do we know how to categorize the phenomena — both of the external world and of our own inner mental life — with which we have to deal? After all, in the process of assigning meanings to concepts, of determining what concepts to have and care about, how to interconnect all the concepts in our mental web of understanding, there are decisions to be made. Despite what the Platonists might have you think, there is not one way to conceptually categorize things. I contend that the process of categorization, the assigning of properties to concepts, is done primarily on the basis of practicality. Some ways of categorizing the phenomena of our experience are more useful than others, and if the general purpose of epistemology, at rock bottom, is to help us navigate the world, to serve as a practical tool, then the core motivation for categorization must be the practical need to navigate the world. Therefore, while categorization is arbitrary in the sense that it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be done any which way, not all categorizations are created equal, and fundamentally the motivating force behind most established categorizations is practicality. Nevertheless, because the construction of categorizations is a volitional human process, other motivations can sneak in. Thus, concepts can be introduced primarily for the purpose of aiding in communication, or motivating others to do things, or to gain power over others. These categories must be disguised so that they are difficult to distinguish from the actually useful, relevant, or important categories which make up the core of our ability to think and speak, so that they do not seem clearly manipulative or dispensable, but they will never &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; be anything more than a manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up till now, I have been speaking about categories and particulars as if they were separate things, but that’s not really the case. Instead, categories and particulars exist on a spectrum: particulars are objects the properties of which are described with a high degree of specificity (although still with ranges and not precise values, since you need to be able to recognize objects from different angles, in different lighting, etc, when they might not give &lt;em&gt;precisely&lt;/em&gt; the same experiences), and categories can refer to multiple objects because their properties have been specified with less specificity, and some properties have not been specified at all — such as, for instance, location, if we are categorizing colors, or color, if we are categorizing locations. We can see that particulars and categories exist on a spectrum because sometimes a particular can turn into a category, when more than one thing turns out to satisfy our understanding of what constituted a particular object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much for the principle of meaning as applied to signs and the concepts or particulars they represent. The same principles apply, &lt;em&gt;mutatis mutandis&lt;/em&gt;, to propositions themselves, since propositions provide a (partial) description of a particular or a concept, using signs to talk about the properties and degrees that are relevant. Essentially, the propositions one gives must add up to a description of a valid concept or particular, which satisfies the conditions for meaning in a concept, particular, and the sign that refers to them. For instance, if I say “the sky is blue,” I am saying that a particular range of locations applies to the property “color” of the particular indicated by the sign “sky.” I am merely further specifying the concept that the sign sky is referring to. If, however, I &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; say “the sky is green,” then I introduce a problem: I have attributed two separate ranges to the same property. Because of this, my meaning is inherently unclear — do I mean it is a blue-green mix, or do I mean it is one range or the other? There is no decision procedure to select which my meaning must be, and so the implications and uses of the complex of propositions I have presented are muddled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-the-principle-of-derivation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. The Principle of Derivation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the principle of meaning encapsulates the law of identity, and the laws of non-contradiction for individual concepts, allowing us to identify particular objects and categories of objects in our sense experience, the principle of derivation is what encapsulates our ability to draw patterns and relations between those particulars and categories from both the intrinsic properties of those concepts, and our experiences of their interrelation, as well as the meaning of the law of non-contradiction as it relates to propositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cover the second purpose of the principle of derivation first, when it comes to describing states of affairs with multiple propositions, it is analogous to describing a particular, just a very all-encompassing particular. Therefore, if contradictory properties are given to that state of affairs, it will be impossible to understand what is intended to be described — i.e., what is meant. Which of the two or more contradictory properties should take precedence, if any? Is there a way to combine and blend all of them? Do they sometimes take precedence at different times? Without an explicit reconciliation of the conflict, what is meant to be a particular will instead refer to a range of different particulars that cannot all be reconciled under the same category, making the description useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the first purpose that the principle of derivation serves, there are far too many sub-principles and different ways of understanding relation and implication to get into here; a full analysis and justification of these in terms of what could possibly be meaningful and sensible to the human mind would require a book of its own, and probably be completely outside my capabilities as a logician. Nevertheless, I will take the time to sketch out some of the basic components, categories of mechanisms, and tools that might be used to derive implications and relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and most crucial approach to establishing relations between concepts is through repeated experience of patterns, e.g. &lt;strong&gt;induction&lt;/strong&gt;: when we commonly experience certain categories of objects in certain spacio-temporal relations, we begin to form an understanding that they are linked somehow, so that one entails the other. This is the pattern-finding mechanism that is fundamental to the human brain and the sort of deep-learning-like process by which humans learn. It is the same process that allows us to slowly learn the pattern in a song or series of numbers or an enemy’s attacks in a video game, but applied generally to all the elements of experience. This is actually how we establish cause and effect too — for, despite the common refrain of “correlation does not imply causation,” fundamentally speaking we do not experience causal relations directly, because there is no way to experience the abstract notion of “a cause”; we only experience the fact that a certain experience is produced whenever a certain state of affairs is the case (determined by a certain range of experiences), and is typically &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; produced when that state of affairs is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the case. This repeated experience of the correlation of a set of experiences, this &lt;em&gt;pattern&lt;/em&gt; of experience, is reified into the notion of a “cause” because the definition of a cause is functionally identical: a cause is something which, when it is the case, is accompanied by some other thing, an effect, and when it is not the case (and absent any other causes with the same or similar effects), that effect is not to be found. Thus, cause and effect is not a product of the inherent nature of concepts — in the sense that the concept, observed apart from any relation it has to other things, would imply its cause and effects, not that the causes and effects that a concept is observed to be enmeshed in in our actual experience are not valid things to be included in its definition — but a product of repeated experience; and this implies and explains why causation is inherently probabilistic: sometimes the conditions are present which usually produce an effect, but are not accompanied by that effect. Thus we can only have relatively certain knowledge of the patterns of experience, because it can always turn out that some pattern was only a sub-pattern in a larger pattern of all the experiences that could be had (either temporally or spatially), or that there was no larger pattern at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first method is how we do induction; it is therefore crucial to what is typically considered purely empirical epistemology, and yet it is a method that must come &lt;em&gt;prior&lt;/em&gt; to experience, to provide a framework for collating and understanding experiences, or else nothing at all could be made sense of, and perception would just be a storm of random inputs. This is because, firstly, this method of relating things is necessary to even form concepts of things, since certain properties or features of our experience must accompany each other frequently in our various experiences in order to be understood as related to the same thing and become properties specifying concepts. Secondly, this method of relating things by repeated accompaniment is also necessary to even understand and establish the meanings of symbols and their other relations, because the association of a certain arbitrary sense datum with a concept by repeated accompaniment is how we establish the meanings of words, etc. There are many other similar ways in which this inductive process is core even to the principle of meaning; thus this reification of patterns commonly associated together forms the bedrock of &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; else. It must exist for us &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; we can learn from experience or do science or anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that induction is based not on necessary logical derivation, but on repeated experience which can turn out to not be representative of the whole pattern of experience is commonly termed the “problem” of induction, but I fundamentally don’t see why this is a problem at all. The fact that past experiences are not a perfect guide to future ones is what allows there to be &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; change in the world at all, any motion in the world at all, any arrow of time, any space, etc. If every future experience had to remain identical to a past one, there would be nothing at all but a static image for all eternity! The fact that some experiences are not actually good guides to the future is what allows there to be patterns &lt;em&gt;in the first place&lt;/em&gt;, just as a sequence of identical numbers has no real interesting pattern, while a sequence where each subsequent number is different from a prior one is the prerequisite for future patterns to form. The problem of induction stems from the fact that we want &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; experiences — the widely aggregated set of experiences from which we draw patterns such as the “laws of physics” — to be permanently constant, permanently good guides to the future, but not others. We don’t even want all patterns from our past experiences to be good inductive guides to the future — for instance, some physical laws or descriptions of population or animal behavior only apply to certain local areas of space or time, or in certain situations, and that’s not considered a huge problem. So it seems to me that the problem of induction steps almost from a sort of instinct for special pleading: we want some patterns or laws to be universal and permanent, but not others, even when there’s really not any logic for one being universal and the other not besides the current horizon of our knowledge (which could expand, changing what things we would want induction to prove universal!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second method by which the principle of derivation operates is what might loosely be termed &lt;strong&gt;entailment&lt;/strong&gt;, which is related to deduction. This is what happens when one takes two or more descriptions that speak about different sets of properties of a state of affairs or a concept, and combine them into a larger set of properties, and then take a &lt;em&gt;unique&lt;/em&gt; subset from that overall list of properties, which overlaps partly with the input sets but is unique from them. This is how you draw conclusions about what a set of propositions or concepts, taken together, imply about things. A variant of this is when some of the properties which specify a concept make reference to the properties of other things that are not relevant to the specific concept and so are therefore not specified. If one concept is related to another that contains properties referenced in that other concept, then our understanding of that concept automatically narrows, giving us more information than we started with. The picture begins to cohere, like pieces of a puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method, too, is something we need prior to experience, in order to learn from empirical experience, since absent it, we cannot derive new predictions and implications from the various patterns and concepts we form. As a specific example, scientific induction and falsification relies on deductive logic, at least informally, in order to form its hypotheses through conceptual relation and exploration, and in order to establish that a hypothesis has been falsified, through &lt;em&gt;modus tollens&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third method of derivation is what we might typically include under the laws of logic, such as material implication. All of these laws can be explained in terms of the laws of identity and non-contradiction, which are inherent and implied in the principle of meaning. For instance, material implication works by asserting that to have one state of affairs but not another is contradictory. These laws, however, are merely descriptions of things, and so the conclusion, for instance, the idea that something implies something else, must be derived from either of the previous two methods of derivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-mathematics&quot;&gt;3. Mathematics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is, essentially, a game we play, like Chess or Go, but instead of playing mathematics with physical pieces that move around a board, we “play mathematics” with symbols marching down a page. We invented the game of mathematics by assigning relationships between various symbols, creating symbols that transform other symbols according to a set of rules, and ways of abbreviating combinations of symbols. Every time we do mathematics, we are simply exploring what happens when we set up the pieces of the game a certain way and play it out according to the rules we’ve established. Because we aren’t aware of the implications of the rules beforehand, it can often feel like one is “discovering” some fact through the process of “doing math,” which is why mathematics often feels like exploring some Platonic realm of numbers and sets. Nevertheless, that’s not what’s happening here at base. The core of what mathematics is, far from being discovered, is constructed — it is only discovered in the sense that a new board game is “discovered”: creativity is applied to the rules of the game, to find the ones that are the most fruitful and practical. We just don’t tinker around with the fundamental axioms of mathematics often enough, now that it’s been established for at least a few hundred years, to realize that’s what we’re doing at the core. Like so many other social institutions and cultural ideas, those who have received the tradition no longer remember how it came about, or what it really is, but instead have come to view it, because of its sacrosanct status and pervasive influence, to be a sort of supernatural thing hovering in the aether somewhere above and to the left of human reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that mathematics is ultimately constructed is made clear by the fact that people &lt;em&gt;invent&lt;/em&gt; new mathematics (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclidean_geometry&quot;&gt;Euclidean geometry&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logarithm&quot;&gt;logarithms&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Analytic_geometry&quot;&gt;Analytic geometry&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calculus&quot;&gt;calculus&lt;/a&gt;) based on their observations of the behavior of things within the bounds of their experience, in order to have a more rigorous and consistent language for describing those things, a language the axioms of which can actually be &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; when compared to reality. This means that mathematics isn’t magically connected to the real world somehow, but is only connected to it, and successful in describing it, because it is a product of our own experiences and our attempts to codify them. Indeed, new bases for &lt;em&gt;existing&lt;/em&gt; mathematical axioms (such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zermelo%E2%80%93Fraenkel_set_theory&quot;&gt;ZFC set theory&lt;/a&gt;) have been constructed specifically to deal with fundamental contradictions and holes in previous mathematical systems, and new branches of mathematics (such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Propositional_calculus&quot;&gt;propositional calculus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lambda_calculus&quot;&gt;lambda calculus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probability_theory&quot;&gt;probability theory&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Set_theory&quot;&gt;set theory&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_O_notation#Family_of_Bachmann%E2%80%93Landau_notations&quot;&gt;Bachmann–Landau notation&lt;/a&gt;) are constantly being invented, not by pulling some new construct out of the inherent implications of old ones, nor by looking into some abstract world, but by thinking about how it would be useful to describe things and how such descriptions could be consistently made clear and formalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why it is fundamentally confused when people marvel at the “the unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics in the natural sciences.” In some cases, we are essentially creating a template based on things we see in the real world, then looking around for other instances of a similar pattern and adjusting the template to fit the parts of the new pattern we have, to see what the new pattern would look like completed if it really is like the old pattern. And most of the time we’re right, because the inherent properties of the first part of the pattern &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; it, for logical consistency to hold, to look like the rest of all similar patterns, but sometimes we’re wrong too! In other cases, we are simply using mathematics, as a very flexible and concise language with a lot of tools for expressing different relations, to describe what we see, just like we could use English to do the same thing. Being surprised that this latter thing works is like being surprised that someone can look at a scene, describe it in words, and then those words actually match up to the scene. If you understand how languages work, it is hardly more surprising than anything else that we experience on a day to day basis — languages are &lt;em&gt;designed to do that!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think what confounds this otherwise obvious realization is that when one is doing mathematics, there are often times when some leap of intuition must be used, and even in those basic cases of constructing new axioms for mathematics, oftentimes the particularities of those axioms are also driven by intuition. How can this be, the Platonist asks, if mathematics is just a language/game we’ve made up to use as a tool? Again, I think the answer lies in thinking of mathematics as fundamentally a product of intellectual entrepreneurship in much the same way programming languages or board games are. Human beings necessarily have an intuitive understanding, which is both evolutionarily “programmed” and learned over the course of our abnormally long (for an animal) childhoods, of the laws and interactions of the world around us. Since the goal of mathematics (whether one is playing by the rules or making them) is to help us construct a language to describe and predict actual phenomena, we can apply our intuitions about how things work to constructing mathematical rules. Additionally, human beings very often can develop intuitions about the subjects of our work or passion, so in the case of mathematicians, intuitions about what constructs are likely to lead to fruitful or wieldy results, for instance, are more than possible. Additionally, to some degree, mathematics is a codification of how we think or what makes sense to us — laws of thought — given certain other axioms of mathematics (I will cover this in more depth later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-conclusion&quot;&gt;4. Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude: logic is the necessary precondition for learning from experience and establishing meaning in thoughts and communication. Without it, nothing is possible for human beings (and I doubt any other conscious animal either). As such a prerequisite, it is impossible to operate completely without it, and any attempt to do so is guaranteed to be a failure; furthermore, there is no need to do without it, as attempting to do so would defeat the purpose of thinking or communication, or trying to understand the world, in the first place. Thus at the very least the careful documentation, understanding, and probably the consistent application of logic is a reasonable reaction to this state of affairs. Formal logics are an attempt to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to formal logics, but directed at external phenomena a little more than logic, mathematics is a linguistic system for describing a subclass of the phenomena that humans interact with in a precise and clear way, where the rules are constructed by humans based on what is likely to be useful, and applied like a template to reality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><category term="mathematics" /><category term="epistemology" /><summary type="html">“Contrariwise”, continued Tweedledee, “if it was so, it might be, and if it were so, it would be; but as it isn’t, it ain’t. That’s logic!” — Lewis Carroll, Through the Looking-Glass</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Is Individualist Anarchism?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/17/what-is-individualist-anarchism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Is Individualist Anarchism?" /><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/17/what-is-individualist-anarchism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/17/what-is-individualist-anarchism.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Infernal world! and thou, profoundest Hell,&lt;br /&gt;
Receive thy new possessor—one who brings&lt;br /&gt;
A mind not to be changed by place or time.&lt;br /&gt;
The mind is its own place, and in itself&lt;br /&gt;
Can make a Heaven of Hell, a Hell of Heaven.&lt;br /&gt;
What matter where, if I be still the same,&lt;br /&gt;
And what I should be, all but less than he&lt;br /&gt;
Whom thunder hath made greater? Here at least&lt;br /&gt;
We shall be free; th’ Almighty hath not built&lt;br /&gt;
Here for his envy, will not drive us hence:&lt;br /&gt;
Here we may reign secure; and, in my choice,&lt;br /&gt;
To reign is worth ambition, though in Hell:&lt;br /&gt;
Better to reign in Hell than serve in Heaven.”&lt;br /&gt;
— &lt;em&gt;Paradise Lost&lt;/em&gt;, by John Milton, Book I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualist anarchism is, at its core, very simple. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists seek individual autonomy above all else.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; We seek our own first of all, but we know that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;our own autonomy can never truly be secure or complete until the autonomy of all is equally respected&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;; furthermore, we are empathetic human beings who want to see others free and flourishing too. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;We seek to eliminate subjugation, domination, authority, and hierarchy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; wherever it can be found&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — be that from the collective, the capitalist, the politician, the bureaucrat, or the priest — so that each person is free to live their own life how they choose, according to their own reason, pursuing their own happiness, and solving their conflicts and problems directly with those involved according to the norms that work best for their particular situation. Autonomy here stands for a rich tapestry of things, not just the empty and farcical notions of freedom foisted by political propaganda upon the common citizen: it stands for negative liberty, the freedom from &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; obstacles, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the primacy of one’s own will and self-determination&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, but it also stands for the ability to choose how one’s labor time is spent and what happens to the products of that labor, to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;control the things important to one’s life and destiny&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; like the means of production one uses and the roof over one’s head, and independence from the wills and whims of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the absolute autonomy of one person can be detrimental to the autonomy of another, so in the sphere of life where one’s actions necessarily collide with others, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the individualist anarchist seeks relations between people that are founded on reciprocity, on mutual benefit, on even footing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — relations free from the dynamics of power and authority which permeate our world. Therefore the only restrictions on the autonomy of each individual must be against actions that would extend their autonomy in ways that require the domination of others, or treat the interests of others as anything but equal to their own. Likewise, although individualist anarchists may occasionally use democratic forms in order to balance the interests of those directly involved in a situation that might otherwise give rise to conflict, we totally reject the myth of democracy, that a larger group of people have the right to subjugate and control a smaller group of people merely on the basis of being a larger group. The individual will, the autonomy of each of us, is to be absolute within its boundaries. To safeguard this, the maximum decentralization and distribution of power to everyone, the splitting up of control to those directly involved in the relevant situation, and pure equality in that: if we are all equal, none may dominate another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists, furthermore, recognize that rights are protected by the reciprocally gifted respect of the community one lives in&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: each person freely and willingly recognizes and respects the autonomy of others with the expectation that the those others will in turn respect their own autonomy. Therefore, if any one does not have much autonomy to speak of — if someone is starving, homeless, has nowhere to work — or if the community is not respecting their autonomy, or supporting through inaction their subjugation at the hands of others, then they have no incentive to respect the autonomy of others and should not be expected to. In essence, then, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the rights of all are forfeit to the direct action of the marginalized and oppressed until such a time as all are provided with what they need for autonomy and respected&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This also works on an individual basis: if someone refuses to respect your autonomy, why respect theirs? They will not respond in goodwill, will not reciprocate your gift of respect. This means that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;to be truly free and autonomous ourselves, it is necessary to lift up, respect, and protect the autonomy of others, through mutual aid and solidarity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; To create a society where everyone’s autonomy is safeguarded, we must all contribute to safeguarding the autonomy of others: providing them with whatever they need, from houses to food to education. Of course, this should not turn into a relationship of domination of others by the needy, not a welfare system or a state, each individual must care for themselves first, but &lt;em&gt;in and through&lt;/em&gt; caring for themselves they must also care for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualist anarchists seek to eliminate property. True to our principles, we believe that those who use something, those for whom something is a direct extension of their autonomy, their ability to control their own destiny and act freely, should own that thing. To prevent someone from using something they regularly use is to restrict their freedom, but to use something that no one else is using, or in such a way as to let the others who use it continue to use it, is not restricting anyone’s freedom. Likewise, to use something that someone will never use is not a restriction of their freedom just because it is theoretically preventing them from taking an action they have never and likely will never take. For instance, walking takes up space on the sidewalk that someone else could &lt;em&gt;theoretically&lt;/em&gt; have used otherwise, but since no one is actually trying to do that, so no one is being bumped out of the way, it restricts no one’s freedom.  Thus &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;we seek to replace absentee property, where people who actually use something are dispossessed in favor of those who will never use it, with the possession of things by the people who occupy or use them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This is the correct principle for those who are committed to autonomy: those whose autonomy is bound up in something have a right not to be dispossessed of it, thrown off the means of their livelihood, and those who have nothing to do with a thing have no say in what is done with it, cannot extend their autonomy by asserting their control over others. The person that lives in a house should own it, not some absentee landlord, the worker who uses a machine should own it, not some capitalist, and so on. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists also believe that the just wage of labor is its product&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: everyone should be able to control the product of their own labor time, because otherwise they are just a slave to someone else; hence, the worker must justly own the product they produce, not have it taken away by the capitalist or the collective. However, if someone produces something, but refuses to use it or sell it, and instead tries to extract economic rent or profit from it, then they are extending their autonomy by asserting their authority over others. They have broken the single “law” which a community of anarchists must recognize: that any autonomy gained by the domination and subjugation of others is illegitimate, that any autonomy gained by the restriction of the autonomy of others (when that autonomy itself is not coercive), is not to be tolerated. They have thrown the gift of respect for their autonomy that others have granted them, in letting them determine the fate of the products of their labor, back in the face of everyone by using that gift of autonomy to restrict the autonomy of the very people that gave them that gift, and have therefore forfeited their right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists seek to eliminate capitalism and property, but we do not seek to bring about communism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Individualist anarchists view communism as just as antithetical to our individualist, autonomy-focused, anti-authoritarian credo as capitalism is. In the first place, giving control of the means of production to the collective subjugates each individual worker to an absentee collective which can be just as domineering as the capitalist was. It makes individuals not able to separate themselves from the will of others, leaving them with no shield for their individuality and no other option but to be subsumed. In the second place, not allowing the worker to decide what to do with the product of their labor, including selling it, or letting others take the product of their labor without permission when they are not using it to dominate anyone else, is domination just as bad as, and in fact quite similar to, capitalism itself. In the third place, placing everyone under the authority of the democratic majority is still subjugating people to the wills of others, just the will of many others instead of the will of a few, and if the will of the majority is made absolute in economic matters, it will not be long until it is made absolute in other matters as well, since then one’s individual autonomy only exists at the sufferance of the majority, and if the majority can hold one’s means of sustenance and livelihood hostage (since the economic sphere is just that) then they can use that as leverage to control everything else. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Therefore, instead of eliminating markets, individualist anarchists seek to bring about socialist ends through market means&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: markets where workers own the means of production, where everyone is as independent as possible, where the economy is as decentralized and localized as possible, and where federations of worker cooperatives&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are the main form of organization for when some centralization or organization of production is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists think this reformation of markets away from capitalism is possible because we do not believe that free markets are synonymous with capitalism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — in fact, we think that the equation of capitalism and markets is the single greatest tragedy in the history of the language of politics, for it gives both Marxists and capitalists free reign to assume their conclusions. For capitalists, since markets are free and just, capitalism must be too, and for Marxists, since capitalism is oppressive and exploitative, markets must be abolished. This is not the case. There have been markets before capitalism, and there will be markets after capitalism. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What creates capitalism is the state enforcement of the absentee property claims of intellectual property, landlords, lenders, and capitalists, not the presence of people producing things and selling the products of their labor to others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is only when the state sends its jackbooted thugs to protect the claims of those who do not produce that markets become exploitative.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; If one could only sell the products of one’s labor, and one forfeited one’s claim on anything as soon as one or tried to use access to it as leverage to gain power over others and extract rent for idleness, the world would look very different than it is. There would not be millions of homes sitting empty as investment vehicles for the wealthy, or waiting for an exploitatively high rent, while there were thousands of homeless people walking the streets just outside, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this society, all that is ultimately necessary is for individuals to recognize that there is no justification, and can be no justification, for any authority — whether moral, political, or any other sort — above their own mind and will. All power structures ultimately rest on the widespread belief in their legitimacy, the servile and obedient perpetuation and reproduction in the small of them by people, so all that is needed for them to crumble is for us to reject the mythology and superstitions inculcated in us by society since birth, to choose not to legitimize or protect those institutions, and to spread that rejection to others through uncompromising commitment to our values and our own reason. Where else does the state, or the capitalist, get their power, but from the cooperation of the masses that vastly outnumber them and any servants they could hire? The difference between the strength of one human being and another is not enough to allow one corporate fat cat, or one slimy politician, to hold off millions of us. There will be battles, in the end, the last violent death-thrashings of an angry and defeated Leviathan, but when once legitimacy is lost in the hearts and minds of the people, the tide is turned, the battle is half-way won! We have seen this in the past, in the tidal shifts of legitimacy that overthrew or chained the old monarchies — why could it not happen again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus those who truly value a world without authority, a world of individual autonomy and self-determination, must dedicate themselves to the education and liberation of those who are currently possessed by the phantoms that haunt our cultural consciousness; and while we wait, and the movement slowly grows, why not also dedicate ourselves to building something that will be ready when the Leviathan falls? Something to provide the structures and institutions a new, free society needs? Something which, while waiting in the interstices, can lighten the load for those who must live in the current era, provide something real, practical, and compassionate in the here-and-now for those who suffer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not hierarchy in the broad sense, of an inequality or ranking between people, but in the specific sense of a hierarchy that gives some control over others or leads people to treat someone as worth more than someone else in a way that leads to oppression. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is what the BLM riots were, in essence: retaliation against an oppressive system by those whose autonomy means little, if anything, to that system, because at that point, they have little to lose and everything to gain, and they needed to be heard. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Worker cooperates do not represent as much of a form of domination over the individual as the whole of society democratically determining what is to be done with all the means of production, because each worker is only influenced by the vote of others concerning the uses of the means of production to ensure that that worker does not usurp something other people are using — i.e. it is a balancing of the autonomy represented by the use of some capital between all those who actually use it, a way of &lt;em&gt;preventing&lt;/em&gt; one person’s exclusive and unilateral use of something to the detriment of others, instead of merely an assertion of the control of others in matters they would otherwise be uneffected by over the autonomy of those who actually use something. It is the difference between balancing the overlapping autonomy of each person equally, so that no one can expand their autonomy by hurting another’s, versus the expansion of autonomy directly and inherently through domination of others in matters that would otherwise not need to represent those interests at all. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><category term="anarchism" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="politics" /><category term="mutualism" /><summary type="html">“Infernal world! and thou, profoundest Hell, Receive thy new possessor—one who brings A mind not to be changed by place or time. The mind is its own place, and in itself Can make a Heaven of Hell, a Hell of Heaven. What matter where, if I be still the same, And what I should be, all but less than he Whom thunder hath made greater? Here at least We shall be free; th’ Almighty hath not built Here for his envy, will not drive us hence: Here we may reign secure; and, in my choice, To reign is worth ambition, though in Hell: Better to reign in Hell than serve in Heaven.” — Paradise Lost, by John Milton, Book I</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abortion and Individualist Anarchism: Why Pro-Choice Is The Only Choice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/abortion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abortion and Individualist Anarchism: Why Pro-Choice Is The Only Choice" /><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/abortion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/abortion.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I first began my journey towards anarchism, my views on abortion have been in a constant state of flux — multiple conflicting intuitions and considerations all pulling my values in different directions, while the prevailing winds of my evolving moral system changed which were foremost in my mind. Usually, with things like this, it is important to open a dialogue about it with others, in order to gain new perspectives and refine one’s understanding, but due to the understandably controversial nature of the topic, I’ve found it difficult to openly discuss it with people. I’ve even found it difficult to begin writing on the topic, so unlike most of my other ethical views, I don’t have a significant corpus of essays on it documenting the development of my views. I think, however, that my ideas on the topic have finally become mature enough, and nuanced enough, that it is time to write them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this essay is primarily to do what I did in my essay on anarchistic relations: to explore all the nuances and complexities of a topic, letting my reasoning take me where it will, in order to clarify for myself, through solidification, my own thoughts. Please bear in mind, then, that this is an exploratory essay, and as such won’t be as clearly structured as my moral formal ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first consideration when we bring up the topic of abortions is our general moral foundations. After all, if we don’t understand those clearly, then it is difficult to derive conclusions about what should or should not be done with any clarity. In my own case, my moral foundations are fundamentally individualistic, anti-authoritarian, and subjectivist — I am only beholden to my own individual desires regarding what I want to see in my own life and in the society around me, my primary concern is for individual autonomy, and my primary opposition is to authority. In light of that, this essay will not be an exploration of what others &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; do regarding abortion — instead it will be an exploration of my own values and how they might require me to act towards others, as well as an attempt to reach reflective equilibrium regarding these two things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a moral subjectivist, you might assume that my response to abortion would be simple: “I have no right to dictate the reproductive health choices of anyone besides myself.” That’s not really the case, however: a moral subjectivist does not believe in ‘rights,’ and does not commit themselves to moral relativism by giving up moral realism, since relativism insists on a commitment to a moral rule (non-interference with others) that is &lt;em&gt;non-relative&lt;/em&gt; to subjective desires and therefore a phantom at best. Therefore, if, according to my values, something is of an abhorrent and undesirable nature — such as oppression, authority, hierarchy, coercion, etc — then it is perfectly acceptable for me to take steps to prevent it, and rally others in doing so as well. This is something no anarchist (except pacifists perhaps) has ever been against, no matter how subjectivist they are. Otherwise they’d cease to be anarchists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although I am not inherently opposed to interfering with others for my moral values, I begin with a presumption of &lt;strong&gt;non-interference&lt;/strong&gt;. This for several reasons. First, because by default interfering with the choices of others is a reduction of autonomy, unless you can prove that that exercise of autonomy was actually resulting in the subordination of someone else. Second, because interfering with the choices of others necessarily brings about conflict, and conflict is costly and dangerous, and so best avoided when possible, since enforcing one’s values is not inherently right or just (as a moral realist would think) but instead just another good to be weighed and measured against one’s other interests. Finally, encouraging a presumption in favor of non-interference produces a society that is less infested with moral busybodies, since people can’t always be trusted to have minimalist moral values that would lead to a live and let live attitude even in the absence of such a presumption. For all these reasons, then, just as the defendant in a court of law is presumed to be innocent until the contrary is proven, so in my own reasoning I prefer to assume a peaceful live-and-let-live attitude until the weight of axiological considerations forces me to overturn that. Therefore, the crucial question is whether my values would imply that abortion is of a terrible enough nature that it would become important enough to me to prevent a society that allows them to overcome my presumption in favor of peace and non-interference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most compelling reason that one could be against abortions is on the basis of a sort of restitution argument. If one values attempting to restore the victims of a coercive or harmful action to the state of happiness and peace that they were in before someone hurt them, then one automatically has to believe that, under some conditions, individual autonomy must take a back-seat to considerations of fairness. I happen to be of the opinion that, generally speaking, not only is restitution a very good way to solve conflicts and maintain peace and general individual autonomy in society, it is also something that I value inherently for its own sake, being an outgrowth of an attempt to deal fairly and empathetically with people. I value this in the same way I value compassion, charity, artistic skill, and other things that are not strictly implied by a purely game theoretic egoist framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the argument would have to proceed like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some activities have a risk of hurting others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If such an activity is voluntarily undertaken, knowing the risk, and someone &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; get hurt, then the person who did it has voluntarily harmed someone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being put in a position of dependency without one’s consent is a form of harm. (For instance, throwing someone who can’t swim into a pool without their consent.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone voluntarily harms someone else, it is unfair to not at least attempt to restore them in some way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sex has a risk of creating a fetus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When a fetus is created, it is dependent for its life on someone else maintaining it, and it could not have consented to this. Therefore a fetus is harmed by being created.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone voluntarily engages in sex, and that results in pregnancy, then it would be unfair to the fetus to abort it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since it is unfair, abortions should not be allowed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is by far the best argument against abortion that there is. All of the other one’s I’ve seen are just various levels of hypocrisy, moral panic, or attempts to control the bodies of people with uteruses for the purpose of perpetuating the patriarchy. I think it is interesting to note, therefore, that this argument is actually rarely used by anyone — indicating that most of the discourse around abortion isn’t really borne out of genuine moral concern on the basis of principles that value freedom and liberty, but instead is the authoritarian drivel of reactionaries. Nevertheless, even though the “pro-life” position is tainted badly by its proponents, this argument still deserves a serious response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should further be noted that this argument has far weaker conclusions than your average pro-life argument. For one thing, if carrying the fetus to term presents a serious risk to the mother’s life, it seems completely disproportionate to require her to die to make restitution to the fetus, just like you shouldn’t be required to give your life just to help someone you get into a car crash with (even if you might be seen as more heroic for doing so). For another, if the sex wasn’t voluntary (such as in the case of rape), then this whole argument breaks down, because if someone else forces you to hurt a third person, then you’re not responsible for that. Additionally, if the fetus won’t be viable, there really isn’t any point to not aborting it, since there’s no way to give it restitution for the harm done to it in any case. There are probably many more exceptions like this that even the most mild “pro-life” advocate will generally have a hard time actually admitting to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of assumptions in this argument. In order to break down why it doesn’t work, those assumptions will need to be examined and refuted in detail, but first, let me list them out. Most importantly, the argument assumes that fairness towards people is a value that is worth abridging the autonomy of others with force to preserve. Additionally, the argument assumes that a fetus is a person in the same sense that a regular human being is. On top of that, it assumes that their are either no limits to what one should have to do to give restitution, or that forced pregnancy and birth falls under those limits. Next, it assumes that doing something to someone without their consent applies in a case where the “person” in question didn’t exist prior to the action that took place. To cap it off, it assumes that creating something in a dependent state is equivalent to transitioning someone from an independent, autonomous state to a dependent one. Each of these assumptions will be examined in the following sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is fairness a value that is worth abridging the autonomy of others to preserve? This might seem like a difficult question at first, until you remember that, to a certain degree, the concept of fairness, or at least the balancing of interests, is &lt;em&gt;baked into&lt;/em&gt; the concept of autonomy and proper &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/12/19/relations.html&quot;&gt;anarchistic relations&lt;/a&gt;. To prevent someone from unilaterally subordinating another to their will, taking away their ability to pursue their own interests and make their own choices, all interests in an interaction must be considered equally. This is the sense of fairness which obviously should be supported through force to a certain degree. Outside of that, other conceptions of fairness are much weaker, which is why disambiguating the strong form of autonomy-supporting fairness, and the rest of the applications of the term, is so important. These other meanings include asking for a too-high price for something, cheating at a game, being a hypocrite, not keeping a promise, etc. All of these things are unfair and might make you an asshole, but none of them seem important enough to me to warrant enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the question becomes: is the &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of fairness spoke about in the anti-abortion argument the strong kind of fairness, or the weak kind? I believe that it is of the weak kind, for this reason: the interaction that involved the harm has already taken place, and is not being repeated. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; interaction is the one in which the interests were imbalanced, and which should have been prevented if possible, but that’s in the past now and there isn’t anything anyone can do about it. You can show your remorse, empathy, and sense of compassion by doing something in the present to help, but since the actually strongly unfair interaction is not ongoing, force isn’t proportionate. It’s a lot like a contract in that sense: if you make a contract, if you break it then you should avoid perpetuating subordinatory relationships, such as holding on to the possessions the other person only gave you conditionally, but once those relations are over, there isn’t any hold on you besides just social norms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore it seems pretty clear to me that abortion does not actually violate the kind of fairness that it is worth breaking the presumption of non-interference to enforce. This knocks out the conclusion of the argument directly, and should make the whole point moot. There are, however, many more flaws with this argument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next problem with this argument is that it assumes that a fetus is a full person with full personhood. This is perhaps a reasonable concession to make in order to respond to some “pro-life” arguments, as Judith Jarvis Thomson did in ‘A Defense of Abortion,’ but aside from that there is no reason to grant such a concession. What makes something a morally significant entity, a &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt;, is the capacity to have desires, make choices motivated by reasoning processes (however faulty), have internal experiences and consciousness, handle abstract thinking and reasoning, and communicate these things. It does not have to be &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; those things, but it has to be capable of doing them or learning to do so. Like gender identity and other things of a sociological or psychological nature, personhood is a spectrum and there are many factors that contribute to it, but I think the absurdity of according a fetus the status of personhood is pretty clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fetus is a clump of human cells, with different DNA from its host, yes, but you can produce a clump of human cells, with different DNA from any other human, quite easily. It’s been done to make a pong-playing AI, in fact, and no one seemed to have an issue with that. And that’s a tiny &lt;em&gt;brain&lt;/em&gt; that processes inputs and responds to them in a semi-intelligent manner, made of human cells! A fetus doesn’t even have a brain like that until well into its development. A fetus doesn’t even have the capacity to feel, let alone feel pain, until after twenty weeks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A human fetus does not have the capacity to experience pain until  after viability. Rigorous scientific studies have found that the  connections necessary to transmit signals from peripheral sensory nerves to the brain, as well as the brain structures necessary to process  those signals, do not develop until at least 24 weeks of gestation. Because it lacks these connections and structures, the fetus does not  even have the physiological capacity to perceive pain until at least 24  weeks of gestation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In fact, the perception of pain requires more than just the  mechanical transmission and reception of signals. Pain is “an emotional  and psychological experience that requires conscious recognition of a  noxious stimulus.”ii This capacity does not develop until the third trimester at the earliest, well past the period between 20 weeks  and viability. The evidence shows that the neural circuitry necessary to distinguish touch from painful touch does not, in fact, develop until  late in the third trimester. The occurrence of intrauterine fetal  movement is not an indication that a fetus can feel pain.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fetuses are vaguely human-shaped clumps of cells, nothing more. Just as we could  theoretically sequence a new human genome and grow an entire, fully grown human body without a brain, and we wouldn’t call that a human person worthy of moral consideration, and just as we couldn’t consider a brain dead person as a person either, neither should we consider a fetus a human person until it’s brain has developed sufficiently to allow for self-awareness, which usually only occurs at 15 to 24 months after the fetus has been born. In fact, until they are viable on their own apart from the mother, it’s not even clear to me that they should be categorized as a separate organism, and they certainly don’t have any autonomy worthy of consideration, since they are essentially completely dependent on the host for sustained life in a physical, biological manner — i.e. they are parasites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One counterargument might be that a fetus is a &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; person, and that if you just “leave it alone” it would become a person, so by preventing its development, you are in effect killing it. This is absurd, of course. Preventing the existence of something is not destroying it, just as preventing me from building a model kit is not destroying my model after it is built. Moreover, fetuses aren’t plants. They don’t just “grow” on their own. Instead they require constant use of the mother’s body, because they are parasites. Thus it isn’t really the case that you are preventing something from happening that would happen without your interference; when you get an abortion you are stopping a process that is actively and already using your body to get something done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse than that, by putting forward this argument, or in fact any argument against abortion that has to do with the ‘rights’ of the fetus, the person putting forward the argument is raising the questionable rights of something that is only arguably a person, and in fact probably isn’t, over the rights of a real, live, adult human being who we know &lt;em&gt;for a fact&lt;/em&gt; is a person. This is absolutely epistemically irresponsible, especially considering the stakes of the case: on the basis of flimsy definitions of humanity, we are taking away the very real bodily autonomy of people, controlling their bodies and their lives, and perpetuating a system of power and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next assumption that this argument makes is that there is either no limit to what someone can be expected to give in restitution to attempt to make their ‘victim’ whole, or that requiring forced pregnancy and birth falls below that limit. Neither of those assumptions makes any sense whatsoever, and since the second one depends on the failure of the first, I’ll cover them one at a time, in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with — is there a limit to the restitution required by fairness? To this, I answer a resounding yes. Besides not requiring someone to give restitution in a way that causes their death — because no one can be expected to give up their lives under any circumstances — I think it seems pretty clear that if the cost of giving restitution is a severe loss of autonomy, a severe detriment to someone’s interests, or a severe setback in their lives, then they should not be required to do it. It’s just too onerous for a value like that. It would be absurd, for instance, to require someone who cheated at a poker game and spent all the money he got on food that he ate, or something else perishable, to work for the next twenty years or however long for another person as an indentured servant just to be “fair.” The upper limit of what can be “required” in fair restitution is proportional to, not the severity of the unfairness, but the severity of the action that was taken to cause the unfairness, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying this framework to pregnancy and abortion, what the people who produced the fetus actually did “to” the fetus itself wasn’t that terrible (although it’s hard to get an exact measurement), whereas having to hold something growing inside you, like some kind of body horror monster, for nine months, at risk to your health and your life, while enduring all kinds of sickness and cramps, and setting back whatever else you wanted to do with your life, and then requiring that person to give birth, which is extremely painful and difficult, is absolutely awful in comparison. The two are simply completely out of balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me bring up an example. Let’s talk about contracts again. Should someone be held to the performance of a contract, or the repayment of a debt by force? It depends on what it costs them to repay it. If it’s just a simple matter of transferring property? Sure. If it involves control over someone’s body and time, forcing them to perform actions or bear things that they don’t want to do? No, that’s horrible! If I contract with someone to, say, take a kidney, I should have the right to rescind my consent to the operation at any time. Same if I make a contract to have sex with someone. Need is only a slightly greater pull here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is the question of whether &lt;em&gt;creating something&lt;/em&gt; can be said to be something that is done without that thing’s consent at all. This is a point that a number of people have brought up to me regarding the anti-abortion argument given above. In essence, the counter argument is that if something didn’t exist at all, then there was not even a conceivable possibility or capacity for consent, and if you take an ought-implies-can Kantian approach, that means you weren’t obligated to try to get consent anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I’m not particularly convinced by this argument. I’m actually pretty convinced that bringing something into existence is, actually, a non-consensual act. I mean, it actually kind of makes sense when someone says, for instance, “I didn’t ask to be born,” and I think that’s telling. Nevertheless, the fact that this is ambiguous further undermines the strength of this argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another objection to the anti-abortion argument is that it rests on a fundamental, hidden equivocation. In the first half of the argument, it is established that doing something to someone, without their consent, that takes away their autonomy, making them dependent on you for help, is a form of harm. In the second part of the argument, I treat this as equivalent to creating something that never had autonomy or independence, in the position of being dependent. These two things seem pretty clearly different to me, however, and I think the second version borrows its strength from conflation with the first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of the intuition in favor of restitution and fairness stems in response to this harm comes from the transition from independent, autonomous agent to dependent one: that is where the harm occurs, since that is where one person’s autonomy was disrespected and their independence lost. An existing person’s interests were ignored, something was unilaterally done to them, and it removed the one thing that is universally and always valuable to an egoist from them. This is specifically where the harm occurs, and because of that, it brings the autonomy- and agency-related &lt;strong&gt;strong&lt;/strong&gt; fairness into the mix, which is what allows it to possibly override considerations of autonomy overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the case of the fetus, there was nothing that existed and was autonomous before it was created or at the moment of creation. Nothing’s autonomy was disrespected, nothings independence was robbed from it. It had no autonomy because it was dead (did not exist), and then it did exist and &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; had no autonomy. Therefore, &lt;em&gt;at best&lt;/em&gt;, the only conception of fairness in play is the weak one. If anything, in a sense, by giving birth to the fetus you &lt;em&gt;gave&lt;/em&gt; it something it did not have before. You cannot be held responsible for taking something away from someone when they never had it to begin with, no matter what state changes you do inflict on them. By aborting a fetus you may be preventing it from gaining something, but you are not keeping something back that you took from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, ultimately, it comes down to this: bodily autonomy, and individual autonomy in general, is the most important thing to me. That is what I care about the most. I also think that choosing to put other things other than autonomy on the top of one’s value hierarchy is a very quick way to produce negative and undesirable outcomes for almost any value hierarchy, if followed through consistently. Therefore, as an anarchist with a commitment to autonomy first, I am in favor of abortion. I recently found a quote that I like on this topic, so let me wrap up with it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The “unborn” are a convenient group of people to advocate for. They never make demands of you; they are morally uncomplicated, unlike the incarcerated, addicted, or the chronically poor; they don’t resent your condescension or complain that you are not politically correct; unlike widows, they don’t ask you to question patriarchy; unlike orphans, they don’t need money, education, or childcare; unlike aliens, they don’t bring all that racial, cultural, and religious baggage that you dislike; they allow you to feel good about yourself without any work at creating or maintaining relationships; and when they are born, you can forget about them, because they cease to be unborn. You can love the unborn and advocate for them without substantially challenging your own wealth, power, or privilege, without re-imagining social structures, apologizing, or making reparations to anyone… — Methodist Pastor David Barnhart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acog.org/advocacy/facts-are-important/fetal-pain&quot;&gt;https://www.acog.org/advocacy/facts-are-important/fetal-pain&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><category term="ethics" /><category term="politics" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="anarchism" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Introduction to Fuzzy Pragmatist Bayesian Epistemology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/fuzzy-logic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Introduction to Fuzzy Pragmatist Bayesian Epistemology" /><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/fuzzy-logic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/fuzzy-logic.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-introduction&quot;&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of pragmatist epistemology is not to arrive at absolute truth, at certain knowledge about the universe, or any of the other goals which have occupied philosophers across the millennia. It has a more humble goal: to help human beings achieve our goals in a world that does not bend to our every whim, a world that is more than happy to slap us in the face with our misconceptions and preconceived notions at every turn. It offers a way to adapt to the world, to move with the current instead of against it, by providing a toolkit for predicting future experiences — the outcomes of our actions, the changes in the world around us — based on the only information we have available to us: past experiences. Human beings are thrust into a world that effects us on a deep and intimate level, one which we can only close our eyes to by committing suicide; therefore we have a choice: death, or learning. Choose to shut the world out permanently, or learn how to operate within it. We cannot know whether we are a brain in a vat, or being deceived by a demon, or NPCs in a cosmic simulation run by higher beings. But until someone offers us the red pill — a way to leave the simulation, if it is one — this world is as real to us as it gets, as real as any other. We have no choice but to face it, to live in it, and to try to live in it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are therefore three core insights which form the foundations of pragmatist epistemology. First, that I experience things, and these experiences effect me. Second, that something which is not a product of my desires or beliefs, but which can influence these things, is what produces my experiences. Third, that I only have my connection, through my experiences past and present, to this external thing. The implications of these axioms form my epistemology, and in this essay I will lay out these implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-definitions&quot;&gt;2. Definitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, we must lay out some definitions. First among them is the definition of “&lt;strong&gt;truth&lt;/strong&gt;.” What, in the pragmatist framework, does it mean for a proposition to be true? Considering that the goal of pragmatist epistemology is to arrive at propositions that help us navigate our world, it seems clear that the goal should be propositions that answer questions about future experiences, since these kinds of questions — what will happen when I push this? what will I see when I turn the next corner? when will winter arrive? — are the most helpful in understanding how to live and act. If the goal is predictive propositions, then the fullest satisfaction of that goal would be propositions that are &lt;em&gt;perfectly&lt;/em&gt; predictive — i.e. propositions that predict the next experiences of any agent under any circumstance relevant to the subject of the proposition, past, present, future, in any place, for anyone, at any time. Since the definition of truth is relative to the goal of epistemic framework one is operating within, the definition of truth in my framework is just such a perfectly predictive proposition. Thus, a proposition is true if it predicts the experiences of any agent, at any time, in any place, regarding the subject of the proposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be &lt;strong&gt;truth-apt&lt;/strong&gt;, therefore, a proposition must be one that can be used to predict experiences with regard to the subject of said proposition. Otherwise, within this framework, there is not really any sense in which the proposition can be counted to be true to some degree, or false to some degree. It is important to note that since the range over which a proposition’s predictiveness can vary, and the accuracy of its predictions can also vary, truth in this framework is a spectrum. The ultimate, ideal goal, as described above, is 100% predictiveness in both detail and scope; propositions can actually be closer to or farther away from this goal as their accuracy and scope differ. Truth is a spectrum, and it varies across several variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the truth of a proposition depends on whether it accurately predicts the experiences that agents could have with regards to its subject, &lt;strong&gt;meaningful&lt;/strong&gt;  propositions must always ultimately be about experiences of some kind, about &lt;em&gt;interactions&lt;/em&gt; with an object. The meaningfulness of any proposition is dependent on its capacity to effect the experiences of some agent. To clarify, it is not relative to its actual effect on any existing agent, because that would mean statements about things that no one can yet check, but could conceivably be checked in the future, would be meaningless; instead the truth of a proposition is relative to its possible effects on any &lt;em&gt;conceivable&lt;/em&gt; agent: thus if someone &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; check concerning whether a proposition accurately describes a certain experience or not, then the proposition is meaningful. Conversely, if no one could &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; check whether a proposition accurately describes some experience concerning its subject, then the proposition is meaningless, useless, and empty nonsense. Note that meaningfulness is not identical with truth-aptness. This is because some statements are definitions and other &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; true statements, which simply assign names to certain experiences or derive conceptual conclusions from them. They need to be about experience in some sense in order to be meaningful because without that then they couldn’t really be used to come to true or false conclusions, wouldn’t really be “about” anything that is really relevant to human life, but they don’t need to make statements about some actual experience in such a way that they could be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is such a thing as “&lt;strong&gt;referred&lt;/strong&gt;” meaning or truth-aptness, too. A proposition that is not directly about an experience can be meaningful as it relates to some conceptual apparatus that ultimately says something about experience, even though without it it would be pointless and useless. Likewise, a proposition could be true to the degree that the system of propositions (that it is derived from or that are in part derived from it) can lead to true propositions in the final conclusion. An example of this last type of thing is clearly to be found in physics. In physics, the givens of a problem are “true,” in that they describe experiences of a thing, and the results of the physics problem are also (hopefully) true, in that they predict future experiences based on those givens. But the intermediate steps of the mathematics aren’t really “true” in any real sense, apart from what they imply about the starting point and ending point. Oftentimes, if you try to translate what the intermediate algebra steps in a physics problem “mean” by applying the standard definitions of the variables, as you use them at the beginning and end, you’ll get nonsensical and often clearly counterfactual claims about reality. This is why when people doing theoretical physics try to derive claims about how reality works from the mathematics they are using to describe that reality, one should accord their claims only a portion of the credence you accord to their predictions overall. It might be the case that their theories are predictive because, when investigated, the intermediate steps of the mathematical process are propositions that accurately describe how the intermediate steps of the physical process look when we check, but it could almost equally be the case that this is not so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point one might be worrying that this is verging too closely to the picture theory of language put forward by Wittgenstein in the &lt;em&gt;Tractatus&lt;/em&gt;, and that therefore these definitions might fall afoul of the same problem that his did, in rendering the very philosophical text that put them forward ultimately meaningless. This is not the case, however. I have been very careful to state that propositions are about experiences, but not that these experiences necessarily must be about the outside world external to our consciousness. Therefore, psychological propositions and others that speak about our own internal experiences of existence are just as truth-apt as ones that speak about our experiences of the world, although they are much more difficult to demonstrate to others. Thus when I talk about how to use pragmatist epistemology later in this essay, and discuss how to arrive at propositions that are more true or less false, this is still a statement about experience, because I am describing how some methods will produce the experience of expected outcomes more often than the experience of unexpected ones. And the definitions I gave above are derived from propositions about experience from the first section, and will influence propositions about experience later, and are, furthermore, in themselves, propositions about experience in a sense, as the definition of truth for instance has itself to do with experiences of expected or unexpected outcomes. Although they don’t &lt;em&gt;predict&lt;/em&gt; things and are therefore not truth-apt, definitions are still about experiences, in that they put labels on them, and so they are still meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another point needs to be made as well. It can actually sometimes be rational for someone to stop refining and improving a theory before it reaches 100% truth (according to the definition just given),  interestingly, because a theory doesn’t have to be predictive in every conceivable situation to be predictive &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; for the purposes of an individual. This can be because it is predictive in all the situations an individual is likely to find themselves in, so the possibility of running into a situation where it doesn’t work doesn’t outweigh the extra effort of improving it, or because it is not perfectly predictive but is right often enough that the accidents caused by being wrong are not enough to outweigh the extra effort in learning more, or because the penalties for being wrong are negligible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One needs to be careful with choosing to stop truth-seeking in a particular area, though, because it can be very difficult to predict when one will come face to face with an area where one’s beliefs don’t hold true, since that would require predicting unknown unknowns, which is basically definitionally impossible. Therefore, to decide whether to continue investigating something or not, one needs to consider the magnitude and probability of harm occurring if what one thinks is true on the basis of the evidence one has so far turns out to be false. This is called &lt;strong&gt;falsity risk.&lt;/strong&gt; If the risk of something one believes turning out to be false is low, there may be no need to investigate it further; but if it is high, than a continual re-evaluation of the theory in terms of new data, and a continual process of trying to acquire new data, is the best course of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, there is a sort of reverse falsity risk as well: some of the unknown unknowns you have to deal with are possible positive results that you are missing out on by not known the full truth or not improving your theory. These chances, too, need to be factored in when choosing to either let a theory rest or keep examining it — in cases where no other courses of action concerning a subject are open to you anyway, for instance, positive and negative falsity risk are pretty much neutralized, since knowing more won’t help anyway. Thus, to borrow a term from game theory, while there &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be such a thing as “rational ignorance,” it is probably not as common as people take it to be, since leaving off the further pursuit of truth in many cases is a very risky business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next sections, I will defend the individual elements of my analysis. Once that is complete, I will assemble them into a form of fuzzy Bayesian induction, and a procedure for setting the priors of that Bayesian form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-the-principle-of-phenomenological-conservatism&quot;&gt;3. The Principle of Phenomenological Conservatism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle element of my approach to pragmatist epistemology, which is assumed — although not explicitly restated and used — throughout the rest of this essay, is (a weak version of) the &lt;strong&gt;principle of phenomenological conservatism&lt;/strong&gt;. This principle is a formalization of the implicit motivations behind my entire philosophy of epistemology, as stated in the introduction. It states that, in the absence of positive reasons to do otherwise, it is reasonable to accept the &lt;em&gt;appearance&lt;/em&gt; of things as being indicative of their actual reality. It is only when new appearances are introduced to us which make the simple reality of previous appearances less likely (called &lt;em&gt;defeaters&lt;/em&gt;) that we should doubt the direct reality of the phenomena we experience. Crucially, it is not the &lt;em&gt;mere possibility&lt;/em&gt; of a contradictory appearance that should make us doubt everyday, non-defeated appearances, as in the logic of the skeptics; it is the presence of an actual defeater for a particular appearance that is necessary. Therefore the general possibility of hallucination or dreaming does not undercut all one’s experiences by itself — one must have a reason to think that some particular experience one is having is a hallucination or dream. This fundamental difference from the skeptics is what allows those who embrace the principle of phenomenological conservatism to defeat external world skepticism in one single stroke: namely, that in all of the experiences I have, there appear to be objects external to me, a whole world of them, and while I may from time to time have reason to doubt a particular external object or whatever, that does not mean I must doubt all appearances. Thus, I can be reasonable in my starting assumption, based on appearance, that the external world does in fact exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons why this is a necessary, almost unavoidable starting principle. In the first place, since all we ultimately have to deal with is appearances, and our goal is primarily to describe, document, navigate, and predict those appearances, right out of the gate we have a strong reason to take the phenomena presented to our awareness at face value: something is happening that appears a certain way to us, and it is that appearance that has the most immediate and, in the absence of anything else, important effect on us; we have to figure out what to do about it, how to deal with it, and taking it at face value for what it is is a start. If it appears to me that a truck is bearing down on me while I’m crossing the street, it doesn’t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; matter whether the automobile is truly there or not — in the end, acting as if it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; there is going to be the better plan. If it turns out it isn’t, better to investigate why the appearances I was presented with were wrong after the fact, than to doubt in the moment, when I need to get on with life, and possibly get run over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is not always the case; for instance, when dealing with some mental condition which causes frequent hallucinations or paranoid fantasies, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; acting on those appearances is probably going to be better than acting on them, in the long run. But the crucial fact here is that generally speaking a person with such a condition is in fact aware of it, and aware of the harm they do to others and themselves when they act on every appearance that occurs to them. Oftentimes, additionally, it is possible for them to differentiate between real and unreal, at least after the fact, because the elements of their illusions are fundamentally unusual and nonsensical when compared to the rest of their experience and the more constant appearances of things. Therefore there are defeaters in place here whereas they are not in place in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason that the principle of phenomenological conservatism is a reasonable starting point is based in more abstract notions of correct reasoning. Essentially, as a general rule, one should not accept the truth of a proposition without sufficient reason to think that it is true. To reject this proposition is, by the law of the excluded middle, to accept its opposite: that it is acceptable to believe any proposition, whether it has sufficient evidence for its truth or not. To choose that route (the route of the epistemic nihilist) obviously makes all epistemology impossible, even pragmatist epistemology, which is not a particularly useful stance, but moreover, it presents the would-be epistemic nihilist with a two-horned dilemma: either they must reject internal consistency and allow themselves to be hypocrites, who accept some propositions and reject others (including their opposites) on the basis of nothing at all, or they must reject internal consistency in the process of trying to avoid such hypocrisy, by following their rule consistently and believing all propositions, even contradictory or nonsensical ones, since they don’t need evidence to choose what to believe. Thus, believing that a particular appearance is untrustworthy without a defeater to contradict it is a violation of sensible reasoning, and commits one to an incoherent and untenable path into intellectual destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final reason is that ultimately, all of our reasons to doubt appearances appeal to appearances themselves. The reason the skeptic doubts the veracity of the information given to them by their senses is because they have from time to time had appearances that were contradictory, which cast doubt on the truth of what they sense. Thus we are all already, in a sense, waiting for defeaters to come along and tell us not to trust appearances; the only difference is just in how sensitive some of us are to those defeaters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that we should believe everything that seems true to us in spite of everything. For one thing, this limited, weak version of the principle of phenomenological conservatism does not say that &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; proposition is &lt;em&gt;justified&lt;/em&gt; by the appearance of truth, as the stronger version does, because I don’t think those arguments work very well. Instead it merely proposes the appearances of things in our experience as a starting point to work from; therefore propositions that are not directly statements about objects of our experience do not gain the benefit of this principle, and it is still our duty to investigate to try to discover evidence for propositions we want to hold true by looking for experiences that confirm them, or defeaters that undercut them. This is a principle of phenomenological conservatism for things we experience alone, not for all propositions, because the appearance of an experience aligning with a proposition is different than simply a proposition that one has an intuitive inclination toward. So one is not justified, for instance, in believing that there is a god until someone disproves its existence simply because one has been brought up in a religious culture and it seems inherently likely that there is a god; one must first have had some kind of experience with a god, and must then deal with all of the defeaters for there being a god (for instance, the lack of the supernatural more generally, the lack of need of gods to explain things, even most religious experiences) before one can be rationally justified in accepting the appearance of a god.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-why-induction&quot;&gt;4. Why Induction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When operating in the world, we are forced to take action whether we are certain in our beliefs about the world or not — the entire condition of our existence is that of being forced to act on the basis of what we guess or think about the world, to deal with uncertainty and to have the courage to act despite it. Induction is, in essence, merely a reification of that principle: although no reasoning can directly support or substantiate induction without first assuming it (as Hume showed), since we have no other information about how the world will effect us, and what experiences it will present to us, than the experiences it has given us in the past, our best bet is to attempt to derive the best picture we can of the world based on those past experiences. Fortunately, induction is a self-correcting process: if our expectations, based on past experiences are wrong, and the world actually appears to us in a different way than we were led to expect, then we need only either correct our expectations, by either learning how these contrasting experiences can be subsumed under the same principle, thereby granting the weight of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of our past experiences to a new guess, or come up with a new principle and reinterpret our older experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, there is no real reason to expect that such a process wouldn’t work. After all, there is no &lt;em&gt;prima facie&lt;/em&gt; reason to assume that the default state of the world is endless chaotic flux, always changing, perhaps in need of some lawgiver to subjugate it, instead of assuming the opposite, that the inherent nature of the world is that of a clockwork machine that proceeds according to orderly laws. Actually, there is no possible benefit to navigating the world at all to assume the former, whereas there is a chance of benefit in assuming the latter. For, if I choose to believe that the universe is chaotic, then I will constantly be confused and adrift whether it is or it isn’t because I will have nothing to go on, not even my past experiences, and therefore no ability to even &lt;em&gt;guess&lt;/em&gt; what happens next; whereas if I choose to believe that it is orderly, then I will be constantly foiled if it is chaotic, but able to act sensibly if it is not. This is the core reason that everyone, even those who deny induction, ultimately cannot help but act as if induction is true: they have to act, and acting on the basis of nothing is guaranteed to only have a random success rate, whereas acting on the basis of past experience at least conceptually has some chance of having a higher-than-random success rate. One can represent these choices with a payoff matrix:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Universe: Chaos&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Universe: Order&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Assume: Chaos&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Assume: Order&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This necessity of acting on the basis of induction in order to survive and reason, whether one thinks it is justified or not, is what I call the property of &lt;strong&gt;performative basicness&lt;/strong&gt;. There are some things which one cannot discard no matter how much one doubts it or views it as baseless, because to discard it is either phenomenologically &lt;em&gt;impossible&lt;/em&gt;, such as the fact that there is some &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; which is thinking and experiencing things, which I typically identify with “myself,” or so completely impractical that attempting to do so is a form of mental or physical suicide — such as induction. To cease to act on any basis at all, to just act randomly because there is no certainty that anything one knows about the past will hold for the future, will quickly lead to problems, as one drinks bleach, walks out into traffic, and so on. The reason that doing those things sounds ridiculous is because inductively we know that they are a bad idea, but if you truly discard induction there is no reason to expect that they &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; actually harm you! Notice that the property of performative basicness isn’t a justification &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;. Instead, it is an observation that we cannot honestly and in good faith leave some things behind, that they are a necessary part of our existence, and so it is better to acknowledge their existence, catalog them, use them if they’re useful, and try to reduce the number of things that we think we can’t leave behind so that our chances of being wrong about things are minimized (since there is no guarantee that just because something is performatively basic, that it is actually accurate to reality).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, there is another thing to consider: all else being equal, the default assumption should be that nothing has changed. That should be the null hypothesis, as that is the simplest assumption to make: when introduced to something, nothing needs to happen, no new concept or element needs to be added, for it to stay the same. Meanwhile, for something to change, that introduces two entities: the thing before the change, and the thing after. There can be reasons to reverse this assumption, as to assert it absolutely would be to bring a Principle of Sufficient Reason into play without due justification, but again changing and staying the same are at least equally likely, and one of them is a bit less complex. This, however, should be dealt with more in the next section, on the principle of parsimony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-why-the-principle-of-parsimony&quot;&gt;5. Why The Principle of Parsimony&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle of parsimony, more commonly referred to as Occam’s Razor, might, at first blush, seem to be a rather arbitrary statement of theoretical preference. Why &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; multiply the entities involved in a theory beyond what is strictly necessary? After all, there is no law of the universe saying that everything has to be as simple as possible to produce the experiences necessary. If we look deeper, however, it quickly becomes clear that the principle of parsimony is a deeply integral part of any consistent and rational attempt to build theories about anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first factor that makes the principle of parsimony necessary is a probabilistic one. Because there is no such thing as certain knowledge outside one’s own head, any proposition not about incorrigible phenomenological experiences has a non-zero chance of turning out to be wrong. Therefore, the more propositions are required to describe a theory, the greater the probability that the theory will turn out to be incorrect.  Therefore, &lt;em&gt;ceterus paribus&lt;/em&gt;, we should favor theories that require few propositions to describe, in order to minimize our chances of being wrong. This factor can be overcome, however, if the propositions you are using in your simpler theory are more probably wrong than the propositions you use in a more complex one, such as would be the case if they either were worse descriptions of experience, made worse predictions, or led to worse predictions (through referred truth). It is important to clarify, here, that when I’m talking about probabilities, I’m using them in a compound sense to refer to a combination of Bayesian credence-probability, accuracy of description, and percentage of possible worlds, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in the sense of frequentist probability that relies on past experiences. Therefore, the probability of a proposition being incorrect relies on the possibility that there are other worlds that would produce the same experiences that led be to construct that proposition, for which that proposition is not true, the accuracy of how well that proposition describes the experiences it is supposed to be about, and how well it fits with other propositions known to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second factor that makes the principle of parsimony a good starting point for theory-building is that it is a natural starting point at the limit. In other words, when starting to build a theory about some phenomena, you can either start at the simplest end of the spectrum, a theory composed of a single proposition, or you can start at the other end of the spectrum with an infinitely complex theory composed of an unlimited number of propositions. The one end of the pole is represented by the principle of parsimony, the other the logical conclusion if you believe that theories should be arbitrarily complex. If you start at the simpler end, then you can build up complexity as needed, as prediction failures require you to increase the complexity of the theory, while if you start at the other end, there can be no justification for decreasing the number of propositions involved in your theory, besides the pragmatic one that it’s too hard to do and so fewer propositions are needed — but that’s an argument for the principle of parsimony too, since if complexity making theories difficult to conceptualize or use is a factor in the practicality of a theory, then trying to make a theory as simple as possible while keeping it functional is the natural conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third factor is that the &lt;em&gt;entire point&lt;/em&gt; of developing a theory in the first place is to simplify: to find an underlying principle behind many diverse propositions, in order to make the world navigable, instead of treating each experience as a totally separate and unique event which can be filed away as a proposition but not linked to anything else. Thus, inherent in the very concept of pragmatic epistemology, and epistemology in general for that matter, is simplification: finding the principles that underlie things. If you’re going to deny the principle of parsimony, for consistency’s sake you have to give up knowing or guessing anything whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important implication of the principle of parsimony is that a theory should be parsimonious not just in its description, but in its implications. A theory that has a lot of implications — that makes a lot of predictions, in other words — that have not yet been verified and confirmed to be in accordance with it, is a theory that is very likely to make a prediction wrong, since each prediction has a chance of being wrong because some detail of the theory matches many areas in past and future experiences but not all. Therefore, theories with wide-ranging implications are to be preferred only if those implications can be, and are, verified to be accurate — in which case those implications add to the likelihood of the theory, since the more of past experiences it explains the more future experiences it is likely to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many subsidiary practical reasons to favor a simpler theory, as long as it is capable of explaining the same data, over a more complex one. For one thing, a more complex theory is more likely to be contradictory, to have hidden assumptions, and to have logical errors. The larger a theory grows, the greater these chances, get, so a theory that is more complex than it absolutely needs to be should be looked at with suspicion. In a similar vein, a larger and more complex theory is more unwieldy, meaning it is more difficult to generate predictions, and even more difficult to make sure the predictions one gets from it actually follow from it. Since I am pursuing a pragmatic theory of epistemology, these considerations should certainly count for something!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other ways to measure the complexity of a theory than counting the number of propositions required to describe it. These ways will ultimately &lt;em&gt;reduce&lt;/em&gt; to that, which is why they are pretty much equivalent in justification, but depending on the circumstances they may be a lot easier to actually check than breaking down your hypothesis into symbolic logic and then into basic propositions (where conjugated propositions count as multiple). I’ll make a table, with each entry in order of relative weight in one’s consideration. The distance between the weights is exponential of some variety, but the specific distance between the weights will change depending on the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Justification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Entity type number (&lt;em&gt;ETN&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The number of types of entities&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;It often requires a huge amount of statements about things to introduce a new type of entity&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Type complexity (&lt;em&gt;TC&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The complexity of the types of entities required&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;This is merely an expression of a feature the former&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Phenomenological distance (&lt;em&gt;PD&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The distance between the appearance of how things work, and how they are supposed to work in the theory&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Appearances are all we have to work with by default, so introducing more distance between experience and theory introduces room for error as the two diverge&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Entity number (&lt;em&gt;EN&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The number of entities&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;It requires more statements about the world to add new entities&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since all of these have to do with different components of the overall propositional complexity, then you can either sum them up or multiply them (as the case requires for the individual aspect) without fear of double-counting. IF there are any other aspects of the complexity of a theory that are left out, you can also add those in. In essence, then, you can look at the complexity of a theory as a mathematical equation, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/assets/math1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then just add in any variables or values you should to capture other parts of the propositional complexity not dealt with by the variables in the table above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful though, as I will explain later, the mathematics to be found in this essay are &lt;em&gt;strictly&lt;/em&gt; for clarifying my words. It is impossible to come up with non-arbitrary numeric values for most of the variables I’m talking about anyway, so the attempt to do so, in order to actually do the algebra, would just multiply and reproduce any mistakes you’ve made, and give a false sense of precision and accuracy. It is better to treat each variable as a vague quantity, or a value with substantial error bounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-kinds-of-predictions&quot;&gt;6. Kinds of Predictions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are assessing the success or truth value of a proposition on the basis of how well it predicts experiences, it is necessary to have a clear idea of what exactly is meant by prediction. The prototypical case of prediction, the one that is primarily used in science, is the &lt;em&gt;ex ante&lt;/em&gt; prediction. To put it in experiential/pragmatic terms, an &lt;em&gt;ex ante&lt;/em&gt; prediction is a proposition about a certain experience of its subject which describes certain details of that experience before that experience takes place, typically along with some indication of how that experience might be generated, how it can be observed, or when it will occur. For instance, “if you touch the stove while it is on, you will get burned.” An accurate prediction is one which, to borrow from William James for a moment, creates an experience of recognition in a person who is first given the prediction and then exposed to the subject of said prediction. If one is not surprised by the experiences which one’s actions or existence relative to a subject generates (surprise being the opposite of expectation/recognition), than this implies that any reasoning or planning one made on the basis of one’s expectations will also be confirmed, which is what allows one to act and plan, since if one expects certain outcomes if one thing happens, and other outcomes if another does, then one can act towards making one or the other of the outcomes happen in order to get positive experiences, and if this leads to expected outcomes, then that means the planning worked, and if this is consistently possible then planning is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another type of prediction is &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; prediction. This is a much more tricky kind of prediction, because it works by deriving your theories from experiences that are already available, which means that it is all too easy to create a &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; theory. An &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; theory is one that is randomly thrown together with no actual predictive power beyond the data that was given for its construction, because it presents either no underlying principle, or an underlying principle that is actually inaccurate and then jam-packed with exceptions in order to fit past experiences, indicating the need for more exceptions in the future and therefore obviating its predictive ability. A stronger attention to the principle of parsimony, and careful attention to avoiding making exceptions or stretching the truth in order to make a theory fit, is needed for &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; predictions to actually confirm a theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most common mistakes made when &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; predictions (predictions of experiences already available to the one constructing the theory) are used to evaluate a theory is to confuse a theory being &lt;em&gt;compatible&lt;/em&gt; with some experience occurring with a theory that &lt;em&gt;predicts&lt;/em&gt; some experience. A theory needs to not just be able to be made to fit with some experience, it actually needs to predict that experience as being more likely than any relevantly different experience — only if that is the case is the theory actually any good for producing &lt;em&gt;ex ante&lt;/em&gt; predictions, which are the kind that are actually useful. A theory that predicts all experiences equally, with a non-zero probability for each, or a too-wide range of experiences with equal or nearly indistinguishable probability, is a theory that actually provides no useful information about how to set our expectations &lt;em&gt;ex ante&lt;/em&gt;, and therefore no useful information about how to act or live, while it can be fit with nearly any experience after the fact because it “predicts” nearly any experience. For instance, pretend someone handed you a black box with a button on the side and a screen on top that displayed a single digit number. Which “theory” about how the box works would be the most useful to you: one that said that the box had an 80% chance of showing a 1, a 10% chance of showing a 2, and a 10% chance of showing anything else, or a theory that said that it could show the digits 0-9? Assuming it is correct, the first theory gives you far more actionable information, while the second theory tells you very little. However, the first theory is more likely to be wrong, in that it would be more difficult to reconcile it with some experiences over time with the box, while the second theory could pretty much be reconciled with any experience of the box, but it tells you basically nothing. Thus for an &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; prediction to actually &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; a prediction of a theory, that theory has to actually be able to make strong predictions. The weaker the differentiation between all its outcomes, and the more predictions a theory makes about the same event’s outcome, the weaker it “fitting” with an event is as evidence for it. This is why omnipotent, deities, for instance, are really not great as explanatory theories: they don’t really predict any outcome any as more likely or possible than any other, and are compatible with any outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-putting-it-all-together&quot;&gt;7. Putting it All Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we have two components: the principle of parsimony, and the principle of induction. The principle of induction indicates the likelihood of a theory being predictive (“true”) given a list of past experiences, by saying that the probability of a theory being true is related to the confidence with which that theory predicted past experiences that actually happened. If the theory predicted something that happened confidently, that should increase one’s credence in it,  in proportion to the confidence; if it predicted something that did not happen, one’s credence should decrease in accordance; and if the theory didn’t predict something that happened to the subject which the theory was about, that should be counted as it having predicted with complete confidence that that thing wouldn’t happen, which should be a fairly serious blow to it. The principle of parsimony indicates the inherent improbability of a given theory, the hurtle that must be &lt;em&gt;overcome&lt;/em&gt; by the theory’s predictive power in order for one to lend credence to a theory — where, as the predictive power of the theory grows over and above the inherent improbability, one’s credence rises as well. Importantly, then, the &lt;em&gt;default&lt;/em&gt; position should be not lending any credence to any particular theory at all. This is because to make any positive statement about something is to risk being wrong, and therefore to set one’s expectations wrong, which can lead to committing to courses of action that will lead to disappointment or even harm. This is also because accepting one theory before it has risen to its “burden of proof” (overcome its inherent improbability) would require, for consistency, one to accept all theories — all infinitely many of them! This of course would be both mentally impossible, and lead to contradictions, as well as being only slightly better than accepting random theories as far as setting expectations goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To formalize all that I said in the previous (large) paragraph, we can adopt Bayes’ Theorem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://wikimedia.org/api/rest_v1/media/math/render/svg/87c061fe1c7430a5201eef3fa50f9d00eac78810&quot; alt=&quot;Bayes' theorem&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;em&gt;P(A | B)&lt;/em&gt; refers to the probability that the theory (A) is true, given the fact that some experience (B) was had — i.e. the credence one should have in A after B happens. Likewise, &lt;em&gt;P(A)&lt;/em&gt; refers to the prior probability of the theory, A. Before any evidence is added to the mix to get induction working to confirm or deny A, this is equal to the negation of the complexity of A, since the probability of A starts out smaller in proportion to its inherent improbability. &lt;em&gt;P(B)&lt;/em&gt; is the probability of the experience happening at all. And &lt;em&gt;P(B | A)&lt;/em&gt; is the probability (the confidence) with which the theory predicts the experience that is being added to the pile of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theorem is applied recursively: for each no experience, the &lt;em&gt;posterior&lt;/em&gt; probability of A is calculated given that that experience happened, and then that becomes the &lt;em&gt;prior&lt;/em&gt; probability of A for the next time we get a new experience relevant to the theory, since it the posterior probability represents the new level of credence we have in A after the experience B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should actually clarify something I said above: the prior probability of a theory is not &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; 100% minus the complexity of a theory. That would imply all kinds of strange things, especially since the default needs to be &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; believing in a theory and that would imply that even before any evidence, if a theory is simple enough we should have a high credence in it. Instead, credence should start out at 50% — essentially agnostic to the truth or falsity of a theory, and then the complexity of a theory should (through some log function probably, to avoid an absolutely zero starting credence for a non-infinitely complex theory) subtract from that starting credence value. So something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/assets/math2.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, in order to have the probabilities weigh against each other proportionately, instead of having the complexity weigh less than it should, each adjustment of the evidence in favor of a theory should also be decreased by the corresponding (reversal of) the logarithm of the complexity of the theory. That way the inherent improbability of a theory is weighed equally against the probability benefits that evidence brings to it, but this does not lead to a zero or negative prior probability, or to positive evidence weighing against the theory. To sum this up in a verbal way that doesn’t require mathematics: you should never start more than agnostic to a theory, either in the positive or negative direction, but your starting places should be heavily informed by how complex the theory is to start with; and positive evidence should always weigh in a theory’s favor, but it should weigh much less in favor of a more complex theory than a simpler one that also predicted that evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-a-fuzzy-table-of-values&quot;&gt;10. A Fuzzy Table of Values&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that the mathematical expressions given for the various components of my epistemology above are intended to clarify what I am describing verbally, and are not intended to be used strictly, since quantifying many of the properties those equations use into constants would be pretty much impossible, and, beyond a certain general sense of (usually relative) size, doing so would be an exercise in arbitrary number games. Nevertheless, it is occasionally helpful to have a more exact sense of the relations of the quantities involved than informal verbal argument can usually provide, without resorting to specific numbers and ending up in the weeds. Additionally, having a preset system of categories in which to place your probabilities, which then have a consistent set of relations between them, is helpful in applying a consistent estimation of the probabilities involved across different theories; it doesn’t eliminate the subjective factor, but it is a servicable crutch in avoiding it as best as possible. Therefore, I propose to introduce what I call “fuzzy values.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, &lt;strong&gt;fuzzy values&lt;/strong&gt; are things that work &lt;em&gt;sort of&lt;/em&gt; like numbers, except that they are incapable of the exactitude of actual numbers. They act almost like labels on ranges of numbers, instead, but are defined relative to each other so that the whole group of labels, the whole classification system, can slide up or down on the actual number scale according to the conceptual needs of the problem. I will introduce the particular values of this fuzzy value system in a table:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symbol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relation Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Extremely likely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Very likely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;μ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Somewhat likely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ν&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Somewhat unlikely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4800&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ψ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Very unlikely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ω&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Extremely unlikely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;230400&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point values here indicate that it takes twelve very unlikely events in a row to make an extremely unlikely event, four somewhat unlikely events in a row to make a very unlikely event, four somewhat likely events in a row to make a somewhat unlikely event, twelve very likely events in a row to make a somewhat likely event, and one hundred extremely likely events to make an only very likely event. This scale is chosen for its intuitive properties in both frequentist and Bayesian interpretations of probability. I made it roughly symmetrical, so that each increasingly likely probability has about the same relationship to the previous one as the other probability with a similar adjective in front of it. Given the above, fuzzy probability calculus is defined by two axioms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/assets/math3.png&quot; alt=&quot;fuzzy probability calculus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for example, the probability of twelve specific very likely events happening in a row is &lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;^12 = &lt;em&gt;μ&lt;/em&gt;, somewhat likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-conclusion&quot;&gt;9. Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, pragmatically speaking, an epistemology that is best designed to manage the inherent complexity of the world, and the inherent need of humanity to act in spite of it, is a form of empiricist Bayesianism. I would like to point out that, although much of what I’ve said here might sound scientistic, in that I am focusing on sense experience and predictive capability instead of absolute true or deductive reasoning, I am not taking the methods of modern science as a dogma, or even as inspiration. In fact, I would argue that substantial areas of science actually don’t use methods like the ones I describe — although it would be much better if they did — nor are they even aware of the epistemic foundations that their practical work is implicitly based on (or the lack of such foundations, as the case may be).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a follow-up article, I intend to cover the implications of this epistemology for various areas, including logic, mathematics, reasoned argument, and so on. So if you have any questions about what the implications of my definition of truth and my method for arriving at it are for the rest of epistemology, wait for that!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><category term="epistemology" /><category term="pragmatism" /><summary type="html">1. Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Possession Versus Absentee Property</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/01/pvp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Possession Versus Absentee Property" /><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/01/pvp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/01/pvp.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I’m just going to try to explain, as succinctly as possible, the important differences between possession and absentee property (generally just referred to as “property” by Proudhon, e.g. “property is theft”). I’ve covered this distinction several times before, but I think I’ve boiled it down enough that creating a self-contained blog post for it is relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone’s possessions are the material objects that they regularly or semi-regularly use or occupy. Such things might include my home, my car, my tools, my clothes, etc. Possessions can also include things that are purchased with the intention of use, as long as they are actually used within a reasonable timeframe, and the things that someone produces by their labor time, which are generally “in their possesion” right after they make them. Possession is a practical category, negotiable with those around you; it is an extension of one’s autonomy, as it represents the sphere of actions that one can take without effecting others or without requiring their permission, and allows for some independance, self-sufficiency, etc. Respending the product of someone’s labor protects their autonomy as it prevents someone else from having authority over them. Possession is a gift granted by everyone else in society in return for reciprocation, in order to ensure the prosperty and autonomy of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Property is generally the product of one’s labor time alienated in material objects (the Lockean definition). Property can also be possessions, so I use the term “absentee property” to refer to property that is not also one’s possession: things that one does not intend to sell, nor to use oneself. Because of this, absentee property is not an extension of one’s autonomy in a direct manner: defending it neither protects one’s sphere of free action, one’s independance from the community, or anything else. Instead, absentee property extends someone’s autonomy by granting them control over something that only &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; people use, granting them authority over those people by extension. Therefore, absentee property extends someone’s autonomy in the same way that a dictator’s territorial claim extends his: in his ability to tell other people what to do and to back it up with force. The only difference in this case is that absentee property still represents the product of someone’s labor time, either produced directly by their labor or paid for by their labor. Absentee property is, however, a greater detriment to the autonomy of others than taking it is a detriment to the owner, and the owner of absentee property can still be paid for providing it to those who actually use it, paid for their risk and opportunity cost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><category term="anarchism" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Going Back to School</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/31/afraid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Going Back to School" /><published>2021-12-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/31/afraid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/31/afraid.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s New Year’s Eve. I’m sitting on the couch, sunlight falling in slanted lines across my legs, browsing on my phone. My right eyelid is twitching constantly, and it’s extremely distracting. It’s been doing it since yesterday morning; I think it’s the stress. You see, that first sentence only describes what my body has been doing. The crucial part, the part that’s generating the stress, is what’s going on inside my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m scared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably way more scared than I should be, but that just comes with the territory when you’ve got an anxiety disorder. I’m going back to campus in six days. In six days, I’m going to have to get up at 4 o’clock in the morning, Uber to San Francisco, and embark on an eight hour series of flights to the other side of the United States. That’s actually not what I’m scared of, but it sure as shit doesn’t help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In eight days, the school semester starts. Although my headaches are far, far better than they’ve been, they’re certainly not gone, and what might be worse, I took the last semester off, so I’m out of practice buckling down and working on assignments, taking notes, etc. That’s not what I’m scared of, either, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, I’m scared of two other things: the loneliness, and losing my new-found self. The first fear makes all-too-much sense; the second one makes no sense at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time I was on campus, I was extremely lonely. Yes, I was a member of three clubs that met regularly, a D&amp;amp;D group, and E House. Yes, I went to classes in person and chatted with the people there. Yes, I had a room-mate. But there’s a distinct difference between seeing human faces regularly, and actually knowing people. I think everyone who’s grown up in a city knows what I mean — it’s unnervingly easy to be &lt;em&gt;completely alone&lt;/em&gt; even in a sea of faces, and it’s even possible to be that alone among a group of people who you see repeatedly. There’s some kind of strange, diaphanous membrane that wraps you like cellophane when this happens: you can touch others, hear them, speak to them, but you can’t &lt;em&gt;touch&lt;/em&gt; them, &lt;em&gt;hear&lt;/em&gt; them, or &lt;em&gt;speak&lt;/em&gt; to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a barrier that I’ve never really learned to cross in the real world. Online, I have a slightly easier time making friends that I don’t feel this disconnection from. People who I share real emotional bonds with, call regularly, talk even more often with, share my interests with. But even then, it’s a tough process. And in the meantime, I feel &lt;em&gt;alone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isolated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On campus last time, this isolation slowly began to wear me down. I didn’t realize it at the time, but looking back that was an incredibly painful experience. I floated back and forth between classes like a spirit unable to find its final resting place. Lost, alone, not knowing it was dead yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to feel this pain again. I still feel it, but in a way it helps to have my dad around, and on top of that at least there’s nobody around besides him to really remind me of my inner isolation. I know if I go back to campus, it will hurt worse if I don’t do something different. But what? For the life of me, I don’t know the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought was clubs — find a group of people who are not just interested in the same things I am, but who are &lt;em&gt;like me.&lt;/em&gt; Don’t think so much about choosing clubs for academic purposes this time, choose them for social ones, right? And now that I’ve realized I’m a member of the LGBTQ+ community, that should be easier, since even if there aren’t clubs for cishet white men to meet and socialize, surely something like that must exist for minority groups? No such luck, though. Clubs at Penn State are almost bizarrely focused on academic pursuits. That’s not really surprising, based on what I’ve seen before, but still, that leaves me with no real plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m afraid I’ll end up isolated again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second, equally immediate and frightening fear is that I’ll lose myself, lose &lt;em&gt;Alexis&lt;/em&gt;, when I go back. It’s a fear that keeps recurring: what if, when I go back to doing this thing that I used to do before I got my concussion and then subsequently found myself, I’ll lose the new version of myself that I uncovered? What if I’ll go lose this colorful, hopeful, beautiful new vista of identity that I worked so hard to uncover, this (metaphorical) land of uncertainty? What if I go back to being the pervasive vague unease, disquiet, and dissatisfaction that permeated my life before now? The varying stages of disassociation and depersonalization that I unconsciously found (and still find) refuge in to get away from those feelings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if I lose Alexis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That won’t happen. I know it won’t happen. The very fact of my fear and unease about this happening is what &lt;em&gt;proves&lt;/em&gt; it won’t, in a sense. But yet it terrifies me. I felt this fear about returning to writing a lot regularly too — still feel it a little, in fact — and although my fear was proven unfounded, somehow it is springing up again anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fear is tied to something else that’s been happening lately that scares me, even though it isn’t related to going back to college: what I’ve been calling “Man Moments.” Moments when I actually like how I look as a man, conceptualizing myself as one, etc. They’re not predicated on my masculinity, exactly, and they’re much rarer than the days when I have dysphoria over being a man, but it’s still strange and a little concerning, and I worry that this might be a sign that I’m not really a girl, or shouldn’t transition, or something, even though I really want to be a girl and transition. In fact, just yesterday, I got so excited at the idea that I might have breast buds soon from HRT that I got giddy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagining hypotheticals really isn’t helping here either. At this point I’ve pretty much spent all the time that is useful laying back and trying to picture what it’ll be like post-transition, and because it’s not real and I’ve trod that mental path so many times, my brain is kind of numb to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. No conclusion, nothin. I just needed to vent a little.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis Purslane Dumas</name></author><summary type="html">1</summary></entry></feed>