<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-21T13:01:14-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Luciferian Loquations</title><subtitle>Unscripted speech, premeditated thought.</subtitle><author><name>Alexis</name></author><entry><title type="html">What Is Individualist Anarchism?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/17/what-is-individualist-anarchism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Is Individualist Anarchism?" /><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/17/what-is-individualist-anarchism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/17/what-is-individualist-anarchism.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Infernal world! and thou, profoundest Hell,&lt;br /&gt;
Receive thy new possessor—one who brings&lt;br /&gt;
A mind not to be changed by place or time.&lt;br /&gt;
The mind is its own place, and in itself&lt;br /&gt;
Can make a Heaven of Hell, a Hell of Heaven.&lt;br /&gt;
What matter where, if I be still the same,&lt;br /&gt;
And what I should be, all but less than he&lt;br /&gt;
Whom thunder hath made greater? Here at least&lt;br /&gt;
We shall be free; th’ Almighty hath not built&lt;br /&gt;
Here for his envy, will not drive us hence:&lt;br /&gt;
Here we may reign secure; and, in my choice,&lt;br /&gt;
To reign is worth ambition, though in Hell:&lt;br /&gt;
Better to reign in Hell than serve in Heaven.”&lt;br /&gt;
— &lt;em&gt;Paradise Lost&lt;/em&gt;, by John Milton, Book I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualist anarchism is, at its core, very simple. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists seek individual autonomy above all else.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; We seek our own first of all, but we know that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;our own autonomy can never truly be secure or complete until the autonomy of all is equally respected&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;; furthermore, we are empathetic human beings who want to see others free and flourishing too. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;We seek to eliminate subjugation, domination, authority, and hierarchy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; wherever it can be found&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — be that from the collective, the capitalist, the politician, the bureaucrat, or the priest — so that each person is free to live their own life how they choose, according to their own reason, pursuing their own happiness, and solving their conflicts and problems directly with those involved according to the norms that work best for their particular situation. Autonomy here stands for a rich tapestry of things, not just the empty and farcical notions of freedom foisted by political propaganda upon the common citizen: it stands for negative liberty, the freedom from &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; obstacles, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the primacy of one’s own will and self-determination&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, but it also stands for the ability to choose how one’s labor time is spent and what happens to the products of that labor, to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;control the things important to one’s life and destiny&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; like the means of production one uses and the roof over one’s head, and independence from the wills and whims of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the absolute autonomy of one person can be detrimental to the autonomy of another, so in the sphere of life where one’s actions necessarily collide with others, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the individualist anarchist seeks relations between people that are founded on reciprocity, on mutual benefit, on even footing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — relations free from the dynamics of power and authority which permeate our world. Therefore the only restrictions on the autonomy of each individual must be against actions that would extend their autonomy in ways that require the domination of others, or treat the interests of others as anything but equal to their own. Likewise, although individualist anarchists may occasionally use democratic forms in order to balance the interests of those directly involved in a situation that might otherwise give rise to conflict, we totally reject the myth of democracy, that a larger group of people have the right to subjugate and control a smaller group of people merely on the basis of being a larger group. The individual will, the autonomy of each of us, is to be absolute within its boundaries. To safeguard this, the maximum decentralization and distribution of power to everyone, the splitting up of control to those directly involved in the relevant situation, and pure equality in that: if we are all equal, none may dominate another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists, furthermore, recognize that rights are protected by the reciprocally gifted respect of the community one lives in&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: each person freely and willingly recognizes and respects the autonomy of others with the expectation that the those others will in turn respect their own autonomy. Therefore, if any one does not have much autonomy to speak of — if someone is starving, homeless, has nowhere to work — or if the community is not respecting their autonomy, or supporting through inaction their subjugation at the hands of others, then they have no incentive to respect the autonomy of others and should not be expected to. In essence, then, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the rights of all are forfeit to the direct action of the marginalized and oppressed until such a time as all are provided with what they need for autonomy and respected&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This also works on an individual basis: if someone refuses to respect your autonomy, why respect theirs? They will not respond in goodwill, will not reciprocate your gift of respect. This means that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;to be truly free and autonomous ourselves, it is necessary to lift up, respect, and protect the autonomy of others, through mutual aid and solidarity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; To create a society where everyone’s autonomy is safeguarded, we must all contribute to safeguarding the autonomy of others: providing them with whatever they need, from houses to food to education. Of course, this should not turn into a relationship of domination of others by the needy, not a welfare system or a state, each individual must care for themselves first, but &lt;em&gt;in and through&lt;/em&gt; caring for themselves they must also care for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualist anarchists seek to eliminate property. True to our principles, we believe that those who use something, those for whom something is a direct extension of their autonomy, their ability to control their own destiny and act freely, should own that thing. To prevent someone from using something they regularly use is to restrict their freedom, but to use something that no one else is using, or in such a way as to let the others who use it continue to use it, is not restricting anyone’s freedom. Likewise, to use something that someone will never use is not a restriction of their freedom just because it is theoretically preventing them from taking an action they have never and likely will never take. For instance, walking takes up space on the sidewalk that someone else could &lt;em&gt;theoretically&lt;/em&gt; have used otherwise, but since no one is actually trying to do that, so no one is being bumped out of the way, it restricts no one’s freedom.  Thus &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;we seek to replace absentee property, where people who actually use something are dispossessed in favor of those who will never use it, with the possession of things by the people who occupy or use them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This is the correct principle for those who are committed to autonomy: those whose autonomy is bound up in something have a right not to be dispossessed of it, thrown off the means of their livelihood, and those who have nothing to do with a thing have no say in what is done with it, cannot extend their autonomy by asserting their control over others. The person that lives in a house should own it, not some absentee landlord, the worker who uses a machine should own it, not some capitalist, and so on. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists also believe that the just wage of labor is its product&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: everyone should be able to control the product of their own labor time, because otherwise they are just a slave to someone else; hence, the worker must justly own the product they produce, not have it taken away by the capitalist or the collective. However, if someone produces something, but refuses to use it or sell it, and instead tries to extract economic rent or profit from it, then they are extending their autonomy by asserting their authority over others. They have broken the single “law” which a community of anarchists must recognize: that any autonomy gained by the domination and subjugation of others is illegitimate, that any autonomy gained by the restriction of the autonomy of others (when that autonomy itself is not coercive), is not to be tolerated. They have thrown the gift of respect for their autonomy that others have granted them, in letting them determine the fate of the products of their labor, back in the face of everyone by using that gift of autonomy to restrict the autonomy of the very people that gave them that gift, and have therefore forfeited their right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists seek to eliminate capitalism and property, but we do not seek to bring about communism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Individualist anarchists view communism as just as antithetical to our individualist, autonomy-focused, anti-authoritarian credo as capitalism is. In the first place, giving control of the means of production to the collective subjugates each individual worker to an absentee collective which can be just as domineering as the capitalist was. It makes individuals not able to separate themselves from the will of others, leaving them with no shield for their individuality and no other option but to be subsumed. In the second place, not allowing the worker to decide what to do with the product of their labor, including selling it, or letting others take the product of their labor without permission when they are not using it to dominate anyone else, is domination just as bad as, and in fact quite similar to, capitalism itself. In the third place, placing everyone under the authority of the democratic majority is still subjugating people to the wills of others, just the will of many others instead of the will of a few, and if the will of the majority is made absolute in economic matters, it will not be long until it is made absolute in other matters as well, since then one’s individual autonomy only exists at the sufferance of the majority, and if the majority can hold one’s means of sustenance and livelihood hostage (since the economic sphere is just that) then they can use that as leverage to control everything else. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Therefore, instead of eliminating markets, individualist anarchists seek to bring about socialist ends through market means&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: markets where workers own the means of production, where everyone is as independent as possible, where the economy is as decentralized and localized as possible, and where federations of worker cooperatives&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are the main form of organization for when some centralization or organization of production is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individualist anarchists think this reformation of markets away from capitalism is possible because we do not believe that free markets are synonymous with capitalism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — in fact, we think that the equation of capitalism and markets is the single greatest tragedy in the history of the language of politics, for it gives both Marxists and capitalists free reign to assume their conclusions. For capitalists, since markets are free and just, capitalism must be too, and for Marxists, since capitalism is oppressive and exploitative, markets must be abolished. This is not the case. There have been markets before capitalism, and there will be markets after capitalism. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What creates capitalism is the state enforcement of the absentee property claims of intellectual property, landlords, lenders, and capitalists, not the presence of people producing things and selling the products of their labor to others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is only when the state sends its jackbooted thugs to protect the claims of those who do not produce that markets become exploitative.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; If one could only sell the products of one’s labor, and one forfeited one’s claim on anything as soon as one or tried to use access to it as leverage to gain power over others and extract rent for idleness, the world would look very different than it is. There would not be millions of homes sitting empty as investment vehicles for the wealthy, or waiting for an exploitatively high rent, while there were thousands of homeless people walking the streets just outside, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this society, all that is ultimately necessary is for individuals to recognize that there is no justification, and can be no justification, for any authority — whether moral, political, or any other sort — above their own mind and will. All power structures ultimately rest on the widespread belief in their legitimacy, the servile and obedient perpetuation and reproduction in the small of them by people, so all that is needed for them to crumble is for us to reject the mythology and superstitions inculcated in us by society since birth, to choose not to legitimize or protect those institutions, and to spread that rejection to others through uncompromising commitment to our values and our own reason. Where else does the state, or the capitalist, get their power, but from the cooperation of the masses that vastly outnumber them and any servants they could hire? The difference between the strength of one human being and another is not enough to allow one corporate fat cat, or one slimy politician, to hold off millions of us. There will be battles, in the end, the last violent death-thrashings of an angry and defeated Leviathan, but when once legitimacy is lost in the hearts and minds of the people, the tide is turned, the battle is half-way won! We have seen this in the past, in the tidal shifts of legitimacy that overthrew or chained the old monarchies — why could it not happen again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus those who truly value a world without authority, a world of individual autonomy and self-determination, must dedicate themselves to the education and liberation of those who are currently possessed by the phantoms that haunt our cultural consciousness; and while we wait, and the movement slowly grows, why not also dedicate ourselves to building something that will be ready when the Leviathan falls? Something to provide the structures and institutions a new, free society needs? Something which, while waiting in the interstices, can lighten the load for those who must live in the current era, provide something real, practical, and compassionate in the here-and-now for those who suffer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not hierarchy in the broad sense, of an inequality or ranking between people, but in the specific sense of a hierarchy that gives some control over others or leads people to treat someone as worth more than someone else in a way that leads to oppression. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is what the BLM riots were, in essence: retaliation against an oppressive system by those whose autonomy means little, if anything, to that system, because at that point, they have little to lose and everything to gain, and they needed to be heard. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Worker cooperates do not represent as much of a form of domination over the individual as the whole of society democratically determining what is to be done with all the means of production, because each worker is only influenced by the vote of others concerning the uses of the means of production to ensure that that worker does not usurp something other people are using — i.e. it is a balancing of the autonomy represented by the use of some capital between all those who actually use it, a way of &lt;em&gt;preventing&lt;/em&gt; one person’s exclusive and unilateral use of something to the detriment of others, instead of merely an assertion of the control of others in matters they would otherwise be uneffected by over the autonomy of those who actually use something. It is the difference between balancing the overlapping autonomy of each person equally, so that no one can expand their autonomy by hurting another’s, versus the expansion of autonomy directly and inherently through domination of others in matters that would otherwise not need to represent those interests at all. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><category term="anarchism" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="politics" /><category term="mutualism" /><summary type="html">“Infernal world! and thou, profoundest Hell, Receive thy new possessor—one who brings A mind not to be changed by place or time. The mind is its own place, and in itself Can make a Heaven of Hell, a Hell of Heaven. What matter where, if I be still the same, And what I should be, all but less than he Whom thunder hath made greater? Here at least We shall be free; th’ Almighty hath not built Here for his envy, will not drive us hence: Here we may reign secure; and, in my choice, To reign is worth ambition, though in Hell: Better to reign in Hell than serve in Heaven.” — Paradise Lost, by John Milton, Book I</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abortion and Individualist Anarchism: Why Pro-Choice Is The Only Choice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/abortion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abortion and Individualist Anarchism: Why Pro-Choice Is The Only Choice" /><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/abortion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/abortion.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I first began my journey towards anarchism, my views on abortion have been in a constant state of flux — multiple conflicting intuitions and considerations all pulling my values in different directions, while the prevailing winds of my evolving moral system changed which were foremost in my mind. Usually, with things like this, it is important to open a dialogue about it with others, in order to gain new perspectives and refine one’s understanding, but due to the understandably controversial nature of the topic, I’ve found it difficult to openly discuss it with people. I’ve even found it difficult to begin writing on the topic, so unlike most of my other ethical views, I don’t have a significant corpus of essays on it documenting the development of my views. I think, however, that my ideas on the topic have finally become mature enough, and nuanced enough, that it is time to write them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this essay is primarily to do what I did in my essay on anarchistic relations: to explore all the nuances and complexities of a topic, letting my reasoning take me where it will, in order to clarify for myself, through solidification, my own thoughts. Please bear in mind, then, that this is an exploratory essay, and as such won’t be as clearly structured as my moral formal ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first consideration when we bring up the topic of abortions is our general moral foundations. After all, if we don’t understand those clearly, then it is difficult to derive conclusions about what should or should not be done with any clarity. In my own case, my moral foundations are fundamentally individualistic, anti-authoritarian, and subjectivist — I am only beholden to my own individual desires regarding what I want to see in my own life and in the society around me, my primary concern is for individual autonomy, and my primary opposition is to authority. In light of that, this essay will not be an exploration of what others &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; do regarding abortion — instead it will be an exploration of my own values and how they might require me to act towards others, as well as an attempt to reach reflective equilibrium regarding these two things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a moral subjectivist, you might assume that my response to abortion would be simple: “I have no right to dictate the reproductive health choices of anyone besides myself.” That’s not really the case, however: a moral subjectivist does not believe in ‘rights,’ and does not commit themselves to moral relativism by giving up moral realism, since relativism insists on a commitment to a moral rule (non-interference with others) that is &lt;em&gt;non-relative&lt;/em&gt; to subjective desires and therefore a phantom at best. Therefore, if, according to my values, something is of an abhorrent and undesirable nature — such as oppression, authority, hierarchy, coercion, etc — then it is perfectly acceptable for me to take steps to prevent it, and rally others in doing so as well. This is something no anarchist (except pacifists perhaps) has ever been against, no matter how subjectivist they are. Otherwise they’d cease to be anarchists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although I am not inherently opposed to interfering with others for my moral values, I begin with a presumption of &lt;strong&gt;non-interference&lt;/strong&gt;. This for several reasons. First, because by default interfering with the choices of others is a reduction of autonomy, unless you can prove that that exercise of autonomy was actually resulting in the subordination of someone else. Second, because interfering with the choices of others necessarily brings about conflict, and conflict is costly and dangerous, and so best avoided when possible, since enforcing one’s values is not inherently right or just (as a moral realist would think) but instead just another good to be weighed and measured against one’s other interests. Finally, encouraging a presumption in favor of non-interference produces a society that is less infested with moral busybodies, since people can’t always be trusted to have minimalist moral values that would lead to a live and let live attitude even in the absence of such a presumption. For all these reasons, then, just as the defendant in a court of law is presumed to be innocent until the contrary is proven, so in my own reasoning I prefer to assume a peaceful live-and-let-live attitude until the weight of axiological considerations forces me to overturn that. Therefore, the crucial question is whether my values would imply that abortion is of a terrible enough nature that it would become important enough to me to prevent a society that allows them to overcome my presumption in favor of peace and non-interference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most compelling reason that one could be against abortions is on the basis of a sort of restitution argument. If one values attempting to restore the victims of a coercive or harmful action to the state of happiness and peace that they were in before someone hurt them, then one automatically has to believe that, under some conditions, individual autonomy must take a back-seat to considerations of fairness. I happen to be of the opinion that, generally speaking, not only is restitution a very good way to solve conflicts and maintain peace and general individual autonomy in society, it is also something that I value inherently for its own sake, being an outgrowth of an attempt to deal fairly and empathetically with people. I value this in the same way I value compassion, charity, artistic skill, and other things that are not strictly implied by a purely game theoretic egoist framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the argument would have to proceed like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some activities have a risk of hurting others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If such an activity is voluntarily undertaken, knowing the risk, and someone &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; get hurt, then the person who did it has voluntarily harmed someone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being put in a position of dependency without one’s consent is a form of harm. (For instance, throwing someone who can’t swim into a pool without their consent.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone voluntarily harms someone else, it is unfair to not at least attempt to restore them in some way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sex has a risk of creating a fetus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When a fetus is created, it is dependent for its life on someone else maintaining it, and it could not have consented to this. Therefore a fetus is harmed by being created.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone voluntarily engages in sex, and that results in pregnancy, then it would be unfair to the fetus to abort it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since it is unfair, abortions should not be allowed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is by far the best argument against abortion that there is. All of the other one’s I’ve seen are just various levels of hypocrisy, moral panic, or attempts to control the bodies of people with uteruses for the purpose of perpetuating the patriarchy. I think it is interesting to note, therefore, that this argument is actually rarely used by anyone — indicating that most of the discourse around abortion isn’t really borne out of genuine moral concern on the basis of principles that value freedom and liberty, but instead is the authoritarian drivel of reactionaries. Nevertheless, even though the “pro-life” position is tainted badly by its proponents, this argument still deserves a serious response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should further be noted that this argument has far weaker conclusions than your average pro-life argument. For one thing, if carrying the fetus to term presents a serious risk to the mother’s life, it seems completely disproportionate to require her to die to make restitution to the fetus, just like you shouldn’t be required to give your life just to help someone you get into a car crash with (even if you might be seen as more heroic for doing so). For another, if the sex wasn’t voluntary (such as in the case of rape), then this whole argument breaks down, because if someone else forces you to hurt a third person, then you’re not responsible for that. Additionally, if the fetus won’t be viable, there really isn’t any point to not aborting it, since there’s no way to give it restitution for the harm done to it in any case. There are probably many more exceptions like this that even the most mild “pro-life” advocate will generally have a hard time actually admitting to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of assumptions in this argument. In order to break down why it doesn’t work, those assumptions will need to be examined and refuted in detail, but first, let me list them out. Most importantly, the argument assumes that fairness towards people is a value that is worth abridging the autonomy of others with force to preserve. Additionally, the argument assumes that a fetus is a person in the same sense that a regular human being is. On top of that, it assumes that their are either no limits to what one should have to do to give restitution, or that forced pregnancy and birth falls under those limits. Next, it assumes that doing something to someone without their consent applies in a case where the “person” in question didn’t exist prior to the action that took place. To cap it off, it assumes that creating something in a dependent state is equivalent to transitioning someone from an independent, autonomous state to a dependent one. Each of these assumptions will be examined in the following sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is fairness a value that is worth abridging the autonomy of others to preserve? This might seem like a difficult question at first, until you remember that, to a certain degree, the concept of fairness, or at least the balancing of interests, is &lt;em&gt;baked into&lt;/em&gt; the concept of autonomy and proper &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/12/19/relations.html&quot;&gt;anarchistic relations&lt;/a&gt;. To prevent someone from unilaterally subordinating another to their will, taking away their ability to pursue their own interests and make their own choices, all interests in an interaction must be considered equally. This is the sense of fairness which obviously should be supported through force to a certain degree. Outside of that, other conceptions of fairness are much weaker, which is why disambiguating the strong form of autonomy-supporting fairness, and the rest of the applications of the term, is so important. These other meanings include asking for a too-high price for something, cheating at a game, being a hypocrite, not keeping a promise, etc. All of these things are unfair and might make you an asshole, but none of them seem important enough to me to warrant enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the question becomes: is the &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of fairness spoke about in the anti-abortion argument the strong kind of fairness, or the weak kind? I believe that it is of the weak kind, for this reason: the interaction that involved the harm has already taken place, and is not being repeated. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; interaction is the one in which the interests were imbalanced, and which should have been prevented if possible, but that’s in the past now and there isn’t anything anyone can do about it. You can show your remorse, empathy, and sense of compassion by doing something in the present to help, but since the actually strongly unfair interaction is not ongoing, force isn’t proportionate. It’s a lot like a contract in that sense: if you make a contract, if you break it then you should avoid perpetuating subordinatory relationships, such as holding on to the possessions the other person only gave you conditionally, but once those relations are over, there isn’t any hold on you besides just social norms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore it seems pretty clear to me that abortion does not actually violate the kind of fairness that it is worth breaking the presumption of non-interference to enforce. This knocks out the conclusion of the argument directly, and should make the whole point moot. There are, however, many more flaws with this argument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next problem with this argument is that it assumes that a fetus is a full person with full personhood. This is perhaps a reasonable concession to make in order to respond to some “pro-life” arguments, as Judith Jarvis Thomson did in ‘A Defense of Abortion,’ but aside from that there is no reason to grant such a concession. What makes something a morally significant entity, a &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt;, is the capacity to have desires, make choices motivated by reasoning processes (however faulty), have internal experiences and consciousness, handle abstract thinking and reasoning, and communicate these things. It does not have to be &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; those things, but it has to be capable of doing them or learning to do so. Like gender identity and other things of a sociological or psychological nature, personhood is a spectrum and there are many factors that contribute to it, but I think the absurdity of according a fetus the status of personhood is pretty clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fetus is a clump of human cells, with different DNA from its host, yes, but you can produce a clump of human cells, with different DNA from any other human, quite easily. It’s been done to make a pong-playing AI, in fact, and no one seemed to have an issue with that. And that’s a tiny &lt;em&gt;brain&lt;/em&gt; that processes inputs and responds to them in a semi-intelligent manner, made of human cells! A fetus doesn’t even have a brain like that until well into its development. A fetus doesn’t even have the capacity to feel, let alone feel pain, until after twenty weeks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A human fetus does not have the capacity to experience pain until  after viability. Rigorous scientific studies have found that the  connections necessary to transmit signals from peripheral sensory nerves to the brain, as well as the brain structures necessary to process  those signals, do not develop until at least 24 weeks of gestation. Because it lacks these connections and structures, the fetus does not  even have the physiological capacity to perceive pain until at least 24  weeks of gestation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In fact, the perception of pain requires more than just the  mechanical transmission and reception of signals. Pain is “an emotional  and psychological experience that requires conscious recognition of a  noxious stimulus.”ii This capacity does not develop until the third trimester at the earliest, well past the period between 20 weeks  and viability. The evidence shows that the neural circuitry necessary to distinguish touch from painful touch does not, in fact, develop until  late in the third trimester. The occurrence of intrauterine fetal  movement is not an indication that a fetus can feel pain.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fetuses are vaguely human-shaped clumps of cells, nothing more. Just as we could  theoretically sequence a new human genome and grow an entire, fully grown human body without a brain, and we wouldn’t call that a human person worthy of moral consideration, and just as we couldn’t consider a brain dead person as a person either, neither should we consider a fetus a human person until it’s brain has developed sufficiently to allow for self-awareness, which usually only occurs at 15 to 24 months after the fetus has been born. In fact, until they are viable on their own apart from the mother, it’s not even clear to me that they should be categorized as a separate organism, and they certainly don’t have any autonomy worthy of consideration, since they are essentially completely dependent on the host for sustained life in a physical, biological manner — i.e. they are parasites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One counterargument might be that a fetus is a &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; person, and that if you just “leave it alone” it would become a person, so by preventing its development, you are in effect killing it. This is absurd, of course. Preventing the existence of something is not destroying it, just as preventing me from building a model kit is not destroying my model after it is built. Moreover, fetuses aren’t plants. They don’t just “grow” on their own. Instead they require constant use of the mother’s body, because they are parasites. Thus it isn’t really the case that you are preventing something from happening that would happen without your interference; when you get an abortion you are stopping a process that is actively and already using your body to get something done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse than that, by putting forward this argument, or in fact any argument against abortion that has to do with the ‘rights’ of the fetus, the person putting forward the argument is raising the questionable rights of something that is only arguably a person, and in fact probably isn’t, over the rights of a real, live, adult human being who we know &lt;em&gt;for a fact&lt;/em&gt; is a person. This is absolutely epistemically irresponsible, especially considering the stakes of the case: on the basis of flimsy definitions of humanity, we are taking away the very real bodily autonomy of people, controlling their bodies and their lives, and perpetuating a system of power and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next assumption that this argument makes is that there is either no limit to what someone can be expected to give in restitution to attempt to make their ‘victim’ whole, or that requiring forced pregnancy and birth falls below that limit. Neither of those assumptions makes any sense whatsoever, and since the second one depends on the failure of the first, I’ll cover them one at a time, in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with — is there a limit to the restitution required by fairness? To this, I answer a resounding yes. Besides not requiring someone to give restitution in a way that causes their death — because no one can be expected to give up their lives under any circumstances — I think it seems pretty clear that if the cost of giving restitution is a severe loss of autonomy, a severe detriment to someone’s interests, or a severe setback in their lives, then they should not be required to do it. It’s just too onerous for a value like that. It would be absurd, for instance, to require someone who cheated at a poker game and spent all the money he got on food that he ate, or something else perishable, to work for the next twenty years or however long for another person as an indentured servant just to be “fair.” The upper limit of what can be “required” in fair restitution is proportional to, not the severity of the unfairness, but the severity of the action that was taken to cause the unfairness, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying this framework to pregnancy and abortion, what the people who produced the fetus actually did “to” the fetus itself wasn’t that terrible (although it’s hard to get an exact measurement), whereas having to hold something growing inside you, like some kind of body horror monster, for nine months, at risk to your health and your life, while enduring all kinds of sickness and cramps, and setting back whatever else you wanted to do with your life, and then requiring that person to give birth, which is extremely painful and difficult, is absolutely awful in comparison. The two are simply completely out of balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me bring up an example. Let’s talk about contracts again. Should someone be held to the performance of a contract, or the repayment of a debt by force? It depends on what it costs them to repay it. If it’s just a simple matter of transferring property? Sure. If it involves control over someone’s body and time, forcing them to perform actions or bear things that they don’t want to do? No, that’s horrible! If I contract with someone to, say, take a kidney, I should have the right to rescind my consent to the operation at any time. Same if I make a contract to have sex with someone. Need is only a slightly greater pull here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is the question of whether &lt;em&gt;creating something&lt;/em&gt; can be said to be something that is done without that thing’s consent at all. This is a point that a number of people have brought up to me regarding the anti-abortion argument given above. In essence, the counter argument is that if something didn’t exist at all, then there was not even a conceivable possibility or capacity for consent, and if you take an ought-implies-can Kantian approach, that means you weren’t obligated to try to get consent anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I’m not particularly convinced by this argument. I’m actually pretty convinced that bringing something into existence is, actually, a non-consensual act. I mean, it actually kind of makes sense when someone says, for instance, “I didn’t ask to be born,” and I think that’s telling. Nevertheless, the fact that this is ambiguous further undermines the strength of this argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another objection to the anti-abortion argument is that it rests on a fundamental, hidden equivocation. In the first half of the argument, it is established that doing something to someone, without their consent, that takes away their autonomy, making them dependent on you for help, is a form of harm. In the second part of the argument, I treat this as equivalent to creating something that never had autonomy or independence, in the position of being dependent. These two things seem pretty clearly different to me, however, and I think the second version borrows its strength from conflation with the first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of the intuition in favor of restitution and fairness stems in response to this harm comes from the transition from independent, autonomous agent to dependent one: that is where the harm occurs, since that is where one person’s autonomy was disrespected and their independence lost. An existing person’s interests were ignored, something was unilaterally done to them, and it removed the one thing that is universally and always valuable to an egoist from them. This is specifically where the harm occurs, and because of that, it brings the autonomy- and agency-related &lt;strong&gt;strong&lt;/strong&gt; fairness into the mix, which is what allows it to possibly override considerations of autonomy overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the case of the fetus, there was nothing that existed and was autonomous before it was created or at the moment of creation. Nothing’s autonomy was disrespected, nothings independence was robbed from it. It had no autonomy because it was dead (did not exist), and then it did exist and &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; had no autonomy. Therefore, &lt;em&gt;at best&lt;/em&gt;, the only conception of fairness in play is the weak one. If anything, in a sense, by giving birth to the fetus you &lt;em&gt;gave&lt;/em&gt; it something it did not have before. You cannot be held responsible for taking something away from someone when they never had it to begin with, no matter what state changes you do inflict on them. By aborting a fetus you may be preventing it from gaining something, but you are not keeping something back that you took from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;9&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, ultimately, it comes down to this: bodily autonomy, and individual autonomy in general, is the most important thing to me. That is what I care about the most. I also think that choosing to put other things other than autonomy on the top of one’s value hierarchy is a very quick way to produce negative and undesirable outcomes for almost any value hierarchy, if followed through consistently. Therefore, as an anarchist with a commitment to autonomy first, I am in favor of abortion. I recently found a quote that I like on this topic, so let me wrap up with it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The “unborn” are a convenient group of people to advocate for. They never make demands of you; they are morally uncomplicated, unlike the incarcerated, addicted, or the chronically poor; they don’t resent your condescension or complain that you are not politically correct; unlike widows, they don’t ask you to question patriarchy; unlike orphans, they don’t need money, education, or childcare; unlike aliens, they don’t bring all that racial, cultural, and religious baggage that you dislike; they allow you to feel good about yourself without any work at creating or maintaining relationships; and when they are born, you can forget about them, because they cease to be unborn. You can love the unborn and advocate for them without substantially challenging your own wealth, power, or privilege, without re-imagining social structures, apologizing, or making reparations to anyone… — Methodist Pastor David Barnhart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acog.org/advocacy/facts-are-important/fetal-pain&quot;&gt;https://www.acog.org/advocacy/facts-are-important/fetal-pain&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><category term="ethics" /><category term="politics" /><category term="feminism" /><category term="anarchism" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Introduction to Fuzzy Pragmatist Bayesian Epistemology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/fuzzy-logic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Introduction to Fuzzy Pragmatist Bayesian Epistemology" /><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/fuzzy-logic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/fuzzy-logic.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-introduction&quot;&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of pragmatist epistemology is not to arrive at absolute truth, at certain knowledge about the universe, or any of the other goals which have occupied philosophers across the millennia. It has a more humble goal: to help human beings achieve our goals in a world that does not bend to our every whim, a world that is more than happy to slap us in the face with our misconceptions and preconceived notions at every turn. It offers a way to adapt to the world, to move with the current instead of against it, by providing a toolkit for predicting future experiences — the outcomes of our actions, the changes in the world around us — based on the only information we have available to us: past experiences. Human beings are thrust into a world that effects us on a deep and intimate level, one which we can only close our eyes to by committing suicide; therefore we have a choice: death, or learning. Choose to shut the world out permanently, or learn how to operate within it. We cannot know whether we are a brain in a vat, or being deceived by a demon, or NPCs in a cosmic simulation run by higher beings. But until someone offers us the red pill — a way to leave the simulation, if it is one — this world is as real to us as it gets, as real as any other. We have no choice but to face it, to live in it, and to try to live in it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are therefore three core insights which form the foundations of pragmatist epistemology. First, that I experience things, and these experiences effect me. Second, that something which is not a product of my desires or beliefs, but which can influence these things, is what produces my experiences. Third, that I only have my connection, through my experiences past and present, to this external thing. The implications of these axioms form my epistemology, and in this essay I will lay out these implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-definitions&quot;&gt;2. Definitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, we must lay out some definitions. First among them is the definition of “&lt;strong&gt;truth&lt;/strong&gt;.” What, in the pragmatist framework, does it mean for a proposition to be true? Considering that the goal of pragmatist epistemology is to arrive at propositions that help us navigate our world, it seems clear that the goal should be propositions that answer questions about future experiences, since these kinds of questions — what will happen when I push this? what will I see when I turn the next corner? when will winter arrive? — are the most helpful in understanding how to live and act. If the goal is predictive propositions, then the fullest satisfaction of that goal would be propositions that are &lt;em&gt;perfectly&lt;/em&gt; predictive — i.e. propositions that predict the next experiences of any agent under any circumstance relevant to the subject of the proposition, past, present, future, in any place, for anyone, at any time. Since the definition of truth is relative to the goal of epistemic framework one is operating within, the definition of truth in my framework is just such a perfectly predictive proposition. Thus, a proposition is true if it predicts the experiences of any agent, at any time, in any place, regarding the subject of the proposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be &lt;strong&gt;truth-apt&lt;/strong&gt;, therefore, a proposition must be one that can be used to predict experiences with regard to the subject of said proposition. Otherwise, within this framework, there is not really any sense in which the proposition can be counted to be true to some degree, or false to some degree. It is important to note that since the range over which a proposition’s predictiveness can vary, and the accuracy of its predictions can also vary, truth in this framework is a spectrum. The ultimate, ideal goal, as described above, is 100% predictiveness in both detail and scope; propositions can actually be closer to or farther away from this goal as their accuracy and scope differ. Truth is a spectrum, and it varies across several variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the truth of a proposition depends on whether it accurately predicts the experiences that agents could have with regards to its subject, &lt;strong&gt;meaningful&lt;/strong&gt;  propositions must always ultimately be about experiences of some kind, about &lt;em&gt;interactions&lt;/em&gt; with an object. The meaningfulness of any proposition is dependent on its capacity to effect the experiences of some agent. To clarify, it is not relative to its actual effect on any existing agent, because that would mean statements about things that no one can yet check, but could conceivably be checked in the future, would be meaningless; instead the truth of a proposition is relative to its possible effects on any &lt;em&gt;conceivable&lt;/em&gt; agent: thus if someone &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; check concerning whether a proposition accurately describes a certain experience or not, then the proposition is meaningful. Conversely, if no one could &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; check whether a proposition accurately describes some experience concerning its subject, then the proposition is meaningless, useless, and empty nonsense. Note that meaningfulness is not identical with truth-aptness. This is because some statements are definitions and other &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; true statements, which simply assign names to certain experiences or derive conceptual conclusions from them. They need to be about experience in some sense in order to be meaningful because without that then they couldn’t really be used to come to true or false conclusions, wouldn’t really be “about” anything that is really relevant to human life, but they don’t need to make statements about some actual experience in such a way that they could be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is such a thing as “&lt;strong&gt;referred&lt;/strong&gt;” meaning or truth-aptness, too. A proposition that is not directly about an experience can be meaningful as it relates to some conceptual apparatus that ultimately says something about experience, even though without it it would be pointless and useless. Likewise, a proposition could be true to the degree that the system of propositions (that it is derived from or that are in part derived from it) can lead to true propositions in the final conclusion. An example of this last type of thing is clearly to be found in physics. In physics, the givens of a problem are “true,” in that they describe experiences of a thing, and the results of the physics problem are also (hopefully) true, in that they predict future experiences based on those givens. But the intermediate steps of the mathematics aren’t really “true” in any real sense, apart from what they imply about the starting point and ending point. Oftentimes, if you try to translate what the intermediate algebra steps in a physics problem “mean” by applying the standard definitions of the variables, as you use them at the beginning and end, you’ll get nonsensical and often clearly counterfactual claims about reality. This is why when people doing theoretical physics try to derive claims about how reality works from the mathematics they are using to describe that reality, one should accord their claims only a portion of the credence you accord to their predictions overall. It might be the case that their theories are predictive because, when investigated, the intermediate steps of the mathematical process are propositions that accurately describe how the intermediate steps of the physical process look when we check, but it could almost equally be the case that this is not so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point one might be worrying that this is verging too closely to the picture theory of language put forward by Wittgenstein in the &lt;em&gt;Tractatus&lt;/em&gt;, and that therefore these definitions might fall afoul of the same problem that his did, in rendering the very philosophical text that put them forward ultimately meaningless. This is not the case, however. I have been very careful to state that propositions are about experiences, but not that these experiences necessarily must be about the outside world external to our consciousness. Therefore, psychological propositions and others that speak about our own internal experiences of existence are just as truth-apt as ones that speak about our experiences of the world, although they are much more difficult to demonstrate to others. Thus when I talk about how to use pragmatist epistemology later in this essay, and discuss how to arrive at propositions that are more true or less false, this is still a statement about experience, because I am describing how some methods will produce the experience of expected outcomes more often than the experience of unexpected ones. And the definitions I gave above are derived from propositions about experience from the first section, and will influence propositions about experience later, and are, furthermore, in themselves, propositions about experience in a sense, as the definition of truth for instance has itself to do with experiences of expected or unexpected outcomes. Although they don’t &lt;em&gt;predict&lt;/em&gt; things and are therefore not truth-apt, definitions are still about experiences, in that they put labels on them, and so they are still meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another point needs to be made as well. It can actually sometimes be rational for someone to stop refining and improving a theory before it reaches 100% truth (according to the definition just given),  interestingly, because a theory doesn’t have to be predictive in every conceivable situation to be predictive &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; for the purposes of an individual. This can be because it is predictive in all the situations an individual is likely to find themselves in, so the possibility of running into a situation where it doesn’t work doesn’t outweigh the extra effort of improving it, or because it is not perfectly predictive but is right often enough that the accidents caused by being wrong are not enough to outweigh the extra effort in learning more, or because the penalties for being wrong are negligible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One needs to be careful with choosing to stop truth-seeking in a particular area, though, because it can be very difficult to predict when one will come face to face with an area where one’s beliefs don’t hold true, since that would require predicting unknown unknowns, which is basically definitionally impossible. Therefore, to decide whether to continue investigating something or not, one needs to consider the magnitude and probability of harm occurring if what one thinks is true on the basis of the evidence one has so far turns out to be false. This is called &lt;strong&gt;falsity risk.&lt;/strong&gt; If the risk of something one believes turning out to be false is low, there may be no need to investigate it further; but if it is high, than a continual re-evaluation of the theory in terms of new data, and a continual process of trying to acquire new data, is the best course of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, there is a sort of reverse falsity risk as well: some of the unknown unknowns you have to deal with are possible positive results that you are missing out on by not known the full truth or not improving your theory. These chances, too, need to be factored in when choosing to either let a theory rest or keep examining it — in cases where no other courses of action concerning a subject are open to you anyway, for instance, positive and negative falsity risk are pretty much neutralized, since knowing more won’t help anyway. Thus, to borrow a term from game theory, while there &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be such a thing as “rational ignorance,” it is probably not as common as people take it to be, since leaving off the further pursuit of truth in many cases is a very risky business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next sections, I will defend the individual elements of my analysis. Once that is complete, I will assemble them into a form of fuzzy Bayesian induction, and a procedure for setting the priors of that Bayesian form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-the-principle-of-phenomenological-conservatism&quot;&gt;3. The Principle of Phenomenological Conservatism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle element of my approach to pragmatist epistemology, which is assumed — although not explicitly restated and used — throughout the rest of this essay, is (a weak version of) the &lt;strong&gt;principle of phenomenological conservatism&lt;/strong&gt;. This principle is a formalization of the implicit motivations behind my entire philosophy of epistemology, as stated in the introduction. It states that, in the absence of positive reasons to do otherwise, it is reasonable to accept the &lt;em&gt;appearance&lt;/em&gt; of things as being indicative of their actual reality. It is only when new appearances are introduced to us which make the simple reality of previous appearances less likely (called &lt;em&gt;defeaters&lt;/em&gt;) that we should doubt the direct reality of the phenomena we experience. Crucially, it is not the &lt;em&gt;mere possibility&lt;/em&gt; of a contradictory appearance that should make us doubt everyday, non-defeated appearances, as in the logic of the skeptics; it is the presence of an actual defeater for a particular appearance that is necessary. Therefore the general possibility of hallucination or dreaming does not undercut all one’s experiences by itself — one must have a reason to think that some particular experience one is having is a hallucination or dream. This fundamental difference from the skeptics is what allows those who embrace the principle of phenomenological conservatism to defeat external world skepticism in one single stroke: namely, that in all of the experiences I have, there appear to be objects external to me, a whole world of them, and while I may from time to time have reason to doubt a particular external object or whatever, that does not mean I must doubt all appearances. Thus, I can be reasonable in my starting assumption, based on appearance, that the external world does in fact exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons why this is a necessary, almost unavoidable starting principle. In the first place, since all we ultimately have to deal with is appearances, and our goal is primarily to describe, document, navigate, and predict those appearances, right out of the gate we have a strong reason to take the phenomena presented to our awareness at face value: something is happening that appears a certain way to us, and it is that appearance that has the most immediate and, in the absence of anything else, important effect on us; we have to figure out what to do about it, how to deal with it, and taking it at face value for what it is is a start. If it appears to me that a truck is bearing down on me while I’m crossing the street, it doesn’t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; matter whether the automobile is truly there or not — in the end, acting as if it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; there is going to be the better plan. If it turns out it isn’t, better to investigate why the appearances I was presented with were wrong after the fact, than to doubt in the moment, when I need to get on with life, and possibly get run over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is not always the case; for instance, when dealing with some mental condition which causes frequent hallucinations or paranoid fantasies, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; acting on those appearances is probably going to be better than acting on them, in the long run. But the crucial fact here is that generally speaking a person with such a condition is in fact aware of it, and aware of the harm they do to others and themselves when they act on every appearance that occurs to them. Oftentimes, additionally, it is possible for them to differentiate between real and unreal, at least after the fact, because the elements of their illusions are fundamentally unusual and nonsensical when compared to the rest of their experience and the more constant appearances of things. Therefore there are defeaters in place here whereas they are not in place in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason that the principle of phenomenological conservatism is a reasonable starting point is based in more abstract notions of correct reasoning. Essentially, as a general rule, one should not accept the truth of a proposition without sufficient reason to think that it is true. To reject this proposition is, by the law of the excluded middle, to accept its opposite: that it is acceptable to believe any proposition, whether it has sufficient evidence for its truth or not. To choose that route (the route of the epistemic nihilist) obviously makes all epistemology impossible, even pragmatist epistemology, which is not a particularly useful stance, but moreover, it presents the would-be epistemic nihilist with a two-horned dilemma: either they must reject internal consistency and allow themselves to be hypocrites, who accept some propositions and reject others (including their opposites) on the basis of nothing at all, or they must reject internal consistency in the process of trying to avoid such hypocrisy, by following their rule consistently and believing all propositions, even contradictory or nonsensical ones, since they don’t need evidence to choose what to believe. Thus, believing that a particular appearance is untrustworthy without a defeater to contradict it is a violation of sensible reasoning, and commits one to an incoherent and untenable path into intellectual destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final reason is that ultimately, all of our reasons to doubt appearances appeal to appearances themselves. The reason the skeptic doubts the veracity of the information given to them by their senses is because they have from time to time had appearances that were contradictory, which cast doubt on the truth of what they sense. Thus we are all already, in a sense, waiting for defeaters to come along and tell us not to trust appearances; the only difference is just in how sensitive some of us are to those defeaters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that we should believe everything that seems true to us in spite of everything. For one thing, this limited, weak version of the principle of phenomenological conservatism does not say that &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; proposition is &lt;em&gt;justified&lt;/em&gt; by the appearance of truth, as the stronger version does, because I don’t think those arguments work very well. Instead it merely proposes the appearances of things in our experience as a starting point to work from; therefore propositions that are not directly statements about objects of our experience do not gain the benefit of this principle, and it is still our duty to investigate to try to discover evidence for propositions we want to hold true by looking for experiences that confirm them, or defeaters that undercut them. This is a principle of phenomenological conservatism for things we experience alone, not for all propositions, because the appearance of an experience aligning with a proposition is different than simply a proposition that one has an intuitive inclination toward. So one is not justified, for instance, in believing that there is a god until someone disproves its existence simply because one has been brought up in a religious culture and it seems inherently likely that there is a god; one must first have had some kind of experience with a god, and must then deal with all of the defeaters for there being a god (for instance, the lack of the supernatural more generally, the lack of need of gods to explain things, even most religious experiences) before one can be rationally justified in accepting the appearance of a god.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-why-induction&quot;&gt;4. Why Induction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When operating in the world, we are forced to take action whether we are certain in our beliefs about the world or not — the entire condition of our existence is that of being forced to act on the basis of what we guess or think about the world, to deal with uncertainty and to have the courage to act despite it. Induction is, in essence, merely a reification of that principle: although no reasoning can directly support or substantiate induction without first assuming it (as Hume showed), since we have no other information about how the world will effect us, and what experiences it will present to us, than the experiences it has given us in the past, our best bet is to attempt to derive the best picture we can of the world based on those past experiences. Fortunately, induction is a self-correcting process: if our expectations, based on past experiences are wrong, and the world actually appears to us in a different way than we were led to expect, then we need only either correct our expectations, by either learning how these contrasting experiences can be subsumed under the same principle, thereby granting the weight of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of our past experiences to a new guess, or come up with a new principle and reinterpret our older experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, there is no real reason to expect that such a process wouldn’t work. After all, there is no &lt;em&gt;prima facie&lt;/em&gt; reason to assume that the default state of the world is endless chaotic flux, always changing, perhaps in need of some lawgiver to subjugate it, instead of assuming the opposite, that the inherent nature of the world is that of a clockwork machine that proceeds according to orderly laws. Actually, there is no possible benefit to navigating the world at all to assume the former, whereas there is a chance of benefit in assuming the latter. For, if I choose to believe that the universe is chaotic, then I will constantly be confused and adrift whether it is or it isn’t because I will have nothing to go on, not even my past experiences, and therefore no ability to even &lt;em&gt;guess&lt;/em&gt; what happens next; whereas if I choose to believe that it is orderly, then I will be constantly foiled if it is chaotic, but able to act sensibly if it is not. This is the core reason that everyone, even those who deny induction, ultimately cannot help but act as if induction is true: they have to act, and acting on the basis of nothing is guaranteed to only have a random success rate, whereas acting on the basis of past experience at least conceptually has some chance of having a higher-than-random success rate. One can represent these choices with a payoff matrix:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Universe: Chaos&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Universe: Order&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Assume: Chaos&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Assume: Order&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This necessity of acting on the basis of induction in order to survive and reason, whether one thinks it is justified or not, is what I call the property of &lt;strong&gt;performative basicness&lt;/strong&gt;. There are some things which one cannot discard no matter how much one doubts it or views it as baseless, because to discard it is either phenomenologically &lt;em&gt;impossible&lt;/em&gt;, such as the fact that there is some &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; which is thinking and experiencing things, which I typically identify with “myself,” or so completely impractical that attempting to do so is a form of mental or physical suicide — such as induction. To cease to act on any basis at all, to just act randomly because there is no certainty that anything one knows about the past will hold for the future, will quickly lead to problems, as one drinks bleach, walks out into traffic, and so on. The reason that doing those things sounds ridiculous is because inductively we know that they are a bad idea, but if you truly discard induction there is no reason to expect that they &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; actually harm you! Notice that the property of performative basicness isn’t a justification &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;. Instead, it is an observation that we cannot honestly and in good faith leave some things behind, that they are a necessary part of our existence, and so it is better to acknowledge their existence, catalog them, use them if they’re useful, and try to reduce the number of things that we think we can’t leave behind so that our chances of being wrong about things are minimized (since there is no guarantee that just because something is performatively basic, that it is actually accurate to reality).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, there is another thing to consider: all else being equal, the default assumption should be that nothing has changed. That should be the null hypothesis, as that is the simplest assumption to make: when introduced to something, nothing needs to happen, no new concept or element needs to be added, for it to stay the same. Meanwhile, for something to change, that introduces two entities: the thing before the change, and the thing after. There can be reasons to reverse this assumption, as to assert it absolutely would be to bring a Principle of Sufficient Reason into play without due justification, but again changing and staying the same are at least equally likely, and one of them is a bit less complex. This, however, should be dealt with more in the next section, on the principle of parsimony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-why-the-principle-of-parsimony&quot;&gt;5. Why The Principle of Parsimony&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle of parsimony, more commonly referred to as Occam’s Razor, might, at first blush, seem to be a rather arbitrary statement of theoretical preference. Why &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; multiply the entities involved in a theory beyond what is strictly necessary? After all, there is no law of the universe saying that everything has to be as simple as possible to produce the experiences necessary. If we look deeper, however, it quickly becomes clear that the principle of parsimony is a deeply integral part of any consistent and rational attempt to build theories about anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first factor that makes the principle of parsimony necessary is a probabilistic one. Because there is no such thing as certain knowledge outside one’s own head, any proposition not about incorrigible phenomenological experiences has a non-zero chance of turning out to be wrong. Therefore, the more propositions are required to describe a theory, the greater the probability that the theory will turn out to be incorrect.  Therefore, &lt;em&gt;ceterus paribus&lt;/em&gt;, we should favor theories that require few propositions to describe, in order to minimize our chances of being wrong. This factor can be overcome, however, if the propositions you are using in your simpler theory are more probably wrong than the propositions you use in a more complex one, such as would be the case if they either were worse descriptions of experience, made worse predictions, or led to worse predictions (through referred truth). It is important to clarify, here, that when I’m talking about probabilities, I’m using them in a compound sense to refer to a combination of Bayesian credence-probability, accuracy of description, and percentage of possible worlds, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in the sense of frequentist probability that relies on past experiences. Therefore, the probability of a proposition being incorrect relies on the possibility that there are other worlds that would produce the same experiences that led be to construct that proposition, for which that proposition is not true, the accuracy of how well that proposition describes the experiences it is supposed to be about, and how well it fits with other propositions known to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second factor that makes the principle of parsimony a good starting point for theory-building is that it is a natural starting point at the limit. In other words, when starting to build a theory about some phenomena, you can either start at the simplest end of the spectrum, a theory composed of a single proposition, or you can start at the other end of the spectrum with an infinitely complex theory composed of an unlimited number of propositions. The one end of the pole is represented by the principle of parsimony, the other the logical conclusion if you believe that theories should be arbitrarily complex. If you start at the simpler end, then you can build up complexity as needed, as prediction failures require you to increase the complexity of the theory, while if you start at the other end, there can be no justification for decreasing the number of propositions involved in your theory, besides the pragmatic one that it’s too hard to do and so fewer propositions are needed — but that’s an argument for the principle of parsimony too, since if complexity making theories difficult to conceptualize or use is a factor in the practicality of a theory, then trying to make a theory as simple as possible while keeping it functional is the natural conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third factor is that the &lt;em&gt;entire point&lt;/em&gt; of developing a theory in the first place is to simplify: to find an underlying principle behind many diverse propositions, in order to make the world navigable, instead of treating each experience as a totally separate and unique event which can be filed away as a proposition but not linked to anything else. Thus, inherent in the very concept of pragmatic epistemology, and epistemology in general for that matter, is simplification: finding the principles that underlie things. If you’re going to deny the principle of parsimony, for consistency’s sake you have to give up knowing or guessing anything whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important implication of the principle of parsimony is that a theory should be parsimonious not just in its description, but in its implications. A theory that has a lot of implications — that makes a lot of predictions, in other words — that have not yet been verified and confirmed to be in accordance with it, is a theory that is very likely to make a prediction wrong, since each prediction has a chance of being wrong because some detail of the theory matches many areas in past and future experiences but not all. Therefore, theories with wide-ranging implications are to be preferred only if those implications can be, and are, verified to be accurate — in which case those implications add to the likelihood of the theory, since the more of past experiences it explains the more future experiences it is likely to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many subsidiary practical reasons to favor a simpler theory, as long as it is capable of explaining the same data, over a more complex one. For one thing, a more complex theory is more likely to be contradictory, to have hidden assumptions, and to have logical errors. The larger a theory grows, the greater these chances, get, so a theory that is more complex than it absolutely needs to be should be looked at with suspicion. In a similar vein, a larger and more complex theory is more unwieldy, meaning it is more difficult to generate predictions, and even more difficult to make sure the predictions one gets from it actually follow from it. Since I am pursuing a pragmatic theory of epistemology, these considerations should certainly count for something!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other ways to measure the complexity of a theory than counting the number of propositions required to describe it. These ways will ultimately &lt;em&gt;reduce&lt;/em&gt; to that, which is why they are pretty much equivalent in justification, but depending on the circumstances they may be a lot easier to actually check than breaking down your hypothesis into symbolic logic and then into basic propositions (where conjugated propositions count as multiple). I’ll make a table, with each entry in order of relative weight in one’s consideration. The distance between the weights is exponential of some variety, but the specific distance between the weights will change depending on the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Justification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Entity type number (&lt;em&gt;ETN&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The number of types of entities&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;It often requires a huge amount of statements about things to introduce a new type of entity&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Type complexity (&lt;em&gt;TC&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The complexity of the types of entities required&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;This is merely an expression of a feature the former&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Phenomenological distance (&lt;em&gt;PD&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The distance between the appearance of how things work, and how they are supposed to work in the theory&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Appearances are all we have to work with by default, so introducing more distance between experience and theory introduces room for error as the two diverge&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Entity number (&lt;em&gt;EN&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The number of entities&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;It requires more statements about the world to add new entities&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since all of these have to do with different components of the overall propositional complexity, then you can either sum them up or multiply them (as the case requires for the individual aspect) without fear of double-counting. IF there are any other aspects of the complexity of a theory that are left out, you can also add those in. In essence, then, you can look at the complexity of a theory as a mathematical equation, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/assets/math1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then just add in any variables or values you should to capture other parts of the propositional complexity not dealt with by the variables in the table above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful though, as I will explain later, the mathematics to be found in this essay are &lt;em&gt;strictly&lt;/em&gt; for clarifying my words. It is impossible to come up with non-arbitrary numeric values for most of the variables I’m talking about anyway, so the attempt to do so, in order to actually do the algebra, would just multiply and reproduce any mistakes you’ve made, and give a false sense of precision and accuracy. It is better to treat each variable as a vague quantity, or a value with substantial error bounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-kinds-of-predictions&quot;&gt;6. Kinds of Predictions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are assessing the success or truth value of a proposition on the basis of how well it predicts experiences, it is necessary to have a clear idea of what exactly is meant by prediction. The prototypical case of prediction, the one that is primarily used in science, is the &lt;em&gt;ex ante&lt;/em&gt; prediction. To put it in experiential/pragmatic terms, an &lt;em&gt;ex ante&lt;/em&gt; prediction is a proposition about a certain experience of its subject which describes certain details of that experience before that experience takes place, typically along with some indication of how that experience might be generated, how it can be observed, or when it will occur. For instance, “if you touch the stove while it is on, you will get burned.” An accurate prediction is one which, to borrow from William James for a moment, creates an experience of recognition in a person who is first given the prediction and then exposed to the subject of said prediction. If one is not surprised by the experiences which one’s actions or existence relative to a subject generates (surprise being the opposite of expectation/recognition), than this implies that any reasoning or planning one made on the basis of one’s expectations will also be confirmed, which is what allows one to act and plan, since if one expects certain outcomes if one thing happens, and other outcomes if another does, then one can act towards making one or the other of the outcomes happen in order to get positive experiences, and if this leads to expected outcomes, then that means the planning worked, and if this is consistently possible then planning is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another type of prediction is &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; prediction. This is a much more tricky kind of prediction, because it works by deriving your theories from experiences that are already available, which means that it is all too easy to create a &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; theory. An &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; theory is one that is randomly thrown together with no actual predictive power beyond the data that was given for its construction, because it presents either no underlying principle, or an underlying principle that is actually inaccurate and then jam-packed with exceptions in order to fit past experiences, indicating the need for more exceptions in the future and therefore obviating its predictive ability. A stronger attention to the principle of parsimony, and careful attention to avoiding making exceptions or stretching the truth in order to make a theory fit, is needed for &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; predictions to actually confirm a theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most common mistakes made when &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; predictions (predictions of experiences already available to the one constructing the theory) are used to evaluate a theory is to confuse a theory being &lt;em&gt;compatible&lt;/em&gt; with some experience occurring with a theory that &lt;em&gt;predicts&lt;/em&gt; some experience. A theory needs to not just be able to be made to fit with some experience, it actually needs to predict that experience as being more likely than any relevantly different experience — only if that is the case is the theory actually any good for producing &lt;em&gt;ex ante&lt;/em&gt; predictions, which are the kind that are actually useful. A theory that predicts all experiences equally, with a non-zero probability for each, or a too-wide range of experiences with equal or nearly indistinguishable probability, is a theory that actually provides no useful information about how to set our expectations &lt;em&gt;ex ante&lt;/em&gt;, and therefore no useful information about how to act or live, while it can be fit with nearly any experience after the fact because it “predicts” nearly any experience. For instance, pretend someone handed you a black box with a button on the side and a screen on top that displayed a single digit number. Which “theory” about how the box works would be the most useful to you: one that said that the box had an 80% chance of showing a 1, a 10% chance of showing a 2, and a 10% chance of showing anything else, or a theory that said that it could show the digits 0-9? Assuming it is correct, the first theory gives you far more actionable information, while the second theory tells you very little. However, the first theory is more likely to be wrong, in that it would be more difficult to reconcile it with some experiences over time with the box, while the second theory could pretty much be reconciled with any experience of the box, but it tells you basically nothing. Thus for an &lt;em&gt;ex post facto&lt;/em&gt; prediction to actually &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; a prediction of a theory, that theory has to actually be able to make strong predictions. The weaker the differentiation between all its outcomes, and the more predictions a theory makes about the same event’s outcome, the weaker it “fitting” with an event is as evidence for it. This is why omnipotent, deities, for instance, are really not great as explanatory theories: they don’t really predict any outcome any as more likely or possible than any other, and are compatible with any outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-putting-it-all-together&quot;&gt;7. Putting it All Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we have two components: the principle of parsimony, and the principle of induction. The principle of induction indicates the likelihood of a theory being predictive (“true”) given a list of past experiences, by saying that the probability of a theory being true is related to the confidence with which that theory predicted past experiences that actually happened. If the theory predicted something that happened confidently, that should increase one’s credence in it,  in proportion to the confidence; if it predicted something that did not happen, one’s credence should decrease in accordance; and if the theory didn’t predict something that happened to the subject which the theory was about, that should be counted as it having predicted with complete confidence that that thing wouldn’t happen, which should be a fairly serious blow to it. The principle of parsimony indicates the inherent improbability of a given theory, the hurtle that must be &lt;em&gt;overcome&lt;/em&gt; by the theory’s predictive power in order for one to lend credence to a theory — where, as the predictive power of the theory grows over and above the inherent improbability, one’s credence rises as well. Importantly, then, the &lt;em&gt;default&lt;/em&gt; position should be not lending any credence to any particular theory at all. This is because to make any positive statement about something is to risk being wrong, and therefore to set one’s expectations wrong, which can lead to committing to courses of action that will lead to disappointment or even harm. This is also because accepting one theory before it has risen to its “burden of proof” (overcome its inherent improbability) would require, for consistency, one to accept all theories — all infinitely many of them! This of course would be both mentally impossible, and lead to contradictions, as well as being only slightly better than accepting random theories as far as setting expectations goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To formalize all that I said in the previous (large) paragraph, we can adopt Bayes’ Theorem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://wikimedia.org/api/rest_v1/media/math/render/svg/87c061fe1c7430a5201eef3fa50f9d00eac78810&quot; alt=&quot;Bayes' theorem&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;em&gt;P(A | B)&lt;/em&gt; refers to the probability that the theory (A) is true, given the fact that some experience (B) was had — i.e. the credence one should have in A after B happens. Likewise, &lt;em&gt;P(A)&lt;/em&gt; refers to the prior probability of the theory, A. Before any evidence is added to the mix to get induction working to confirm or deny A, this is equal to the negation of the complexity of A, since the probability of A starts out smaller in proportion to its inherent improbability. &lt;em&gt;P(B)&lt;/em&gt; is the probability of the experience happening at all. And &lt;em&gt;P(B | A)&lt;/em&gt; is the probability (the confidence) with which the theory predicts the experience that is being added to the pile of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theorem is applied recursively: for each no experience, the &lt;em&gt;posterior&lt;/em&gt; probability of A is calculated given that that experience happened, and then that becomes the &lt;em&gt;prior&lt;/em&gt; probability of A for the next time we get a new experience relevant to the theory, since it the posterior probability represents the new level of credence we have in A after the experience B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should actually clarify something I said above: the prior probability of a theory is not &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; 100% minus the complexity of a theory. That would imply all kinds of strange things, especially since the default needs to be &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; believing in a theory and that would imply that even before any evidence, if a theory is simple enough we should have a high credence in it. Instead, credence should start out at 50% — essentially agnostic to the truth or falsity of a theory, and then the complexity of a theory should (through some log function probably, to avoid an absolutely zero starting credence for a non-infinitely complex theory) subtract from that starting credence value. So something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/assets/math2.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, in order to have the probabilities weigh against each other proportionately, instead of having the complexity weigh less than it should, each adjustment of the evidence in favor of a theory should also be decreased by the corresponding (reversal of) the logarithm of the complexity of the theory. That way the inherent improbability of a theory is weighed equally against the probability benefits that evidence brings to it, but this does not lead to a zero or negative prior probability, or to positive evidence weighing against the theory. To sum this up in a verbal way that doesn’t require mathematics: you should never start more than agnostic to a theory, either in the positive or negative direction, but your starting places should be heavily informed by how complex the theory is to start with; and positive evidence should always weigh in a theory’s favor, but it should weigh much less in favor of a more complex theory than a simpler one that also predicted that evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-a-fuzzy-table-of-values&quot;&gt;10. A Fuzzy Table of Values&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that the mathematical expressions given for the various components of my epistemology above are intended to clarify what I am describing verbally, and are not intended to be used strictly, since quantifying many of the properties those equations use into constants would be pretty much impossible, and, beyond a certain general sense of (usually relative) size, doing so would be an exercise in arbitrary number games. Nevertheless, it is occasionally helpful to have a more exact sense of the relations of the quantities involved than informal verbal argument can usually provide, without resorting to specific numbers and ending up in the weeds. Additionally, having a preset system of categories in which to place your probabilities, which then have a consistent set of relations between them, is helpful in applying a consistent estimation of the probabilities involved across different theories; it doesn’t eliminate the subjective factor, but it is a servicable crutch in avoiding it as best as possible. Therefore, I propose to introduce what I call “fuzzy values.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, &lt;strong&gt;fuzzy values&lt;/strong&gt; are things that work &lt;em&gt;sort of&lt;/em&gt; like numbers, except that they are incapable of the exactitude of actual numbers. They act almost like labels on ranges of numbers, instead, but are defined relative to each other so that the whole group of labels, the whole classification system, can slide up or down on the actual number scale according to the conceptual needs of the problem. I will introduce the particular values of this fuzzy value system in a table:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symbol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relation Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Extremely likely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Very likely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;μ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Somewhat likely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ν&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Somewhat unlikely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4800&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ψ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Very unlikely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ω&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Extremely unlikely&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;230400&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point values here indicate that it takes twelve very unlikely events in a row to make an extremely unlikely event, four somewhat unlikely events in a row to make a very unlikely event, four somewhat likely events in a row to make a somewhat unlikely event, twelve very likely events in a row to make a somewhat likely event, and one hundred extremely likely events to make an only very likely event. This scale is chosen for its intuitive properties in both frequentist and Bayesian interpretations of probability. I made it roughly symmetrical, so that each increasingly likely probability has about the same relationship to the previous one as the other probability with a similar adjective in front of it. Given the above, fuzzy probability calculus is defined by two axioms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/assets/math3.png&quot; alt=&quot;fuzzy probability calculus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for example, the probability of twelve specific very likely events happening in a row is &lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;^12 = &lt;em&gt;μ&lt;/em&gt;, somewhat likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-conclusion&quot;&gt;9. Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, pragmatically speaking, an epistemology that is best designed to manage the inherent complexity of the world, and the inherent need of humanity to act in spite of it, is a form of empiricist Bayesianism. I would like to point out that, although much of what I’ve said here might sound scientistic, in that I am focusing on sense experience and predictive capability instead of absolute true or deductive reasoning, I am not taking the methods of modern science as a dogma, or even as inspiration. In fact, I would argue that substantial areas of science actually don’t use methods like the ones I describe — although it would be much better if they did — nor are they even aware of the epistemic foundations that their practical work is implicitly based on (or the lack of such foundations, as the case may be).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a follow-up article, I intend to cover the implications of this epistemology for various areas, including logic, mathematics, reasoned argument, and so on. So if you have any questions about what the implications of my definition of truth and my method for arriving at it are for the rest of epistemology, wait for that!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><category term="epistemology" /><category term="pragmatism" /><summary type="html">1. Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Possession Versus Absentee Property</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/01/pvp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Possession Versus Absentee Property" /><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/01/pvp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/01/pvp.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I’m just going to try to explain, as succinctly as possible, the important differences between possession and absentee property (generally just referred to as “property” by Proudhon, e.g. “property is theft”). I’ve covered this distinction several times before, but I think I’ve boiled it down enough that creating a self-contained blog post for it is relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone’s possessions are the material objects that they regularly or semi-regularly use or occupy. Such things might include my home, my car, my tools, my clothes, etc. Possessions can also include things that are purchased with the intention of use, as long as they are actually used within a reasonable timeframe, and the things that someone produces by their labor time, which are generally “in their possesion” right after they make them. Possession is a practical category, negotiable with those around you; it is an extension of one’s autonomy, as it represents the sphere of actions that one can take without effecting others or without requiring their permission, and allows for some independance, self-sufficiency, etc. Respending the product of someone’s labor protects their autonomy as it prevents someone else from having authority over them. Possession is a gift granted by everyone else in society in return for reciprocation, in order to ensure the prosperty and autonomy of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Property is generally the product of one’s labor time alienated in material objects (the Lockean definition). Property can also be possessions, so I use the term “absentee property” to refer to property that is not also one’s possession: things that one does not intend to sell, nor to use oneself. Because of this, absentee property is not an extension of one’s autonomy in a direct manner: defending it neither protects one’s sphere of free action, one’s independance from the community, or anything else. Instead, absentee property extends someone’s autonomy by granting them control over something that only &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; people use, granting them authority over those people by extension. Therefore, absentee property extends someone’s autonomy in the same way that a dictator’s territorial claim extends his: in his ability to tell other people what to do and to back it up with force. The only difference in this case is that absentee property still represents the product of someone’s labor time, either produced directly by their labor or paid for by their labor. Absentee property is, however, a greater detriment to the autonomy of others than taking it is a detriment to the owner, and the owner of absentee property can still be paid for providing it to those who actually use it, paid for their risk and opportunity cost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><category term="anarchism" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Going Back to School</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/31/afraid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Going Back to School" /><published>2021-12-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/31/afraid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/31/afraid.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s New Year’s Eve. I’m sitting on the couch, sunlight falling in slanted lines across my legs, browsing on my phone. My right eyelid is twitching constantly, and it’s extremely distracting. It’s been doing it since yesterday morning; I think it’s the stress. You see, that first sentence only describes what my body has been doing. The crucial part, the part that’s generating the stress, is what’s going on inside my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m scared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably way more scared than I should be, but that just comes with the territory when you’ve got an anxiety disorder. I’m going back to campus in six days. In six days, I’m going to have to get up at 4 o’clock in the morning, Uber to San Francisco, and embark on an eight hour series of flights to the other side of the United States. That’s actually not what I’m scared of, but it sure as shit doesn’t help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In eight days, the school semester starts. Although my headaches are far, far better than they’ve been, they’re certainly not gone, and what might be worse, I took the last semester off, so I’m out of practice buckling down and working on assignments, taking notes, etc. That’s not what I’m scared of, either, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, I’m scared of two other things: the loneliness, and losing my new-found self. The first fear makes all-too-much sense; the second one makes no sense at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time I was on campus, I was extremely lonely. Yes, I was a member of three clubs that met regularly, a D&amp;amp;D group, and E House. Yes, I went to classes in person and chatted with the people there. Yes, I had a room-mate. But there’s a distinct difference between seeing human faces regularly, and actually knowing people. I think everyone who’s grown up in a city knows what I mean — it’s unnervingly easy to be &lt;em&gt;completely alone&lt;/em&gt; even in a sea of faces, and it’s even possible to be that alone among a group of people who you see repeatedly. There’s some kind of strange, diaphanous membrane that wraps you like cellophane when this happens: you can touch others, hear them, speak to them, but you can’t &lt;em&gt;touch&lt;/em&gt; them, &lt;em&gt;hear&lt;/em&gt; them, or &lt;em&gt;speak&lt;/em&gt; to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a barrier that I’ve never really learned to cross in the real world. Online, I have a slightly easier time making friends that I don’t feel this disconnection from. People who I share real emotional bonds with, call regularly, talk even more often with, share my interests with. But even then, it’s a tough process. And in the meantime, I feel &lt;em&gt;alone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isolated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On campus last time, this isolation slowly began to wear me down. I didn’t realize it at the time, but looking back that was an incredibly painful experience. I floated back and forth between classes like a spirit unable to find its final resting place. Lost, alone, not knowing it was dead yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to feel this pain again. I still feel it, but in a way it helps to have my dad around, and on top of that at least there’s nobody around besides him to really remind me of my inner isolation. I know if I go back to campus, it will hurt worse if I don’t do something different. But what? For the life of me, I don’t know the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought was clubs — find a group of people who are not just interested in the same things I am, but who are &lt;em&gt;like me.&lt;/em&gt; Don’t think so much about choosing clubs for academic purposes this time, choose them for social ones, right? And now that I’ve realized I’m a member of the LGBTQ+ community, that should be easier, since even if there aren’t clubs for cishet white men to meet and socialize, surely something like that must exist for minority groups? No such luck, though. Clubs at Penn State are almost bizarrely focused on academic pursuits. That’s not really surprising, based on what I’ve seen before, but still, that leaves me with no real plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m afraid I’ll end up isolated again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second, equally immediate and frightening fear is that I’ll lose myself, lose &lt;em&gt;Alexis&lt;/em&gt;, when I go back. It’s a fear that keeps recurring: what if, when I go back to doing this thing that I used to do before I got my concussion and then subsequently found myself, I’ll lose the new version of myself that I uncovered? What if I’ll go lose this colorful, hopeful, beautiful new vista of identity that I worked so hard to uncover, this (metaphorical) land of uncertainty? What if I go back to being the pervasive vague unease, disquiet, and dissatisfaction that permeated my life before now? The varying stages of disassociation and depersonalization that I unconsciously found (and still find) refuge in to get away from those feelings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if I lose Alexis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That won’t happen. I know it won’t happen. The very fact of my fear and unease about this happening is what &lt;em&gt;proves&lt;/em&gt; it won’t, in a sense. But yet it terrifies me. I felt this fear about returning to writing a lot regularly too — still feel it a little, in fact — and although my fear was proven unfounded, somehow it is springing up again anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fear is tied to something else that’s been happening lately that scares me, even though it isn’t related to going back to college: what I’ve been calling “Man Moments.” Moments when I actually like how I look as a man, conceptualizing myself as one, etc. They’re not predicated on my masculinity, exactly, and they’re much rarer than the days when I have dysphoria over being a man, but it’s still strange and a little concerning, and I worry that this might be a sign that I’m not really a girl, or shouldn’t transition, or something, even though I really want to be a girl and transition. In fact, just yesterday, I got so excited at the idea that I might have breast buds soon from HRT that I got giddy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagining hypotheticals really isn’t helping here either. At this point I’ve pretty much spent all the time that is useful laying back and trying to picture what it’ll be like post-transition, and because it’s not real and I’ve trod that mental path so many times, my brain is kind of numb to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. No conclusion, nothin. I just needed to vent a little.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cops, Vigilantes, and Protection</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/29/protection.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cops, Vigilantes, and Protection" /><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/29/protection</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/29/protection.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a fine line between the defense of oneself and others, which is proper to anarchistic relations, and the exercise of authority which (when unleashed) is paradigmatic of police. This is not to say that there is a fine line between reciprocal anarchistic relations and the state’s jackbooted enforcers — that is not the case at all, those two things are poles apart. Instead, this is to say that the line where one steps from non-hierarchical, anarchist relations with others onto relations of authority and hierarchy which &lt;em&gt;will eventually&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;at their most extreme,&lt;/em&gt; lead to statism and police, is difficult to trace in the case of defense. In this essay, I’ll try to explore where that boundary is, as part of my ongoing attempts to approach reflective equilibrium and understand my anarchism better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with a description of what it is that police do. Police, as agents of the state, are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;, despite what pig propaganda would have you believe, tasked with defending the citizens.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Their job is also not to prevent crime, resolve conflicts, or keep the peace.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Education, economic equality, social aid, and similar things are &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; more effective in preventing crime and keeping neighborhoods safe, and introducing police into a situation is a surefire way to escalate a conflict. Even if police “end” a conflict by arresting some or all of those involved, that’s often merely a band-aid on a situation that has much deeper roots, roots that will cause it to bubble up again and again unless someone deals with the real cause of the conflict. This is all because the real task of the police is to be the armed enforcers of the state’s will: their only job is to punish people for disobeying laws. You can picture this like attempting to force a rigid mold onto something, brutally chopping off any of the parts that don’t fit, squashing others, all so that it’ll fit this arbitrary shape. The state has a list of rules it wants everyone to follow, and any disobedience is an offense to it that must be punished for no other reason than that the laws were disobeyed. Some of these laws have to do with protecting people — laws against murder, for instance — but that is certainly not the majority, and even those are enforced purely because they are laws, with an eye to social control, not with actual care as to whether they actually make anyone safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point, then, is that the police do what they do independent of what &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; wants — independent of what the community wants, and independent of what the people involved in the situation want. They are there to force things to go a certain way, and will use any means necessary to do so. This is why we should fear police: ultimately, everything they say is backed up with a gun, and chances are they’ll get away with using it, too — any attempt at accountability is laughable on a systemic basis when this kind of unilateral authority is handed to an organization. There is no counter-balancing force; there are the police, and that’s it. There’s no balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, protection is a necessary good. No matter how economically equal everyone is, no matter how educated, there will always be those who will try to hurt others. To some degree, this protection can be directly satisfied with self-defense, security, and direct conflict resolution between the parties to a conflict.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I think it will be useful to outline what I mean here, as these are by far the simplest cases, the farthest on the spectrum from police authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firearms are the great equalizer, obviating physical size, strength, and even reflexes to a significant degree. If everyone is armed, committing most crimes would be a terrible idea, more so in fact that in a society that relies on police for protection, since by the time the police arrive most crimes that require self-defense are already long since over, and police do not have a good track record in solve such crimes so most criminals get away with it. To quote the old adage, “an armed society is a polite society.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cases where there is more ongoing, slow moving conflict, where in-the-moment self-defense is not needed, if people were less reliant on the state to determine how things “should” go, mediators would likely be all that is necessary. Both sides likely want to avoid conflict, as that is expensive, risky, and dangerous, and so naturally it would make sense to either try to solve the conflict on their own, or consult with a third party that they trust to make fair decisions that are beneficial to all. This has the added benefit of it being possible to address the root causes of conflicts, as well. Instead of only the proximate conflict being prevented, completely to the detriment of one side or the other in most cases, the interests of &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; sides would be represented equally, so the interests of the person starting the conflict will have to be considered and some concessions will have to be made for them. The force backing up any decisions made in an attempt to solve a conflict will be the capacity for self-defense, the defense of their own interests, of both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cases where someone wants to &lt;em&gt;prevent&lt;/em&gt; a conflict from arising, or protect something other than their person, locks and other similar security measures are usually enough to deter most thieves and vandals, and this is what most people rely on even when police do exist anyway. That need not change in an anarchist society. Pretty much the only time such passive security measures will not work is in the case of absentee property ownership, where someone else regularly occupies or uses whatever one is trying to defend, or in the event that someone is really determined to get something. In the first case, that’s probably something that should not be defended from its actual possessor, then, and in the second case, that’s what security cameras, and then a follow-up attempt at conflict resolution as described above, are for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if self-defense and its accompaniments are not enough? There are such cases. For instance, it can be very costly, debilitating, and problematic to have to constantly deal with possessions being stolen and/or destroyed, and having to seek out the perpetrators for restitution and resolution to the conflict. Alternatively, you could be dealing with someone gathering up superior numbers in an attempt to enforce their will on you — gangs, mobs, etc. In these cases, something more structured, communal, and robust is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the concept of vigilantes might come to mind. If there is no state, no central authority to determine whose acts of force are legitimate and whose are not, it is possible that individuals might take defending others’ interests into their own hands. If a pedestrian sees another person being mugged, for instance, or someone breaking into someone else’s house while they’re out grocery shopping, they might, if they were so inclined, attempt to stop that person. If someone sees another person attempting to exercise authority over others, growing a gang to enforce their will, and so on, they might be motivated to gather up allies to put a stop to such nonsense. This might sound like the anarchist’s dream: distributed, individualist, stigmergic action in order to maintain harmonious anarchistic relations. However, there are features of this sort of interaction that should be examined further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the first two examples, the vigilante is starting to act a little like a cop. Specifically, they were asked to do what they did by &lt;em&gt;neither&lt;/em&gt; of the parties actually involved in the conflict, and it really didn’t have anything to do with them. The victim might be glad that they stepped in to help, but alternatively they might not, and there is no way to find out beforehand. Moreover, since the vigilante does not consult with the victim’s wishes before they step in, they cannot be a representative of the victim’s will — instead they are enacting their own will. That’s not something that’s inherently bad, especially if they are trying to prevent violations of autonomy, but it is still a dangerous line to step across. Vigilantes also fall victim to many of the same problems as cops. Because they do not know the context of the situation, and are likely only interested in solving the immediate conflict at hand, they are at best a band-aid on a root cause which will bubble up again later, when they aren’t around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the third example, however, things area  little different. Someone trying to set up authority effects everyone in the area (the ‘community’), so someone gathering up people to try to organize a resistance to it is much more legitimate. It’s something they should have a say in anyway, and if others disagree with what should be done they simply don’t have to be involved. In this case, the vigilante is representing themselves still, but that is fine because they are not stepping in on behalf of a set of people that actually doesn’t include them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, vigilantes in the real world often spend the majority of their time focusing on enforcing The Law:tm:, or stopping immediate conflicts, instead of actually trying to protect people or solve problems. This is partially because everyone in modern society has had the idea of ‘the law’ and its ultimate authority so ingrained in their heads that it is difficult to think outside that paradigm, but also because that is actually the approach that vigilantism actually lends itself to most naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if self-defense and passive security doesn’t always cut it, and vigilantes are a mixed bag at best, what is the most consistently anarchist way to handle protection? Obviously, as I’ve said before, one should not attempt to plan, or predict, what an anarchist society will look like with absolute certainty. Nevertheless, I have two solutions which I favor. I talk about them at some length in &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/10/27/reciprocity.html&quot;&gt;‘Two Principles of Anarchism’&lt;/a&gt;, so you can read more about the abstract notion there. Here, I’d like to instead quote some historical examples directly, from Roderick Long’s great article, &lt;a href=&quot;http://freenation.org/a/f21l1.html&quot;&gt;‘Anarchy in the U.K.: The English Experience With Private Protection’&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t endorse exactly replicas of these solutions, but I like many features of them: they all existed in a large power vacuum where there was no state to back them up, they all worked fairly well for long periods of time, and they all exited in systems that had markets, but were pre-capitalist, and were organized around principles of mutual aid and free association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first solution I present is the idea of ‘crime insurance.’ Briefly, this is the idea that you can sign up to an organization where each member agrees to help you pay restitution for any crimes you commit, and you agree to do likewise. Maybe you all pay into a common pool on a monthly basis, which then you all draw out of when you commit a crime, or maybe the co-payment happens when the crime occurs. Roderick Long describes something similar in ancient England:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Before the Norman Conquest in 1066, government in England was radically decentralized. The King had little or no role in setting domestic policy; this was left to the &lt;em&gt;moots,&lt;/em&gt; local courts that passed judgment in accordance with customary law. The King’s authority lay primarily in the area of foreign policy, and here he acted simply as a war leader, a kind of military entrepreneur, whose followers supplied financial contributions and military service &lt;em&gt;voluntarily.&lt;/em&gt; England possessed neither a police force nor a standing army; law enforcement and national defense alike were the prerogative and responsibility of the armed citizenry.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;For purposes of security, the most important social unit was the &lt;em&gt;borh.&lt;/em&gt; A &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; was an association, typically of twelve people, who stood surety for one another’s good behavior. If a member of a &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; committed a crime, the other members were committed to bringing him to justice — but also to helping him pay restitution for his crime. (Financial restitution rather than retribution was the normal sentence for most crimes; those who refused to pay restitution were outlawed, that is, placed outside the law — meaning that anyone could kill them with impunity.)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; may have originated as a kinship group, but if so, its kin-based aspects soon dwindled; at the height of the Anglo-Saxon system, &lt;em&gt;borhs&lt;/em&gt; were purely contractual arrangements. Individuals were free to apply to a &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; of their choosing, and members of that &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; were likewise free to accept or refuse the applicant; once accepted, an individual was free to leave, and could also be expelled. Since the members of the &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; would be held responsible for one another’s actions, there was a strong incentive to police members’ behavior. Likewise, there was a strong incentive to belong to a &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; and not be kicked out, because few were willing to deal with someone who belonged to no &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt;; such a person was in effect an uninsured risk, since he had no fellow &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt;-members standing surety for him. The &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; system thus created powerful incentives for responsible behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It might be objected that such a system could not work in today’s vast, impersonal, and highly mobile society, where the close ties and personal knowledge required for effective &lt;em&gt;borh&lt;/em&gt; membership are often absent. Reputation, it might seem, can serve as an effective incentive only in a small community where everyone knows everyone else. But the experience of the Law Merchant suggests otherwise: this vast system of private mercantile law that operated via reputation, credit, and economic boycott, was able to regulate commercial transactions across all Europe in the late Middle Ages, among merchants of different nations, without the benefit of either face-to-face interaction or government enforcement. And in the modern information age of instantaneous electronic communications, credit reports, and the like, one might well expect reputation to serve even more effectively as a tool for maintaining social order privately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option, which could exist separately or could be used in tandem with crime insurance associations, depending on what people need, is the mutual protection association. Something similar to this was seen in England in the 1800s:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries, the mutual-aid approach to law enforcement was active in England once again. England had no police force in the modern sense before 1829, when Home Secretary Sir Robert Peel (whence the term “Bobby”) established Scotland Yard for the London area; similar police administrations for other areas followed in the 1830s and 1840s. The classical liberal feminist and social reformer Josephine Butler responded with alarm, penning a ringing denuciation of the budding police state in her book &lt;em&gt;Government by Police.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But before the reign of the Bobbies, English law enforcement relied heavily on organizations known as Associations for the Prosecution of Felons — also known as thief-takers’ associations. Imagine a cross between a Neighborhood Watch group, an insurance agency, and an Old West style posse. People in a particular neighborhood would pool their resources, and supply their own labor, to support their local thief-takers’ association. The association would keep its eyes open for robbers (particularly those who robbed houses displaying the plaque of association membership!). If a crime (against an association member) did occur, the association would hunt down, or pay to have hunted down, the wrongdoer, often cooperating with similar associations in other districts — and then use the pooled resources to pay for the felon’s prosecution in a government court. (Criminal justice was not free in those days.)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The traditional English system — with its roots in Anglo-Saxon antiquity, but extending as recently as the nineteenth century — is worlds away from the modern system of centralized police and gun control. Under the old system, every able-bodied male citizen was in effect a policeman, and the behavior of these policemen was regulated not by government edict but by the laws of economic self-interest. Despite important differences in details, both the &lt;em&gt;borhs&lt;/em&gt; and the thief takers operated according to the principle of &lt;em&gt;mutual assurance&lt;/em&gt;: individuals pooled their resources and effort for the purpose of mutual protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own ideas for mutual protection associations differ in some relatively significant details from these old thief-takers’ associations — for instance, their services would have to be directly called in by the people subscribing to them, and they would be governed by the decisions of their members in a vote, etc — but there are enough relevant similarities as well that some idea of how these things would work can be gathered from the quotes above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/28/politics/justices-rule-police-do-not-have-a-constitutional-duty-to-protect.html &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/how-we-rise/2021/05/19/7-myths-about-defunding-the-police-debunked/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I cover what the difference is between self-defense and an exercise of violence and subordination in &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/12/19/relations.html&quot;&gt;‘Anarchistic Relations’&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><category term="ethics" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moral Persuasion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/27/non-cog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moral Persuasion" /><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/27/non-cog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/27/non-cog.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my previous article on egoism, &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/12/08/egoism.html&quot;&gt;‘An Introduction to Anarchist Egoism,’&lt;/a&gt; I stated that all normativity ultimately breaks down to desire, and therefore that moral statements are expressions of desire alienated from their actual origin and source of force (the individual), or, secondarily and derivatively, prescriptive statements about what one will allow oneself or others to do. This highlighted the inherently subjective and individualistic nature of morality, and how it gets its ultimate power from a sort of egoism focused on satisfying these desires. However, following on from that, I reaffirmed that, even though this is the case, it is still possible to persuade people using moral language. In this essay, I want to elaborate on why I think moral persuasion is still possible, even if morality is irrevocably &lt;em&gt;subjective&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;egoistic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two primary ways that one can convince someone else of one’s moral propositions. First, to highlight to them a latent desire that they have but which they have not yet identified correctly; second, to explain to them that the natural implications of their desires are other than they thought they were. In both cases, you are ultimately appealing to already existing desires that the other person has, merely clarifying to them something they got wrong about what those desires implied for how they should act, in order to get them to act how &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; think they should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first method is the most difficult, and is made so for the precise reason that it is possible! It is possible for people to have latent or misapprehended values because it can be difficult to determine what our actual underlying values are, and it is therefore &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; difficult to correct people on their misapprehensions, precisely because understanding our own desires is so hard, so understanding the desires of others is even harder. Nevertheless, it can be done. This is probably the most powerful form of moral persuasion there is, and it can be used to bring about substantial changes in how someone believes they should act. It is usually done by carefully analyzing moral hypotheticals, clarifying concepts, exploring real world situations, and so on, in order to uncover the principles behind the moral judgments that people feel compelled to make in different situations, when special pleading and equivocation are cleared away. This is also how one discovers one’s own values too: through what John Rawls called &lt;em&gt;reflective equilibrium&lt;/em&gt; — a process by which one’s moral values and desires are uncovered, processed into principles and rules of thumb, and then, if contradictions or inconsistencies are found, one attempts to change one’s intuitions to rectify those inconsistencies, in order to avoid regret and guilt in future actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second method of persuasion is the easier of the two, since usually what it comes down to is either faulty reasoning (contradictions, exceptions, missed details, etc) or a lack of knowledge of specific factual information. This is why it is often possible to convince other people to join you in doing something merely by outline facts to them, without breathing a word concerning values: values are already shared between you, so it is easy, once the facts are available to both of you, for you to act in sync. This is also why the popular political discourse is so muddled: because it is so often possible, among political tribes, to convince each other (through a shared understanding of their values) while only explicitly stating facts, people come to expect those of other political tribes, who think about their values differently, to be convinced in the same way by the facts presented to them. This is also why moral discourse in general is so often able to rely simply on clarifying and breaking down a situation into clear conceptual components, removing fallacies such as special pleading, and making things consistent: human beings tend to share a much more significant number of values than we generally realize, so, operating on the shared basis of those, it is merely a matter of conceptual clarification, logic, and evidence. There is no need to drill further down into the realm of what someone’s values actually are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further complicate matters, it is possible to create structural distortions of built-in human desires. This is most often done by the culture that we live in and are raised by. For one thing, culture encourages people to interpret certain inherent desires that they have in the same specific set of ways. For instance, for a particularly blatant example, Christian culture teaches people to interpret any feeling of depression, loneliness, or lack of fulfillment, purpose, or meaning, as specifically a “Jesus-shaped hole” in their hearts, instead of a need for those general categories of things that can be satisfied in a wide range of ways. This has an obvious survival advantage for the “meme” of Christianity, which explains the existence of such a cultural idea even though it hinders its followers’ ability to actually satisfy their desires. This is basically moral persuasion of the first kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, culture can be a structural way of doing moral persuasion of the second kind, as well as the first, by convincing us that certain ways are better than others of satisfying certain desires, whether that is true or not. This may not always be something that can be rectified by presenting people with evidence, however. While evidence is usually enough to show someone the right way to go about satisfying their desires for isolated cases of misunderstanding how to do so, cultures usually provide people with &lt;em&gt;matrices&lt;/em&gt; of beliefs and desires that lock each other up, all feeding into each other, so that to get someone to accept facts about how to satisfy one desire might require presenting them with numerous other facts in all sorts of other areas, or new interpretations of what their desires are. This is why ideologies are so monolithic, and often so hard to escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, then, culture is actually the systematic use of moral persuasion — generally in a fallacious and obfuscatory but superficially convincing manner — on whole populations, in order to ensure that they have common norms and that their actions line up. I believe this is how it is possible for people to have such seemingly different value systems, while still being members of the same species with generally similar psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of all this, it can be very difficult to differentiate between one’s base level desires and the distortions and impositions that culture lays over them. This leaves people less happy and fulfilled than they could be, but not knowing how to fix that, or even sometimes that they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; missing out on happiness that they could have otherwise, depending on their psychology. Thus, it is important to at least attempt to differentiate these things, and excise the cultural and indoctrinated distortions overlaid atop one’s understanding of one’s desires, in order to be freed to better understand them, since culture is a meme which need only preserve itself, not ensure the well-being of other people, and can fall victim to sub-optimal equilibria like any other evolutionary product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also why it can be very important to actually &lt;em&gt;listen&lt;/em&gt; to the moral arguments of others, because although they may seem to be making arguments that go against your values (and therefore have no weight for you), it is not exceedingly likely that they will have &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; different values than you do at bottom, so it is possible that you might have a misapprehension about what your basic values are or how to achieve them. Thus, even if one accepts egoism, that does not mean that you should necessarily reject out of hand the arguments of those who do not obviously share your precise values — although there are cases in which values are actually irreconcilable, in which case there is no reason for a moral discussion to happen. For instance, there is no reason an anarchist and a fascist could have for attempting to convince one another of their positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is important to stress at this point exactly how much humans actually share in terms of values. We are, after all, not &lt;em&gt;tabula rasa&lt;/em&gt;, blank slates born to be indoctrinated into the desires of those around us. If human beings didn’t have innate desires, there would be nothing for culture to hook into, no reason for us to act or listen, and, furthermore, no culture in the first place, as culture is a product of humans and so some humans must have had the desire to continue living long enough to create it in the distant past. We are, instead, born with a whole rich toolkit in our minds: for enabling us to learn certain things very fast, for processing things in a certain way… and for desiring certain things. Although we cannot specify with certainty any set of desires which all human beings share, or what exactly the desires that most people share are, we can give general outlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to popular belief, human beings are not actually inherently ‘sinful’ and evil. We are actually, generally speaking, pro-social creatures: we derive happiness from helping others, and are motivated to form social bonds, engage in mutual aid, and treat each other with fairness and reciprocity. We are also motivated to &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; these things of others, such that we will often take the less ‘rational’ choice if it means punishing someone for not treating us fairly, which helps discourage that behavior, thereby making those ‘irrational’ lose-lose choices rare and also avoiding unfair treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human beings generally desire a good balance of stability and change, although where that balance lies exactly can differ from person to person. We generally also desire autonomy, the ability to act on our own and be our own people without the entangling web of obligation and authority, but once we have that autonomy we will, as I mentioned above, tend to seek out society, because autonomy and society are not mutually exclusive: the collective need not be granted sovereignty over the individual to allow social bonds to form, and indeed doing so destroys the natural and mutually enjoyable social bonds that form when people are granted freedom of association and the ability to grow and develop as individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These common values are too vague and general to draw any specific desires or plans of action from; however, they do ensure that there will generally be a substantial overlap of core values between any two people, so that if they are able to drill down past the cultural indoctrination which shapes how they view those values and the best way to achieve them, they will be able to find common ground on which to build a ‘moral’ system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I have briefly outlined the ways in which moral persuasion is still possible in a subjective moral framework. The natural follow-up question is: what can we do when moral persuasion fails? I mentioned before that it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; possible for two people to share completely different, irreconcilable values. It is also possible for the matrix of cultural indoctrination to be too deeply embedded in a person’s psyche to be rooted out by mere argument, or even by demonstration and experience. As I said in my previous essay on the matter, however, this is not really different than conditions which can occur under moral realism: after all, it is possible for someone to be so deeply indoctrinated, or otherwise so committed to their values, that no amount of reasoning will encourage them to see the “truth” of the moral arguments you present to them. It is also possible for them to be equally convinced of another, opposing moral realist framework, and perhaps equally rational in that conviction too, since philosophy of ethics, like any other branch of philosophy, is deep and subtle, broad enough for opposing views to be equally justified within it. Therefore, to reiterate, the moral subjectivist is not really at a disadvantage here in comparison to the moral realist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the moral subjectivist and the moral realist must react in the same way to an irreconcilable interlocutor: they must either attempt to find some way to co-exist with them, or, if their values do not allow that, fight them, impose their own moral will. The only benefit the moral realist has in this area is that, should they choose to fight and enforce their moral will, they can claim a moral “high ground,” saying that the other person was “wrong” and deserved to be subordinated to their will; a moral subjectivist instead must recognize that they are no more justified in their core values than anyone else — core values are brute facts, neither good nor bad in themselves apart from other values judging them. This does not make the moral subjectivist a moral relativist, though! The only justification a moral subjectivist needs to act is the attestation of their own desires, so if their desires include enforcing their moral framework on those who do not share it, so be it. There need not be any term among the values of the moral subjectivist that insists that they leave alone those who violate their values simply because their values are not any more justified than anyone else’s. The moral subjectivist acts to attain their values, acts according to their desires and principles, and there is nothing outside those things to stop them from doing so. This does mean, however, that it is going to be more difficult to find the will to actually enforce one’s values on others; after all, moral realists are motivated to do this by a self-assured belief in their own correctness and the necessity of enforcing that correctness on others, but there is no such belief to encourage the moral subjectivist to acts of moral imperialism. Thus the violation of one’s values — the infliction of harm or suffering or subjugation or whatever else — would have to be great to motivate a moral subjectivist to enforce their will on others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sense, moral subjectivism encourages toleration, but not to the absurd and frankly contradictory degree that moral relativism is often taken to. Being an egoist requires merely that you realize that your moral beliefs are predicated on your desires and not on absolute, objective, universal truths; it does not require you to (necessarily, always) respect the desires of others for that reason.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><category term="egoism" /><category term="ethics" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Property Provisos</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/24/difference-principle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Property Provisos" /><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/24/difference-principle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/24/difference-principle.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the particularly interesting threads from &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/12/19/relations.html&quot;&gt;‘Anarchistic Relations’&lt;/a&gt; that I wanted to follow more was that a set of limitations on property were a natural outgrowth of property based on egoistic reciprocity. To recap:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, if we take the idea that generally speaking people want to be able to satisfy the maximum amount of desires, that conflict is bad for that, and that autonomy is pretty much a prerequisite for desire satisfaction, it seems clear to me that the basis for property “rights” would be in a reciprocal deal to respect the boundaries of others in return for similar consideration, in order to protect  individual autonomy. This is because raising up some boundaries around people protects their ability to act as an individual, to achieve their goals without needing to go to others for permission, and also because having a clear set of norms around that can help with resolving the inevitable conflicts that the infinite extent of our possible desires creates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized, however, that if we base property rights on this sort of “gift” from everyone in society to each other, based on this kind of reasoning, that puts some pretty clear limits on those property rights. After all, if we take them to be the result of a deeper set of interests and values that are at play, than those deeper values will sometimes have to take precedence over property. So far, I’ve discussed two limits on property based on this observation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, as soon as property becomes a tool for the subordination of others, granting it as a gift ceases to serve the purpose of &lt;em&gt;protecting&lt;/em&gt; them from subordination, and so there would be no reason to respect it. This leads to a heavy bias towards possession (occupancy and use) property norms over ones that allow a lot of debt and absentee ownership, since absentee ownership basically only extends the liberty of the owner by dominating and controlling the people &lt;em&gt;actually using&lt;/em&gt; the property, instead of extending the owner’s liberty directly by insuring that they can take individual actions with the property as they see fit (use it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, that if someone already doesn’t have the basic necessities needed to survive, they are not going to have much of an interest in ensuring the protection of what they do have by protecting or respecting that of others. If I’m already going to starve, or I already don’t have a house to call my own where I’m not dominated by others, or a workplace where I am not already essentially a slave, I’m not going to have much interest in respecting the property of the people doing this to me, because I’ve already lost what I would be bargaining for their reciprocal respect of by doing so. This leads to a picture of a society that will, first and foremost, have to ensure that everyone really &lt;em&gt;owns&lt;/em&gt;, has an individual possession of, with no domination attached, the basic necessities of life, and then, once that is done, will then be able to establish something on top of that that’s more rigid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I phrased this second proviso (limitation) on property in terms of Locke’s proviso: it is hard to see a community voluntarily respecting someone’s property rights, as part of a mutually-beneficial equilibrium where everyone’s interests are represented, if they don’t already have “enough and as good” of the basic necessities for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way of describing both of these provisos is through a generalized form of John Rawls’ difference principle. Although I dislike Rawls in general, and how he used the difference principle himself is still pretty dubious, I do think that there is a kernel of truth in it: it really &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; describe something similar to how a rational egoistic actor would think about inequality of material possessions. Here is the principle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Social and economic inequalities … are to be to the greatest benefit of the least advantaged members of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the biggest issue I take with the phrasing here is just the word “greatest.” An egoist would have no reason to support inequality in possessions if it was of no benefit to me, except perhaps to avoid the threat of force, but such an egoist would totally support inequality that &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;overall&lt;/strong&gt; beneficial to them, even if they did not get the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; benefit out of it. Crucially, I bolded the word “overall” there because defenders of capitalism often talk about the billionaire class’s riches actually &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; benefit people, and in a sense they do, but only at the expense of a lot of other things in people’s lives, which means they are, overall, worse off. It’s kind of a “giving with one hand, taking with the other” situation. Lord Bezos giveth, and Lord Bezos taketh away, blessed be His name!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, though, finding a more concise formulation of my two property provisos isn’t why I’m bringing up Rawls. What I really wanted to talk about goes a little deeper. When someone hears me say that property rights don’t really have any claim to be respected until everyone is provided with enough to survive, what they probably &lt;em&gt;hear&lt;/em&gt; me saying is that what we need is the state, or some other organization, to redistribute property from those who have enough to give away, and those who need it to meet the basic minimum needs. And that’s essentially what Rawls got out of his principle, which is very similar to mine, so it’s understandable why you would have that impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not at all where I’m going with this, though. First of all, I think if we eliminated absentee property — property that one is not using as a way to protect one’s own freedom to act as an individual, but is instead using to extend one’s freedom by restricting and controlling the actions of others, because you never actually use it, only make others pay and obey to use it — much of our problems with distribution would be solved stigmergically. With everyone no longer able to lay claim to things they don’t even need and prevent others from using them, those who actually need resources will be able to claim them from those who do not without any kind of organization or centralized authority. They will simply move into that empty apartment, take a few cans of that stored grain that would have rotten otherwise, and so on. We already produce enough of the basic necessities of life to feed, clothe, and house basically everyone, the problem is merely one of having a system that does not permit, or reward, a more equitable distribution happening on its own. Once you fix the incentives, market forces and individual action will take care of the rest, no top-down “forcing” necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t pretend to know how this will be solved on an ongoing basis, though, but I’m sure other anarchist writers have written on this. I do foresee a slight problem, in that if people can just &lt;em&gt;take&lt;/em&gt; what they need, and you can’t horde things, there might be less of an incentive to produce as much as we do in the first place. There still would be an incentive, though, because if you don’t have the power of the state protecting you, you kind of need to start caring about what the “underclasses” and the public think, because all of your “rights” are on the line if you go far enough. Moreover, contributing to a minimum safety net for society voluntarily ensures that it is available for yourself as well, should you fall on hard times, so there will be an incentive to contribute to whatever pool there is for supporting people who can’t work so that people have an interest (through reciprocity) in supporting you should you be injured or fall on hard times or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, though, although my logic here might &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; similar to that of statists praising the welfare system, there are crucial, important differences. First of all, I do not think that having a centralized body with the power to give and take property at will is the right way to solve this, &lt;em&gt;precisely because&lt;/em&gt; my logic for supporting these redistributive provisos rests on the fact that there is no such agency in society, and also because the existence of such a thing implies domination of one institution over everyone in society, their property on loan by its benevolence, instead of horizontal balance between the interests of everyone in society. Additionally, my logic for this kind of libertarian socialist welfare “system” is logic endorsing a purely voluntary system. When a statist says “I want redistributive welfare so that if I fall on hard times there will be something for me” it is not on reciprocal logic that they rest this statement. They are not saying that they want to give a gift so that others will be willing to return the favor should they need it, which is what I was saying above. They are saying that they want to be able to point a gun at everyone else in society and &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; them to contribute to something, not just themselves, and they don’t want &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; involved to have a choice, so that they can unilaterally ensure that, if something goes wrong for them, they have a backup plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I’m starting to sound like a socialist, that’s because I am! Anarchists, even individualist anarchists, have &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; been socialists, and always will be. We are just a different kind of socialist than the state socialists and communists that you usually find under that label. That difference is crucial, because it shows our commitment to individualism and liberty, but you shouldn’t lose sight of the important similarity in our goals. To quote Gary Chartier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is good reason to use “socialism” to mean, at minimum, some-
thing like opposition to:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;bossism&lt;/em&gt; (that is, subordinative workplace hierarchy); and&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;deprivation&lt;/em&gt; (that is, persistent, exclusionary poverty, whether resulting from state-capitalist depredation, private theft, disaster, accident, or other factors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Socialism” in this sense is the genus; “state-socialism” is the (much-to-be-lamented) species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are goals that all socialists share, whether statist or not, and for all my individualism, my anarchism, and my affinity for markets and the private ownership of the means of production, these are, still, among my goals as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><category term="politics" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="egoism" /><category term="rawls" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Hayekian Argument For Occupancy-and-Use</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/21/hayekian-usufruct.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Hayekian Argument For Occupancy-and-Use" /><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/21/hayekian-usufruct</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/21/hayekian-usufruct.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occupancy-and-use is the term given by anarchist theory to a vague collection of property norms focused around the idea that the right&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to use a thing, to determine what happens to it, and determine the conditions of its transfer, etc, should be assigned to those who &lt;em&gt;actually do&lt;/em&gt; use (or occupy, a form of use that has to do with spacial location) that thing. Of course, the range and extent of this bundle of rights, as well as what counts as actual occupancy or use, is up for debate and compromise, but that is simply the nature of anarchism: any too-rigid set of rules will of necessity not be adapted to the particular situations and needs of the people that are to follow them, and so will not rationally and willingly be obeyed by them, instituting another form of subjugation, requiring either force, authority, or indoctrination. No set of rules, not even one that claims to be moral, can be absolute, &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/12/08/egoism.html&quot;&gt;can be placed over the interests of individuals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many arguments as to why occupancy-and-use norms are preferable to others. Against collectivism and communism, occupancy-and-use allows individuals to have a sphere of action within which they have autonomy, independance from others, the ability to do things and live without the need to get the permission, or have the involvement, of anyone else. To quote Proudhon, in this sense, property is “a breastplate of [an individuals’s] personality,” protecting  them from “the incursions of [their] fellows.” Against private property and absenteeism, occupancy-and-use insures that each person actually has what they need to ensure their individuality, their extrication from others, and that no one can assert their dominance over things that are not necessary for them to do this, but which others need for that purpose. It does this by ensuring that those who actually use something, whether for production or for shelter, or for other things, are accorded the right to use it without the need to pay tribute to, or obey the dictats of, any other person. Occupancy and use are important here precisely because actual use is the most important indicator of whose autonomy and individuality it serves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go into more detail, but I think I have already elaborated on the reasoning behind these two points in enough detail in other places (see: &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/10/27/reciprocity.html&quot;&gt;‘Two Principles of Anarchism’&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/12/09/not-ancap.html&quot;&gt;‘Why I Am No Longer an Anarcho-Capitalist’&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbdp-web.github.io/blog/2021/12/19/relations.html&quot;&gt;‘Anarchistic Relations’&lt;/a&gt;). In this article I want to elaborate on a point that I have used concerning worker cooperatives, but which I think can be used more precisely, and with even more effect, in the context of distributing ownership to individuals. This has to do with the Hayekian conception of tacit, or distributed, knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Hayek, the market is superior to a centralized, planned economy, because it allows each person to make use of the specific knowledge they have about their situation and the particular materials they have to work with in order to move production forward. By distributing the information processing between people, and letting people with the best knowledge of each particular situation take charge of that situation, the market can use more knowledge, and make &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; use of it, than a central planner could. After all, even if all that tacit, local, distributed knowledge &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; even be communicated to a central authority, it would be quickly overwhelemed by the sheer volume of information, let alone the task of coming up with the huge volumes of complex comands it would have to distribute out to all points of the economy. To quote from &lt;em&gt;The Use of Knowledge in Society&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The peculiar character of the problem of a rational economic order is  determined precisely by the fact that the knowledge of the circumstances of which we must make use never exists in concentrated or integrated  form but solely as the dispersed bits of incomplete and frequently  contradictory knowledge which all the separate individuals possess. The  economic problem of society is thus not merely a problem of how to  allocate “given” resources—if “given” is taken to mean given to a single mind which deliberately solves the problem set by these “data.” It is  rather a problem of how to secure the best use of resources known to any of the members of society, for ends whose relative importance only  these individuals know. Or, to put it briefly, it is a problem of the  utilization of knowledge which is not given to anyone in its totality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, however, notice that the strength of this argument hinges on the people who are actually using and producing things — means of production, materials, etc — getting to decide what to do with the things they have, and communicating through the price system so that the relevant bits of their local knowledge are incapsulated and communicated instantly to others, who are motivated &lt;em&gt;by&lt;/em&gt; the price system to change their actions. Nowhere in this does the capitalist, or the landlord, come in! The capitalist is not using their capital, and often knows little about the specifics of how it is applied. They are not the ones actually on the ground directing the use of the property used in production, with local, tacit, distributed knowledge about things relevant to that. They just obtain rent in return for &lt;em&gt;letting&lt;/em&gt; other people do all that. To quote again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we can agree that the economic problem of society is mainly one of  rapid adaptation to changes in the particular circumstances of time and  place, it would seem to follow that the ultimate decisions must be left  to the people who are familiar with these circumstances, who know  directly of the relevant changes and of the resources immediately  available to meet them. We cannot expect that this problem will be  solved by first communicating all this knowledge to a central board  which, after integrating &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; knowledge, issues its orders. We must solve it by some form of decentralization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This criticism of “central boards” also applies to the boards of corporations, capitalists or groups of capitalists, etc. The fact that they do not have to integrate &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; knowledge does not mean that they are aware of the knowledge relevant to the use of the property they lay claim to, or could integrate all of that knowledge and use it effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course decentralization — or, as I prefer it, &lt;em&gt;distribution&lt;/em&gt; — is just one piece of the puzzle: “the ‘man on the spot’ cannot decide solely on the basis of his limited  but intimate knowledge of the facts of his immediate surroundings.” There needs to be a way to communicate encapsulated distributed information in a way that allows people with local knowledge to gain just enough information to act in light of the local knowledge of others, without actually &lt;em&gt;having&lt;/em&gt; that local knowledge. This is what the price system is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is in this connection that what I have called the  “economic calculus” proper helps us, at least by analogy, to see how  this problem can be solved, and in fact is being solved, by the price  system. Even the single controlling mind, in possession of all the data for some small, self-contained economic system, would not—every time some small adjustment in the allocation of resources had to be made—go explicitly through all the relations between ends and means which might possibly be affected. It is indeed the great contribution of the pure logic of choice that it has demonstrated conclusively that even such a single mind could solve this kind of problem only by constructing and constantly using rates of equivalence (or “values,” or “marginal rates of substitution”), &lt;em&gt;i.e.,&lt;/em&gt; by attaching to each kind of scarce resource a numerical index which cannot be derived from any property possessed by that particular thing, but which reflects, or in which is condensed, its significance in view of the whole means-end structure. In any small change he will have to consider only these quantitative indices (or “values”) in which all the relevant information is concentrated; and, by adjusting the quantities one by one, he can appropriately rearrange his dispositions without having to solve the whole puzzle &lt;em&gt;ab initio&lt;/em&gt; or without needing at any stage to survey it at once in all its ramifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, &lt;em&gt;prices&lt;/em&gt; represent an encapsulated quantitative representation of the relation between means and ends, values, of the entire market. As such, they can be used to calculate the best use of things. Here, again, all that is required for the price system to work is a single price, at the point of sale; economic rent (ongoing, recurring, indefinate prices on things) is of no help to this. In fact, because it is indefinate, economic rent might actually be a hindrance to relating all the values of the individuals in a market together, since it might make some values appear infinate, introducing a sort of singularity into the calculation. This, again, is an argument for only allowing prices &lt;em&gt;at the point of sale&lt;/em&gt;, when use transfers from one person to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another fun point: economic rents encourage the separation of means and ends in the price system by inflating the cost of means relative to their actual cost in terms of alternate ends given up. After all, for the price system to work as it is “intended,” the price of means must come down to labor and scarcity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the one hand, people ask for payment for things because they want to be compensated for their labor time. This is for two reasons: payment for labor time is a compensation for not doing other possibly profitable things that could have been done with that time, and it is compensation for the inherent disutility of labor (it being unpleasant). Therefore, the price of a means partially represents the ends that could have been served if a different means had been made in the first place, or even none at all.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the smaller the amount of something there is, the more reluctant people are to give it up, because they have more important uses to put it to still than if it was more plentiful. In weighing the use of means for different ends, then, the price of the means partially represents the other ends the means could have applied to.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic rent makes that first signal artificially high, because instead of being a finite compensation for a finite amount of labor, it is an amortized, ongoing cost, not proportional at all. Economic rent also distorts the second signal involved in pricing means, because it makes things seem artificially scarce: if people aren’t calculating the price of something based on whether they actually need to keep it to use it, which is how their subjective ends get factored into scarcity cost, that messes with things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, there are good market-oriented, subjectivist, pragmatic reasons that occupancy-and-use should be seriously considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;By “right” here, I am not talking about natural or moral rights, but the sort of right generated by communal recognition and reciprocity — i.e. rights on the “gift economy” of social relations. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><category term="mutualism" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ontology of Being Trans</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/20/being-trans.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ontology of Being Trans" /><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/20/being-trans</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/20/being-trans.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-introduction&quot;&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out I was a few months ago. Since then, a lot of things have started to make a lot more sense than I did, and I’ve been happier with myself, and who I am, than ever before. I’ve been taking quick strides towards becoming the woman I want to be, too, and it’s been exhilerating, if also a little frightening. As I’ve gone through the process of learning what it means to be trans, and interacting with the community more, some of the things I said in my previous article on transgender people, back in September, are starting to look wrong. Or at least, incomplete. With my new perspective, I think it’s time to go back and revise some of the things I said. Most of the research I did was good, and I still stand by it, but a lot of the stuff around it requires some revisiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-science-and-trans-people&quot;&gt;2. Science and Trans People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that I would like to say is that medicalization of genderqueer people is not really a good thing. Although the neurological and other studies can be helpful, the important thing to remember is that because gender is a phenomenological experience, until we are capable of mapping the brain out and inspecting its contents with enough fidelity to figure out &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; inherent traits of personality and identity — which I highly doubt it will ever be possible to do thanks to the inherent complexity and black-box nature of neural networks — attempting to decide gender based on brain scans is only marginally better than phrenology. Additionally, the gendered characteristics of the brain that we are even capable of looking at fall into a bimodal distribution even for cis people: some cis women’s brains fall within the range more commonly associated with male brains, etc, meaning that it would be totally possible for a trans woman to &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; have a brain that looks more like a cis man’s. It’s all about probabilities, and probabilities admit of exceptions — exceptions that are often more common than you’d expect, and deserve respect and concern. Furthermore, since being transgender is a psychological thing, medicalization is just a concern in general. Excessive medicalization of other mental illnesses is also a problem; while psychiatry does help, it is best if it is encapsulated in more holistic methods, and I think this is true for being transgender as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should also add that my focus on binary trans people in the previous article was unfortunate, and not even warranted by the studies I was using, which, being bimodal and probabalistic in nature, make the existence of brains which exist at a neutral point in the binary, or even outside of it entirely, a complete possibility. Leaving aside those studies for the reasons I mentiond, just as feeling that you are another gender than the one you were assigned at birth is valid if you pick the opposite gender, or a gender that already exists, I really don’t see why there would be any reason why new genders can’t exist either. After all, gender (I’ll get to this later), exists on thousands of nuanced dimensions, and the two particular instances we have now aren’t even really “real,” just what we happened to arrive at, and they’ve been different throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, I don’t think an excessive scientific study of trans people is particularly helpful to begin with. Because psychological/phenomenological phenomena are necessarily not repeatable or inspectiable, not things you can break down, dissasemble, study, and reproduce, non-social science will never really be able to capture it. To attempt to do so, scientists would have to create imperfect proxies that &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; testable and repeatable and so on, and that then leads to the danger of treating those not as &lt;em&gt;indications&lt;/em&gt; of being trans, but instead as &lt;em&gt;definitions&lt;/em&gt; of being trans, especially with the tendency of people to quote and use science they don’t really understand for their own purposes. This is why I actually think that any kind of neurological or physical study of why people are transgender &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; wait until social sciences, psychology, and trans care are much more mature, and society has accepted us more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-gender-gender-roles-gender-expression-and-gender-identity&quot;&gt;3. Gender, Gender Roles, Gender Expression, and Gender Identity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender appears to be a social construct: a collection of roles (usually two, but &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; always) that are developed through historical and socio-cultural forces, and then assigned to people. These roles include ideas about how you should act, what social roles you should fulfill and how you should do so, how you should relate to others, how you should dress, even how you should think. Crucially, no one property determines gender; everything exists on a sliding scale and for every categorization that can be arrived at there are clear and widely-agreed-upon exceptions, both in the relation between sex and gender, and in the designation of what gender someone is. Thus it is best to define gender in terms of a set of properties that can be more or less satisfied, and which in total &lt;em&gt;add up&lt;/em&gt; to something closer or farther away from a definition, instead of a rigid set of properties all things of one gender must share. (This is actually true of all definitions, in my opinion, as I am not a fan of any kind of essentialism). In essence, then, gender is really a high-dimensional latent space, and gender &lt;em&gt;roles&lt;/em&gt; are the specific areas in that space that society deems “standard” or “normal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These “gender roles” appear to have varied extremely widely throughout history, which indicates that they are not biologically determined. Nevertheless, people are drawn to each role as it most naturally fits them, in the way that people are often drawn to other things they have innate talents in or affinities for, which are also biological determined (sue me, I’m a physicalist). Generally, the biological sex of a person effects their minds and therefore their personalities, and makes a certain point in the space of latent gender space work for them. This is what we call “gender identity:” the desire to exist at some point of the gender latent space. Basically, gender roles are at least partially constructed based on the two most frequent points on the bimodal distribution of gender identities (which is based on the bimodal distribution of biological sex traits for the mind), and since biological sex traits for the body tend to correlate strongly with those of the mind, those are associated with those roles as well, and used to guess someone’s gender identity. The fact that there are only two gender roles, it should be stressed, is due to an imperfect reification of the bimodal nature of biological sex differences, not to anything inherent. Just like if we made two rigid roles in any other area of society people would reluctantly sort themselves into them, if we allowed more gender roles it would better map onto what worked for people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biological sex itself is a very complicated thing, however, and people are capable having mixes of the characteristics manifesting in different areas. Thus, isible, external, physiological sex traits do not correlate perfectly with the internal ones that lead to gender identity. Therefore, for every sex characteristic that “every” member of the gender roles has, you can find a well-documented exception. For instance, there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://rarediseases.org/rare-diseases/swyer-syndrome/&quot;&gt;cis women with XY chromosomes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/conditions-and-diseases/gynecomastia&quot;&gt;cis men with breasts&lt;/a&gt;, the list goes on. One example of this is trans people: people for who the biological sex determiners that are externally visible would normally be correlated with a personality that would be suited for one gender role, but the mind developed in such a way that it was actually suited for a different point in the space of genders. Since bodily sex characteristics are typically (absent this malfunction) correlated with gender identity, the brain structure expects accompanying traits, but doesn’t find them. Hence, typically speaking, trans people will experience various states of distress that their bodies aren’t as they would be to ideally align with their minds. Also, because their minds are oriented toward a particular point in gender space, they’ll typically experience great satisfaction and happiness from getting closer to that. And because gender is stretchy and fluid already, it is certainly possible for someone with a certain gender identity to fully embody their desired gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, however, a lot of gender has to do with how someone things, acts, and interacts with others, and those can be satisfied by gender identity directly; insofar as people don’t act in line with the gender associated with their identity, it is usually because they are being forced not to, and so it is a game or lie. Just as a woman pretending to be a man is still acting/thinking/etc like a woman, just simulating doing it like a man, or vice versa (for any pair of genders you like), the same is true for trans people even if they don’t “act” their gender. In this way, a lot of the most important components of someone’s gender is already determined by someone’s gender identity. In fact, part of being a certain gender is wanting to be that gender and achieve it, and gender identity satisfies this property as well. Hence the “wanting to be an X is a symptom of being X”, where X is a gender, saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed it could be argued that the most important part of any gender is the mental, social, psychological part, and the rest (presentation, etc) is just icing on the cake; in that sense, someone who has a gender identity is pretty much already entirely that gender. And since everyone already satisfies a certain gender role “more or less” and not completely, someone is not really that much less of a certain gender just because it’s only an identity so far and they haven’t been able to express it much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll add that there is a lot more here I could talk about, especially about how gender roles are formed, but I feel like the whole analysis would get totally out of hand. To summarize:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gender&lt;/strong&gt; is a high-dimensional latent space, where different properties relevant to gender are mapped onto different axes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mental traits are the most important dimensions in determining gender, because other traits (physical, social) have so many exceptions and are so vague and complex. For further illustration of why mental traits are the most important, try to think about what is actually the most important about the different genders. Is a man really reducable to his penis? A woman her uturus? Hardly. Furthermore, to take an extreme case, note that when, for instance, in comics, someone’s brain is taken out and put in a robot body, they might mope about not having the physical characteristics of their gender anymore, but they still get referred to with the pronouns of their gender and still pretty much think of themselves as that gender and act that way. It therefore makes sense to think of people, &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; personality, not just &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; body, as being gendered, and of course what determines what you are as a person (other identities and traits that pertain to your personhood) is what is in your mind — e.g. in this case, gender identity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biological sex is very complex, and can be inconsistent or completely non-binary throughout the body, including the brain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The way the brain developes based on biological sex determines personality, which determines which point in the gender latent space people function best in. This is &lt;strong&gt;gender identity.&lt;/strong&gt; This is usually aligned with the biological sex of the rest of the body, but not always. Sometimes particular things are off, sometimes it’s a brain/body split, sometimes it’s a chromosomes/everythign else split, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Because the way biological sex effects the development and the way normal distributions work, the distribution in gender space of gender identities is bimodal. Because of this, societies tend to pick two points in the gender space that relatively satisfy one of the the two most common points in the distribution of gender identities more (that picking is determined by many factors). These become reified as &lt;strong&gt;gender roles.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The external manifestations of biological sex are also bimodal, and mostly correlate with &lt;strong&gt;gender identity&lt;/strong&gt;, but because biological sex can be inconsistent this is not always the case. However, because these two usually correlate, societies use external manifestations to assume gender identity, and thereby assign gender roles, and this &lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; works (unless the gender roles are not actually very well mapped onto even the bimodal distribution, which is often the case, and how you get sexism, etc). In cases where the assigned role is completely different than the identity, someone is &lt;strong&gt;transgender&lt;/strong&gt;. This can be because a different already-existing role works for them, or because they want to be on a completely different point in the gender space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Someone can be closer to or farther away from a certain point in gender space (a gender role) on a lot of different axes, and because of the amount of exceptions and complexity of gender, it is possible to move where you are on that space by changing expression, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Additionally, since the most important axes in gender space are already mental/psychological,[^1] and gender identity is a mental/psychological phenomena that basically determines the gender of the mind, having a certian gender identity basically gets you most of the way to being a certain gender even without changes in expression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, no, trans people aren’t “crazy.” We’re aware, all too aware, that we don’t satisfy the physical characteristics of our desired gender role, of what our biological sex is, etc, we’re not claiming counterfactuals. We are voicing the fact that a different gender role than the one we’ve been assigned would be far better for us (we’d be more functional and happier), and that it’s possible to adopt a gender because physical characteristics don’t just simply map onto a gender binary and definitions aren’t essentialist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-neopronouns-and-xenogenders&quot;&gt;4. Neopronouns and Xenogenders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that all of this analysis is completely agnostic to how many genders there are, what they are, what constitutes them, etc. In fact, I’m totally happy to invent new genders, as long as they actually correlate somewhat to a gender identity and the axes that gender space has. This is why I’m more than happy to accept non-binary people, xenogender stuff, etc. And since pronouns are just a shorthand way of referring back to someone based on their gender (to allow for increased reference capacity), having as many pronouns as their are relatively standardized gender roles makes total sense to me, so neopronouns are really cool. (Although, personally, a system that had pronouns based on the relative order the nouns were originally referenced in makes way more sense to me, something like how certain programming languages do arguments for lambdas).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexis</name></author><category term="lgbtq" /><category term="ontology" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">1. Introduction</summary></entry></feed>